<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text>
<header
		manual-title="Old Testament 2022 Come, Follow Me—For Sunday School"
		audience="adult-teacher"
		copyright="2021"
		usage-years="2022"
		standard-work="old-testament"
		edition="original"
		era="come-follow-me">
	</header>
<chapter type="cover">
<heading>OLD TESTAMENT 2022</heading>
<heading>Come, Follow Me—For Sunday School</heading>
<heading>Living, Learning, and Teaching the Gospel of Jesus Christ</heading>
</chapter>
<chapter type="title-page">
<heading>OLD TESTAMENT 2022</heading>
<heading>Come, Follow Me—For Sunday School</heading>
<heading>Living, Learning, and Teaching the Gospel of Jesus Christ</heading>
<p>Published by
The Church of Jesus Christ of latter-day Saints
Salt Lake City, Utah</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="copyright">
<p>© 2021 by Intellectual Reserve, Inc.
All rights reserved.
Version: 8/19
17091 000
Printed in the United States of America
Comments and corrections are appreciated. Please send them, including errors, to ComeFollowMe@ChurchofJesusChrist.org.</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="teacher-help">
<heading>You Are a Teacher in the Church of Jesus Christ</heading>
<p>You have been called of God to teach His children in the Savior's way. You were set apart to this calling by the authority of His holy priesthood. Even if you are not an experienced teacher, as you live worthily, pray daily, and study the scriptures, Heavenly Father will grant you the influence and power of the Holy Ghost to help you succeed (see 2 Nephi 33:1).</p>
<p>Those entrusted to your care are Heavenly Father's children, and He knows what they need and how best to reach them. Through the Holy Ghost, God will guide you as you prepare and while you are teaching. He will reveal to you what you should say and what you should do (see 2 Nephi 32:5).</p>
<p>The essential purpose of gospel teaching and learning is to deepen conversion to Heavenly Father and Jesus Christ. Your goal as a teacher is to help those you teach do all they can to become more converted — an effort that extends far beyond class time. Invite those you teach to actively participate in learning about Jesus Christ and His gospel and to act on what they learn. Encourage them to make their individual and family study outside of class the primary source of their gospel learning. As they act in faith by studying as individuals and families, they will invite the Spirit into their lives, and it is the Spirit that brings about true conversion. Everything you do as a teacher should point to this sacred objective.</p>
<p>Teach only the doctrine of the restored gospel of Jesus Christ as found in the scriptures and the words of latter-day prophets. Pure doctrine — eternal, unchanging truth taught by God and His servants — invites the Spirit and has the power to change lives.</p>
<p>The calling to teach is a sacred trust, and it is normal to feel overwhelmed at times. But remember that your Heavenly Father called you, and He will never forsake you. This is the Lord's work, and as you serve "with all your heart, might, mind and strength" (Doctrine and Covenants 4:2), He will enlarge your capacities, gifts, and talents, and your service will bless the lives of those you teach.</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="teacher-help">
<heading>Using Come, Follow Me—For Sunday School</heading>
<heading>Preparing to Teach in Sunday School</heading>
<p>Personal and family study at home should be the center of gospel learning. This is true for you and for those you teach. As you prepare to teach, start by having your own experiences in the scriptures. Your most important preparation will occur as you search the scriptures and seek the inspiration of the Holy Ghost.</p>
<p><i>Come, Follow Me—For Individuals and Families</i>is an important part of both your personal study and your preparation to teach. It will help you gain a deeper understanding of the doctrinal principles found in the scriptures. It will also enable you to inspire and invite class members to use<i>Come, Follow Me—For Individuals and Families</i>to enhance their personal and family scripture study (for help doing this, see "Ideas for Encouraging Personal and Family Study" in this resource). As you do, remember to be sensitive to class members whose family circumstances may not support regular family scripture study and family home evening.</p>
<p>During your preparation, thoughts and impressions will come to you about the people you teach, how the principles in the scriptures will bless their lives, and how you can inspire them to discover those principles as they study the scriptures for themselves.</p>
<heading>Teaching Ideas</heading>
<p>As you prepare to teach, you might gain additional inspiration by exploring the teaching outlines in this resource. Think of these ideas not as step-by-step instructions but rather as suggestions to spark your own inspiration. You know your class members, and you will get to know them even better as you learn together in class. The Lord knows them too, and He will inspire you with the best ways to help class members build on the gospel learning they are doing at home.</p>
<p>Many other resources are available for you to use as you prepare, including ideas in<i>Come, Follow Me—For Individuals and Families</i>and Church magazines. For more information about these and other resources, see the section titled "Additional Resources" in this resource.</p>
<heading>Some Things to Keep in Mind</heading>
<ul>
<li>Gospel learning is most effective when it is centered in the home. As a teacher, you have an important responsibility to support, encourage, and build upon class members' gospel learning at home.</li>
<li>Class members' conversion to Jesus Christ and His gospel will deepen as they understand and apply true doctrine. Encourage them to record and act on the impressions they receive from the Holy Ghost.</li>
<li>Teaching is more than lecturing, but it is also more than simply leading a discussion. Part of your role is to encourage participation that edifies and is based on the scriptures. You should also share the inspired insights you received as you studied the scriptures.</li>
<li>Remember that many class members are having meaningful experiences studying at home the same scriptures that you will be discussing in class. You can support their scripture study by providing them with frequent opportunities to share what they are learning at home.</li>
<li>Heavenly Father wants you to succeed as a teacher. He has provided many resources to help you, including teacher council meetings. In these meetings you can counsel with other teachers about challenges you face. You can also discuss and practice principles of Christlike teaching.</li>
<li>People learn best when they have opportunities to teach. On occasion, consider allowing class members, including youth, to teach a part of the lesson. Base this decision on the needs and abilities of class members. If you do invite a class member to teach, take the time to help him or her prepare in advance by using the ideas found in this resource and in<i>Come, Follow Me—For Individuals and Families</i>. Remember that as the called teacher, you are ultimately responsible for what is taught in class.</li>
</ul>
<p>This resource includes teaching outlines for every week of the year. On Sundays when Sunday School is not held, class members continue reading the Old Testament at home according to the schedule outlined in<i>Come, Follow Me—For Individuals and Families</i>. When Sunday School is held, you may choose to either skip or combine lessons.</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="teacher-help">
<heading>Ideas for Encouraging Personal and Family Study</heading>
<p>Here are some ideas to help you encourage class members to study the word of God at home, both individually and as families. Be sensitive to the fact that not all class members can study the scriptures with their families (for example, some members live alone or in part-member families).</p>
<ul>
<li>Invite class members to share experiences they had studying the scriptures at home. For example, you could ask them to share a verse that impressed them and to explain why they found it meaningful.</li>
<li>Ask class members to give examples of what they are doing to make personal or family scripture study more meaningful. (Some ideas can be found under "Ideas to Improve Your Personal Scripture Study" and "Ideas to Improve Your Family Scripture Study" in<i>Come, Follow Me—For Individuals and Families</i>.)</li>
<li>Invite class members to share how they acted on impressions they received during their personal or family scripture study.</li>
<li>Spend a few minutes showing class members some of the resources provided by the Church to help members study the gospel. These resources include the scripture study helps found at scriptures.ChurchofJesusChrist.org; "Scripture Stories" found at children.ChurchofJesusChrist.org; teaching outlines and other resources in<i>Come, Follow Me—For Primary;</i>youth-focused content at youth.ChurchofJesusChrist.org; seminary and institute manuals; and videos, audio recordings, and images found at MediaLibrary.ChurchofJesusChrist.org. Many of these are also in the Gospel Library app.</li>
<li>Spend a few minutes explaining how to use the Gospel Library app to study the scriptures, including how to mark verses and record impressions.</li>
<li>Invite one or more class members to share how they have taught a specific gospel principle in their families.</li>
</ul>
</chapter>
<chapter type="teacher-help">
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<p>These resources can be found in the Gospel Library app and at ChurchofJesusChrist.org.</p>
<heading>Hymns and Children's Songbook</heading>
<p>Sacred music invites the Spirit and teaches doctrine in a memorable way. In addition to using the print versions of Hymns and Children's Songbook, you can find video and audio recordings of many hymns and children's songs at music.ChurchofJesusChrist.org and in the Sacred Music and Gospel Media apps.</p>
<heading>Seminary and Institute Manuals</heading>
<p>Seminary and institute manuals provide historical background and doctrinal commentary for principles found in the scriptures. They may also inspire teaching ideas for Sunday School classes.</p>
<heading>Church Magazines</heading>
<p>The Liahona and For the Strength of Youth magazines provide articles and other features that can supplement the principles you are teaching from Come, Follow Me—For Sunday School.</p>
<heading>Gospel Topics</heading>
<p>In Gospel Topics (topics.ChurchofJesusChrist.org) you can find basic information about a variety of gospel topics, along with links to helpful resources, such as related general conference messages, articles, scriptures, and videos. You can also find Gospel Topics Essays, which offer in-depth information about doctrinal and historical issues.</p>
<heading>Preach My Gospel</heading>
<p>This guide for missionaries provides an overview of the basic principles of the gospel.</p>
<heading>For the Strength of Youth (booklet)</heading>
<p>This resource outlines Church standards that can help us live the gospel and enjoy the companionship of the Spirit. Consider referring to it often, especially if you are teaching youth.</p>
<heading>Videos and Art</heading>
<p>Artwork, videos, and other media can help those you teach understand doctrine and visualize stories related to the scriptures. Visit Gospel Media at MediaLibrary.ChurchofJesusChrist.org to browse the Church's collection of media resources. Gospel Media is also available as a mobile app. Many images that you can use in class are found in the Gospel Art Book.</p>
<heading>Teaching in the Savior's Way</heading>
<p>Teaching in the Savior's Way can help you learn about and apply principles of Christlike teaching. These principles are discussed and practiced in teacher council meetings.</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="teacher-help">
<heading>A Pattern for Teaching</heading>
<p>Each outline in this resource follows a pattern of inviting, sharing, and teaching the doctrine.</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>As part of every class, invite class members to share insights and experiences they had during the previous week as they studied the scriptures as individuals and families and applied what they learned. Help class members see that their personal learning outside of class is important. Their individual conversion to Heavenly Father and Jesus Christ will come not only through Sunday learning but also through their daily experiences. When class members hear each other's experiences and testimonies of Jesus Christ and His gospel, they are more likely to seek similar experiences of their own.</p>
<p>Not everyone will have read the chapters for each lesson, and even some who did may not feel comfortable sharing. Make sure all class members feel they are a valued part of the class, whether or not they have something to share.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<p>You and your class members should focus on Jesus Christ and His doctrine — the eternal truths of the gospel — found in the assigned scripture passages. As you discuss doctrine from the scriptures, what verses, quotations, experiences, questions, and additional resources might you share? How might you use these resources to help class members discover and understand gospel principles? How can you help them build their faith in Heavenly Father and Jesus Christ?</p>
<heading note="large graphic that needs better details">Old Testament Overview</heading>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<heading type="date">DECEMBER 27–JANUARY 2</heading>
<heading type="ref">Moses 1; Abraham 3</heading>
<heading type="title">"THIS IS MY WORK AND MY GLORY"</heading>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>Members of your class may have had some wonderful experiences reading Moses 1 and Abraham 3 at home. How will you give class members opportunities to share those experiences? It may be as simple as asking questions like these: What impressed you as you read the scriptures this week? What surprised you? What made you stop and think? What helped you feel closer to your Heavenly Father and Jesus Christ?</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>MOSES 1:1–10, 37–39; ABRAHAM 3:22–26</heading>
<heading>As children of God, we have a divine destiny.</heading>
<ul>
<li>The truths revealed in Mose's and Abraham's visions can have a powerful influence on our choices and on our ability to overcome life's challenges. How can you help members of your class discover theses truths in Moses 1 and Abraham 3? One idea is to divide the class into groups and assign each group one of the following passages: Moses 1:1–10; Moses 1:37–39; Abraham 3:22–26. Each group could look for answers to questions such as "Who am I?" "Why am I here?" and "Who does God want me to become?" After sufficient time, the groups could then share their answers. How can these answers influence our daily actions?</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>Christ and the Creation, by Robert T. Barrett</graphics-caption>
<heading>MOSES 1:12–23</heading>
<heading>We can resist Satan's influence.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Moses's confrontation with Satan, found in Moses 1:12–23, holds lessons that could help your class members as they face temptation or deception from the adversary. What can we learn from Moses's response? The video "I Am a Son of God" (ChurchofJesusChrist.org) can help class members discuss one of Satan's tactics — tempting us to doubt our spiritual experiences (see also "Additional Resources"). It might be meaningful if class members shared ideas and encouragement to help each other detect and resist Satan's efforts.</li>
<li>One lesson from Moses's experience is that Satan tempts us with counterfeits of God's truth and power. To help class members visualize this, you could bring to class some objects that are fake versions of other things, such as an artificial plant or a baby doll. How can we tell that these are fake? What are some of the counterfeits Satan uses today to tempt us? How can we recognize and reject them? (To learn how Moses did this, see Moses 1:13–18.) How does the Lord help us in our efforts? (see Moses 1:24–26).</li>
</ul>
<heading>ABRAHAM 3:22–28</heading>
<heading>This life is our opportunity to show that we will do what God commands.</heading>
<ul>
<li>How can you help class members see their lives as an opportunity to prove their faithfulness to God's commands? You might start by asking them to talk about experiences when they had to demonstrate proficiency in a skill — for example, in school, at work, or on an athletic team. They could talk about what they were required to do to prove themselves. How are these experiences similar to what is described in Abraham 3:24–26? How are they different? How do we include Heavenly Father and the Savior in our efforts to "prove" ourselves? (Abraham 3:25). How does knowing that we are here to prove ourselves obedient affect the way we respond to life's challenges?</li>
<li>What else do we learn from Abraham 3:22–28 about the premortal life, or our "first estate"? (verse 26). Why are these truths valuable to us?</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>Don't doubt what has been revealed to you.</heading>
<p>Elder Jeffrey R. Holland taught this about Moses's experience in Moses 1: "Moses' message to you today is: Don't let your guard down. Don't assume that a great revelation, some marvelous, illuminating moment, the opening of an inspired path, is the end of it. . . . Once there has been illumination, beware the temptation to retreat from a good thing. If it was right when you prayed about it and trusted it and lived for it, it is right now. Don't give up when the pressure mounts. Certainly don't give in to that being who is bent on the destruction of your happiness. Face your doubts. Master your fears. «Cast not away therefore your confidence» [Hebrews 10:35].
"Stay the course and see the beauty of life unfold for you" ("Cast Not Away Therefore Your Confidence," Ensign, Mar. 2000, 7, 9).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Help learners discover truths in the scriptures.</b>Before inviting class members to read a scripture passage, you might give them something specific to look for or consider. For example, they could look for something they learn about the Savior or something they would like to share with a family member. (See Teaching in the Savior's Way, 21.)</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<heading type="date">JANUARY 3–9</heading>
<heading type="ref">GENESIS 1–2; MOSES 2–3; ABRAHAM 4–5</heading>
<heading type="title">"IN THE BEGINNING GOD CREATED THE HEAVEN AND THE EARTH"</heading>
<p>In order to prepare to teach, first read and ponder Genesis 1–2; Moses 2–3; and Abraham 4–5, and record your spiritual impressions. Come, Follow Me—For Individuals and Families and the ideas below can help you understand and teach the doctrine in these chapters.</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>God repeatedly declared that the things He made during the Creation were "good" (see Moses 2:4, 10, 12, 18, 21, 25, 31). Invite class members to share good things they found as they read the scriptures at home this week. What was good about the things they discovered?</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>Genesis 1; Moses 2; Abraham 4</heading>
<heading>"God created the heaven and the earth."</heading>
<ul>
<li>Class members may have noticed similarities and differences among the accounts of the Creation in the books of Genesis, Moses, and Abraham. Encourage class members to share what Joseph Smith's translation in Moses 2 adds to our understanding of the Creation account in Genesis 1. What additional insights do we gain from Abraham 4? To allow more people to share, you could encourage the class to do this comparison in pairs or small groups. (Some of the verses that have important differences are noted in "Additional Resources.") How do we benefit from having multiple accounts? What do these accounts suggest about what God wants us to know about the Creation?</li>
<li>When God created Adam and Eve, He gave them dominion over the earth and His other creations on it (see Genesis 1:28; Moses 2:28; Abraham 4:28). How do Doctrine and Covenants 59:16–21 and 104:13–18 help us better understand what it means to exercise righteous dominion over the earth?</li>
<li>A few days before class, you might invite class members to bring pictures they have taken or have in their homes that remind them of the beauty of God's creations. How does learning about the Lord's creative work affect our feelings about Him, ourselves, and the world? Class members could also share what messages they feel God has for us in these accounts of the Creation in Genesis 1; Moses 2; and Abraham 4. Singing or listening to a song about the Creation, such as "For the Beauty of the Earth" (Hymns, no. 92) could help class members feel gratitude for God's creations.</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>Creation, by Joan Hibbert Durtschi</graphics-caption>
<heading>GENESIS 1:26–28; MOSES 2:26–28; ABRAHAM 4:26–28</heading>
<heading>We are created in the image of God.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Why is it important for us to understand that we are created in the image of God? How can you help class members ponder this truth? They could read Genesis 1:26–28; Moses 2:26–28; Abraham 4:26–28; or the second paragraph of "The Family: A Proclamation to the World" (ChurchofJesusChrist.org). How does this truth affect the way we see ourselves, others, and God? Class members could find further insights in hymns such as "O My Father" or "I Am a Child of God" (Hymns, nos. 292, 301).</li>
<li>In the video "God's Greatest Creation" (ChurchofJesusChrist.org), President Russell M. Nelson bears testimony of the miraculous human body (see also "Thanks Be to God," Ensign or Liahona, May 2012, 77–80). Consider sharing this video before reading Genesis 1:26–28; Moses 2:26–28; or Abraham 4:26–28 as a class. How does President Nelson's testimony deepen our gratitude for the truths in these verses?</li>
</ul>
<heading>GENESIS 1:27–28; MOSES 3:18, 21–25; ABRAHAM 5:14–19</heading>
<heading>Marriage between a man and a woman is ordained of God.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Many views on marriage in the world today diverge from eternal truth. To help your class learn about God's views on marriage, you might invite them to read Genesis 1:27–28; Moses 3:18, 21–25; or Abraham 5:14–19 and to list on the board the truths they find. They could add to their list truths they find in "The Family: A Proclamation to the World" (ChurchofJesusChrist.org). Why are these truths valuable to us?</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>Comparing Creation stories.</heading>
<table><thead>
<tr>
<th>Genesis</th>
<th>Moses</th>
<th>Abraham</th>
</tr></thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Genesis 1:1</td>
<td>Moses 2:1</td>
<td>Abraham 4:1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Genesis 1:16</td>
<td>Moses 2:16</td>
<td>Abraham 4:16</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Genesis 1:26–27</td>
<td>Moses 2:26–27</td>
<td>Abraham 4:26–27</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Genesis 1:30</td>
<td>Moses 2:30</td>
<td>Abraham 4:30</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Genesis 2:5</td>
<td>Moses 3:5</td>
<td>Abraham 4:30</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Genesis 2:5</td>
<td>Moses 3:5</td>
<td>Abraham 5:5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Genesis 2:7</td>
<td>Moses 3:7</td>
<td>Abraham 5:7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Genesis 2:9</td>
<td>Moses 3:9</td>
<td>Abraham 5:9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Genesis 2:17–19</td>
<td>Moses 3:17–19</td>
<td>Abraham 5:13–14</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Help learners liken the scriptures to themselves.</b>"The same gospel truths that inspired and sustained Abraham, Esther, Lehi, and Joseph Smith can help those you teach face modern challenges" (Teaching in the Savior's Way, 21). Encourage learners to apply principles they find in the scriptures to their own situations.</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<graphics-caption>Adam and Eve, by Douglas M. Fryer</graphics-caption>
<heading type="date">JANUARY 10–16</heading>
<heading type="ref">Genesis 3–4; Moses 4–5</heading>
<heading type="title">THE FALL OF ADAM AND EVE</heading>
<p>As you prepare to teach about Genesis 3–4 and Moses 4–5, think about what questions or activities might help class members better understand the Fall of Adam and Eve.</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>Class members could briefly review Genesis 3–4 or Moses 4–5, select a verse that stands out to them, and share it with someone sitting nearby. Then a few people could share an insight with the class.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>MOSES 4:1–13; 5:1–12</heading>
<heading>We need agency and opposition in order to grow.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Because agency — the God-given right to make choices is such a fundamental part of mortal life, we sometimes take it for granted. To deepen class members' appreciation for this gift, they could read and discuss Moses 4:1–4. What do these verses teach about the importance of agency? Why would God's plan be destroyed if we did not have agency? The quotation in "Additional Resources" could provide some insights.</li>
<li>Perhaps class members studied President Dallin H. Oaks's message "Opposition in All Things" (Ensign or Liahona, May 2016, 114–17) as part of their individual or family study this week. During the week, you might consider inviting a few people to come prepared to share something from his message that helped them understand the Fall of Adam and Eve (see especially sections I and II). Why does Heavenly Father allow us to experience "opposition in all things"? (see 2 Nephi 2:11–16). You might invite class members to read Doctrine and Covenants 29:39–40 and discuss why Satan's temptations are necessary in God's plan. How do Heavenly Father and Jesus Christ help us when we face temptation?</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>Leaving Eden, by Annie Henrie Nader</graphics-caption>
<heading>MOSES 4:4–12; 5:13–33</heading>
<heading>Satan seeks "to deceive and to blind" us.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Moses 4:4–12; 5:13–33 can help your class members identify some ways in which Satan tempts us to do evil. You might ask half of the class to read Moses 4:4–12 and the other half to read Moses 5:13, 18–33. As they read, they could list ways Satan tried to tempt Adam and Eve and their children. How does he attempt these same things today? How can Heavenly Father help us resist Satan's deceptions?</li>
</ul>
<heading>GENESIS 3:1–7; MOSES 4:22–31; 5:4–15</heading>
<heading>Jesus Christ's Atonement offers hope and redemption from the Fall.</heading>
<ul>
<li>The more we understand the effects of the Fall, the more we appreciate the Atonement of Jesus Christ. Class members could search for the effects of the Fall in Genesis 3:1–7; Moses 4:22–31 and list what they find on the board. Then they could search Moses 5:4–12, 14–15 to learn about God's plan to redeem us from those effects (see also 2 Nephi 2:19–25; Alma 12:22–34) and list what they find on the board. They could also share what impresses them about Adam's and Eve's testimonies of Jesus Christ found in verses 10–12. How do we feel about God's plan after reading these scriptures?</li>
<li>Adam and Eve's story of hope and redemption can encourage class members when life is difficult. Consider inviting them to find words and phrases in Moses 5:7–12 that express the hope that Adam and Eve felt hope similar to what Adam and Eve felt? Consider inviting class members to share their favorite hymns expressing the hope that comes through the Savior's Atonement. You could sing a few of these together.</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>We can choose for ourselves.</heading>
<p>Elder Dale G. Renlund taught:
"Our Heavenly Father's goal in parenting is not to have His children<i>do</i>what is right; it is to have His children<i>choose</i>to do what is right and ultimately become like Him. If He simply wanted us to be obedient, He would use immediate rewards and punishments to influence our behaviors.
"But God is not interested in His children just becoming trained and obedient «pets» who will not chew on His slippers in the celestial living room. No, God wants His children to grow up spiritually and join Him in the family business" ("Choose You This Day," Ensign or Liahona, Nov. 2018, 104).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Increase the participation of class members.</b>Many activities can be done as a class, in small groups, or in pairs. Use a variety of methods to allow people to participate who might not otherwise have a chance. (See Teaching in the Savior's Way, 33–34.)</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<graphics-caption>Better than Paradise, by Kendal Ray Johnson</graphics-caption>
<heading type="date">JANUARY 17–23</heading>
<heading type="ref">Genesis 5; Moses 6</heading>
<heading type="title">"TEACH THESE THINGS FREELY UNTO YOUR CHILDREN"</heading>
<p>Before you read any additional materials, read and ponder Genesis 5 and Moses 6, and record your spiritual impressions.<i>Come, Follow Me—For Individuals and Families</i>and this outline can give you ideas about how to help those you teach discover truths relevant to them.</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>How can you encourage class members to share insights and experiences they had as they studied Genesis 5 and Moses 6? You could write the names<i>Adam</i>and<i>Enoch</i>on the board and invite class members to write something that one of these prophets did or taught that was meaningful to them.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>MOSES 6:26–39</heading>
<heading>The Lord calls us to do His work despite our inadequacies.</heading>
<ul>
<li>There's a good chance that someone in your class has felt — or is feeling — inadequate about a responsibility at home or at church. To build class members' faith that the Lord can help them, you could invite them to read Enoch's experience found in Moses 6:26–39. How did God help Enoch do His work despite Enoch's fears? Ask class members to think about other examples of people who overcame their weaknesses and accomplished the Lord's work, either from the scriptures or their own lives. What examples can we share? (see also Exodus 4:10–16; Jeremiah 1:4–10; 2 Nephi 33:1–4; Ether 12:23–29).</li>
<li>Many modern-day apostles and prophets have expressed concerns similar to Enoch's when they have described how it felt to receive their calls. Their experiences could enhance class members' understanding of Moses 6:26–39. Consider reviewing the video "On the Lord's Errand: The Life of Thomas S. Monson" (ChurchofJesusChrist.org; between minutes 35:46 and 39:40) or a talk by a recently called member of the Quorum of the Twelve (for example, see the testimonies of Elder Ronald A. Rasband, Elder Gary E. Stevenson, and Elder Dale G. Renlund [Ensign or Liahona, Nov. 2015, 89–94]). Let class members share what impresses them about these examples. What can we learn from these leaders about our own feelings of inadequacy? The statement from President Thomas S. Monson in "Additional Resources" may also be helpful as part of this discussion.</li>
</ul>
<heading>MOSES 6:48–65</heading>
<heading>Faith, repentance, baptism, and receiving the Holy Ghost prepare us to return to God.</heading>
<ul>
<li>This week's outline in<i>Come, Follow Me—For Individuals and Families</i>suggests reading Moses 6:48–62 to find what each of us must know and do to be redeemed. Perhaps class members could share any insights that came from that study in their homes. Or you could discuss Moses 6:48–62 together in class. How would we respond to someone who asks why faith, repentance, baptism, and receiving the gift of the Holy Ghost are necessary? How does the Lord answer this question in verses 53–65, and what do we learn from His answer?</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>Parents should teach their children the gospel.</graphics-caption>
<heading>MOSES 6:51–63</heading>
<heading>"Teach these things freely unto your children."</heading>
<ul>
<li>In Moses 6:51–63 we learn of gospel truths that the Lord taught to Adam and asked him to teach to future generations. Perhaps class members could make a list of these truths by studying smaller groups of verses, such as verses 51–52, 53–57, 58–60, 61–63. Why are these truths valuable to today's rising generation? What would you want young people to know about the Savior from these verses? Class members may be willing to share ideas or experiences to help each other teach these truths more effectively to children and youth. What else can we learn from the Lord's instructions to parents in Mosiah 4:14–15 and Doctrine and Covenants 68:25–28; 93:40–50?</li>
<li>To add to what Moses 6 teaches about parents' responsibility to teach their children, you might invite class members to watch one or more of the following videos: "Parenting: Touching the Hearts of Our Youth," "Proclamation Series: Children," or "Mother in Israel" (ChurchofJesusChrist.org). What do we learn from these videos about teaching the gospel to our children? If you are teaching youth, you could invite them to share how they can support their parents in their efforts to teach the gospel at home.</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>"Whom the Lord calls, the Lord qualifies."</heading>
<p>President Thomas S. Monson taught: "Some of you may be shy by nature or consider yourselves inadequate to respond affirmatively to a calling. Remember that this work is not yours and mine alone. It is the Lord's work, and when we are on the Lord's errand, we are entitled to the Lord's help.
"Remember that whom the Lord calls, the Lord qualifies" ("Duty Calls," Ensign, May 1996, 44).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>The Holy Ghost is the teacher.</b>Your role as a teacher is important, but remember that the Holy Ghost is the real teacher. Help class members learn from the Spirit and share with each other what they learn.</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<graphics-caption>Love One Another, by Emma Donaldson Taylor</graphics-caption>
<heading type="date">JANUARY 24–30</heading>
<heading type="ref">Moses 7</heading>
<heading type="title">"THE LORD CALLED HIS PEOPLE ZION"</heading>
<p>As you study Moses 7, think about the people you teach and how you can help them understand what this chapter teaches about Zion and other gospel principles.</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>Sometimes a simple question and a few minutes to ponder are enough to help people share what they are learning at home. Perhaps you could give class members a little time to review Moses 7, find a verse that makes them feel thankful for the truths restored in the book of Moses, and then share it.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>MOSES 7:16–21, 27, 53, 62–69</heading>
<heading>We can build Zion in our day.</heading>
<ul>
<li>What would be the best way to introduce the concept of Zion in your class? One idea could be to contact class members during the week before class and invite them to bring an object from home that they feel represents the characteristics of the people of Zion, as described in Moses 7:18. As you discuss this verse together, class members could explain the significance of the object they brought.</li>
<li>The video "We Come Together and Unite as One" (ChurchofJesusChrist.org) could help you start a discussion about how we can be "of one heart and one mind" (Moses 7:18) in our wards and families. Consider asking class members to think about times when they have felt unity within their families or while serving with others in the Church or community. What did people do to create unity in these situations? What can we learn about Zion and unity from Moses 7? (see especially verses 16–21, 27, 53, 62–69). Here are some other scriptures that could help: Philippians 2:1–4; 4 Nephi 1:15–18; Doctrine and Covenants 97:21; 105:5.</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>We should strive to be "of one heart and one mind" (Moses 7:18).</graphics-caption>
<heading>MOSES 7:28–44</heading>
<heading>God weeps for His children.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Some people may view God as distant, unapproachable, and even uncaring. How can you use Enoch's vision to help your class understand that God is involved in our lives and cares for us? You might invite class members to read Moses 7:28–44 and make a list of some of the reasons God was weeping. What do these verses teach you about how God feels about His children? The statement in "Additional Resources" can contribute to this discussion.</li>
<li>This week's outline in<i>Come, Follow Me—For Individuals and Families</i>suggests pondering what Moses 7:28–31, 35 teaches about God. Those who did this at home might be willing to share their thoughts with the class. Or you could invite class members to ponder these verses and discuss them in class.</li>
</ul>
<heading>MOSES 7:59–67</heading>
<heading>The Lord will come again in the last days.</heading>
<ul>
<li>How can you help your class members discover what Moses 7:59–67 teaches about the Savior's Second Coming? Maybe you could list two or three truths or events from these verses on the board and ask class members to search the verses and add to the list. Why is it a blessing to have a record of Enoch's vision — one of the earliest prophecies of the Second Coming?</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<p>Elder Jeffrey R. Holland taught:
"In the midst of a grand vision of humankind which heaven opened to his view, Enoch, observing both the blessings and challenges of mortality, turns his gaze toward the Father and is stunned to see Him weeping. He says in wonder and amazement to this most powerful Being in the universe: 'How is it that thou canst weep?'. . .
"Looking out on the events of almost any day, God replies: «Behold these thy brethren; they are the workmanship of mine own hands. . . . I gave unto them. . .[a] commandment, that they should love one another, and that they should choose me, their Father; but behold, they are without affection, and they hate their own blood. . . . Wherefore should not the heavens weep, seeing these shall suffer?» [Moses 7:29–33, 37].
"That single, riveting scene does more to teach the true nature of God than any theological treatise could ever convey. . . . What an indelible image of God's engagement in our lives! What anguish in a parent when His children do not choose Him nor «the gospel of God» He sent! [Romans 1:1]. How easy to love someone who so singularly loves us!" ("The Grandeur of God," Ensign or Liahona, Nov. 2003, 72).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Encourage class members to study the scriptures at home.</b>One way you can encourage scripture study at home is to provide time for class members to share discoveries and insights from their personal and family study. (See Teaching in the Savior's Way, 29.)</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<graphics-caption>Illustration of Noah leaving the ark, by Sam Lawlor</graphics-caption>
<heading type="date">JANUARY 31–FEBRUARY 6</heading>
<heading type="ref">Genesis 6–11; Moses 8</heading>
<heading type="title">"NOAH FOUND GRACE IN THE EYES OF THE LORD"</heading>
<p>This outline highlights principles found in Genesis 6–11 and Moses 8, but these are not the only principles you could focus on as you teach. Trust the spiritual promptings you receive as you study the scriptures.</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>Consider asking class members to share a spiritual message for our day from the story of Noah or the Tower of Babel. Encourage them to share a scripture that supports this message.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>GENESIS 6–8; MOSES 8</heading>
<heading>There is spiritual safety in following the Lord's prophet.</heading>
<ul>
<li>The wickedness in the days of Noah can remind us of the wickedness we see around us today. To help class members benefit from the lessons in the story of Noah, you could write on the board<i>Warnings</i>and<i>Reassurances</i>. Class members could review Genesis 6–8 or Moses 8:13–30 and find something they feel is an important warning for our day and something they consider reassuring (see also "Additional Resources"). They could write what they find under the appropriate heading on the board. Why is the story of Noah valuable to us today?</li>
</ul>
<heading>GENESIS 9:8–17</heading>
<heading>Tokens or symbols help us remember our covenants with the Lord.</heading>
<ul>
<li>This week's outline in<i>Come, Follow Me—For Individuals and Families</i>suggests reading Genesis 9:8–17 and pondering how symbols or tokens can serve as reminders of our covenants. To help class members share their thoughts, you might bring to class some objects that remind us of important things — such as a wedding ring, a national flag, or a missionary name tag — and compare them with the "token" of the rainbow. What does Joseph Smith Translation, Genesis 9:21–25 (in the Bible appendix) teach us about this token? How does God use tokens or symbols to help us remember our covenants?</li>
</ul>
<heading>GENESIS 11:1–9</heading>
<heading>The only way to reach heaven is by following Jesus Christ.</heading>
<ul>
<li>The account of the people of Babel building a tower provides an interesting contrast to the account of Enoch and his people building Zion, which class members studied last week. Both groups of people were trying to reach heaven but in different ways. You might invite class members to list on the board anything they remember about the people of Zion (see Moses 7:18–19, 53, 62–63, 69) and what they learn from Genesis 11:1–9 and Helaman 6:26–28 about the people of Babel. What differences do they find? What does this teach us about our own efforts to return to God's presence?</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>Illustration of the Tower of Babel, by David Green</graphics-caption>
<ul>
<li>The ancient city of Babel no longer exists, but the pride and worldliness it symbolizes do. To help class members apply lessons from the Tower of Babel to their lives, start by inviting them to review Genesis 11:1–9. Then you could distribute slips of paper and invite the class members to write things people do that draw them away from God; then, on other slips of paper, they could write things people do that draw them nearer to God. Youth might enjoy arranging the first group of papers on the board in the shape of a tower and the second group in the shape of a temple. What has God provided to help us "reach unto heaven"? (Genesis 11:4; see also John 3:16). You might sing a hymn on this topic, such as "Nearer, My God, to Thee" (Hymns, no. 100).</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>Lessons from Noah.</heading>
<p>President Henry B. Eyring said:
"The failure to take prophetic counsel lessens our power to take inspired counsel in the future. The best time to have decided to help Noah build the ark was the first time he asked. Each time he asked after that, each failure to respond would have lessened sensitivity to the Spirit. And so each time his request would have seemed more foolish, until the rain came. And then it was too late.
"Every time in my life when I have chosen to delay following inspired counsel or decided that I was an exception, I came to know that I had put myself in harm's way. Every time that I have listened to the counsel of prophets, felt it confirmed in prayer, and then followed it, I have found that I moved toward safety" ("Finding Safety in Counsel," Ensign, May 1997, 25).</p>
<heading>Why did God send the Flood?</heading>
<p>Some people wonder about the justice of God in sending a flood to "destroy man" (Genesis 6:7). Elder Neal A. Maxwell explained that at the time of the Great Flood, "corruption had reached an agency-destroying point that spirits could not, in justice, be sent here" (We Will Prove Them Herewith [1982], 58).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Allow time for pondering.</b>Good questions require pondering, searching, and inspiration. Give class members a few minutes to ponder a question before asking for answers. (See Teaching in the Savior's Way, 31–34.)</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<graphics-caption>Illustration of Abraham and Sarah, by Dilleen Marsh</graphics-caption>
<heading type="date">FEBRUARY 7–13</heading>
<heading type="ref">Genesis 12–17; Abraham 1–2</heading>
<heading type="title">"TO BE A GREATER FOLLOWER OF RIGHTEOUSNESS"</heading>
<p>What has the Holy Ghost taught you this week as you studied Genesis 12–17 and Abraham 1–2? Be sure to give class members opportunities to share what the Holy Ghost has taught them.</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>To give class members opportunities to share something they learned from Genesis 12–17 and Abraham 1–2, they could each choose a person mentioned in these chapters and complete a sentence like the following: "Abraham taught me__" or "Sarah taught me__."</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>GENESIS 15:1–6; 17:15–22; ABRAHAM 1:1–19</heading>
<heading>God will bless us for our faith and righteous desires.</heading>
<ul>
<li>The experiences of Abraham and Sarah recorded in Genesis 15; 17; Abraham 1 can help class members maintain faith that their righteous desires will be fulfilled in the Lord's time. How can you begin a discussion about this principle? One idea is to invite the class to search Genesis 15:1–6 and Abraham 1:1–19 and describe Abraham's desires and difficult circumstances. How did Abraham and Sarah demonstrate their faith in times of difficulty? (see Hebrews 11:8–13). How were their righteous desires eventually fulfilled? (see Genesis 17:15–22; 21:1–3; Doctrine and Covenants 132:29; Abraham 1:31). How can we demonstrate our faith when our righteous desires are not yet fulfilled as we would like them to be? Perhaps class members could share how the Savior has supported them in such situations.</li>
<li>Some members of your class may receive little support from their families as they strive to live the gospel — and they may even face opposition. What can we learn from Abraham's example in Abraham 1:1–19 that can help those striving to live righteously in such situations?</li>
<li>You might ask class members to read Joseph Smith Translation, Genesis 14:36–40 (in the Bible appendix) and share what they learn about Abraham's faith and desires. They could also share how they have been blessed when they have exercised their faith to pay tithing.</li>
</ul>
<heading>ABRAHAM 2:6–11</heading>
<heading>The Abrahamic covenant blesses all of us.</heading>
<ul>
<li>To help class members understand what the Abrahamic covenant is, you might share the statements by President Russell M. Nelson in "Additional Resources" (see also Gospel Topics, "Abrahamic Covenant," topics.ChurchofJesusChrist.org). Class members may have learned about the Abrahamic covenant from Abraham 2:6–11, as suggested in this week's outline in<i>Come, Follow Me—For Individuals and Families</i>. Perhaps class members could share what they learned, or the class could study these verses together. What promises and responsibilities do we receive through the Abrahamic covenant? The video "Special Witness — President Nelson" could help answer this question (ChurchofJesusChrist.org/media-library/video/2011-04-18-special-witness-president-nelson). What do we need to do to receive the blessings of this covenant? How can we, as Abraham's seed, bless "all the families of the earth"? (Abraham 2:11).</li>
</ul>
<heading>GENESIS 14:18–19; JOSEPH SMITH TRANSLATION, GENESIS 14:25–40</heading>
<heading>"Melchizedek was a man of faith."</heading>
<ul>
<li>Because of the Restoration of the gospel, most members of the Church are familiar with the Melchizedek Priesthood, but some do not know about the man Melchizedek. To help class members learn more about him, perhaps you could invite them to imagine that they were asked to introduce him to someone who did not know him and make a list on the board of things they would say. They could base these things on what they read in Joseph Smith Translation, Genesis 14:26–27, 33–38 (in the Bible appendix); Alma 13:13–19; and Doctrine and Covenants 107:1–4. What do we learn about the Melchizedek Priesthood from these verses?</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>Melchizedek Blesses Abram, by Walter Rane</graphics-caption>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>Blessings of the Abrahamic covenant.</heading>
<p>President Russell M. Nelson taught:
"The covenant God made with Abraham and later affirmed with Isaac and Jacob is of transcendent significance. . . . The Lord appeared in these latter days to renew that Abrahamic covenant. . . . With this renewal, we have received, as did they of old, the holy priesthood and the everlasting gospel. We have the right to receive the fulness of the gospel, enjoy the blessings of the priesthood, and qualify for God's greatest blessing — that of eternal life" ("Covenants," Ensign or Liahona, Nov. 2011, 87–88).
"The ultimate blessings of the Abrahamic covenant are conferred in holy temples. These blessings allow us to come forth in the First Resurrection and inherit thrones, kingdoms, powers, principalities, and dominions, to our «exaltation and glory in all things» [Doctrine and Co ants 132:19]" ("Special Witnesses of Christ," Ensign, Apr. 2001, 7).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Bear testimony often.</b>Your simple, sincere witness of spiritual truth can have a powerful influence on those you teach. For example, you could share a simple testimony about how covenants have blessed your life.</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<graphics-caption>Sarah and Isaac, by Scott Snow</graphics-caption>
<heading type="date">FEBRUARY 14–20</heading>
<heading type="ref">Genesis 18–23</heading>
<heading type="title">"IS ANY THING TOO HARD FOR THE LORD?"</heading>
<p>As you prepare to teach, keep in mind that many class members may have had meaningful experiences of their own as they read Genesis 18–23. What can you do to encourage them to share these experiences and insights? Consider letting those insights influence the class discussion.</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>Our tests and trials often become defining moments in our lives. Genesis 18–23 describes several such moments in the lives of Abraham and Lot. Perhaps class members could share a verse they found during their personal study this week that describes a possible defining moment for Abraham. They could then share what they learned from it.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>GENESIS 18:9–14; 21:1–7</heading>
<heading>The Lord fulfills His promises in His own time.</heading>
<ul>
<li>The account in these verses can be inspiring to class members who wonder if God's promises to them will be fulfilled. To begin a discussion, it may be helpful to invite class members to review with someone else in class the account of God's promises to Abraham and Sarah in Genesis 17:4, 15–22; 18:9–14 and the fulfillment of those promises in Genesis 21:1–7. What in these verses stands out to class members? What truths could we draw from Abraham and Sarah's experience to share with a friend who is losing hope that God will fulfill His promises? What other scriptures or personal experiences might we share? (see, for example, Romans 8:28; Hebrews 11; Mormon 9:19–21; Doctrine and Covenants 88:64). What experiences could class members share in which God's promises were fulfilled in their lives? How can we sustain our faith when promised blessings may<i>not</i>be received in this life? (see Hebrews 11:8–13).</li>
</ul>
<heading>GENESIS 19:15–26</heading>
<heading>As disciples of Jesus Christ, we should flee wickedness and not look back.</heading>
<ul>
<li>What lessons do you feel class members could learn from the account of Lot's family fleeing Sodom and Gomorrah? One possible lesson is suggested in Elder Jeffrey R. Holland's statement in "Additional Resources." Perhaps you could share it with the class after summarizing the events described in Genesis 19:15–26. In what ways or in what situations do we sometimes "[look] back" (verse 26) when we ought to be looking forward with faith in the Savior? Perhaps class members could share experiences that illustrate the importance of not looking back. What does Luke 9:62 add to our understanding of this concept?</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>Fleeing Sodom and Gomorrah, by Julius Schnorr von Carolsfeld</graphics-caption>
<heading>GENESIS 22:1–14</heading>
<heading>Abraham's willingness to sacrifice Isaac is a similitude of God and His Son.</heading>
<ul>
<li>The account of Abraham offering his son as a sacrifice can teach us about Heavenly Father's sacrifice of His Son. One way to explore this account is to assign half of the class to ponder Genesis 22:1–14 from the perspectives of Abraham and God the Father, while the other half ponders this account from the perspectives of Isaac and Jesus Christ. Ask class members to share insights they gain. In particular, what do class members learn that deepens their gratitude for Heavenly Father and Jesus Christ? As part of this discussion, you could display the picture Abraham Taking Isaac to Be Sacrificed (Gospel Art Book, no. 9) or show the video "Akedah (The Binding)" (ChurchofJesusChrist.org).</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>"Faith is always pointed toward the future."</heading>
<p>Elder Jeffrey R. Holland taught:
"It is possible that Lot's wife looked back with resentment toward the Lord for what He was asking her to leave behind. . . . So it isn't just that she looked back; she looked back longingly. In short, her attachment to the past outweighed her confidence in the future. . . .
". . . I plead with you not to dwell on days now gone nor to yearn vainly for yesterdays, however good those yesterdays may have been. The past is to be learned from but not lived in. We look back to claim the embers from glowing experiences but not the ashes. And when we have learned what we need to learn and have brought with us the best that we have experienced, then we look ahead and remember that<i>faith is always pointed toward the future</i>. . . .
". . . [Lot's wife] did not have faith. She doubted the Lord's ability to give her something better than she already had. Apparently, she thought that nothing that lay ahead could possibly be as good as what she was leaving behind. . . .
". . . Dwelling on past lives, including past mistakes, is just not right! It is not the gospel of Jesus Christ" ("The Best Is Yet to Be," Ensign, Jan. 2010, 24, 26–27).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Promise blessings.</b>As you invite those you teach to act on what they learn, also testify of the blessings that God has promised to those who do so. (See also Teaching in the Savior's Way, 35.)</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<graphics-caption>Illustration of Rebekah, by Dilleen Marsh</graphics-caption>
<heading type="date">FEBRUARY 21–27</heading>
<heading type="ref">Genesis 24–27</heading>
<heading type="title">THE COVENANT IS RENEWED</heading>
<p>As you read Genesis 24–27, pray to know how you can encourage class members to have their own experiences learning from the scriptures.</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>To encourage class members to share their insights from Genesis 24–27, you could invite them to select a specific passage that inspired them and write it on a slip of paper. Collect the papers, and choose several to read and discuss as a class.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>GENESIS 24</heading>
<heading>Covenant marriage is essential to God's eternal plan.</heading>
<ul>
<li>The importance Abraham placed on finding a wife for Isaac provides an opportunity to discuss the importance of covenant marriage in God's plan for us. To start the discussion, class members could scan Genesis 24 and share things the Lord did to help bring Isaac and Rebekah together in marriage. Why is marriage important to the Lord? To help class members discuss this question, you could share with them Elder D. Todd Christofferson's statement in "Additional Resources." How can we help ensure that God's purposes for marriage are accomplished?</li>
<li>Ask class members what qualities they have seen in a spouse, parents, or other married couples that have contributed to a faithful, happy marriage. The account in Genesis 24 demonstrates qualities that can help a person create happiness in marriage — and other aspects of life. For example, in verse 12 we learn about being guided by prayer, and in verse 19 we learn about giving extra effort in service. What other principles can be found in these chapters? Class members might also look in "The Family: A Proclamation to the World" (ChurchofJesusChrist.org).</li>
</ul>
<heading>GENESIS 25:29–34</heading>
<heading>We can choose between immediate gratification and things of greater value.</heading>
<ul>
<li>How might you help class members find personal lessons from Jacob and Esau's experiences? One idea is to invite them to make two lists on the board — one of eternal blessings God wants to give us and another of worldly things that distract us from those blessings. Then class members could read Genesis 25:29–34, replacing "birthright" with something from the first list and "pottage" with something from the second list. How does the adversary try to convince us to exchange God's blessings for things that are less valuable? Consider inviting class members to give each other advice on how to focus on the Savior and the eternal blessings He offers us.</li>
</ul>
<heading>GENESIS 26:18–25, 32–33</heading>
<heading>Jesus Christ is the well of living water.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Genesis 26 mentions several times that Isaac and his household had to dig wells to find water, and this often required great effort. This fact could help you teach class members about the effort required to bring the Savior's "living water" into our lives (see John 4:10). Perhaps you could illustrate this with a drawing on the board of a water source covered by deep dirt. Class members could take turns erasing some of the dirt as they describe how they can find the Savior's living water. Encourage them to use the Guide to the Scriptures to find verses that relate to the things they share.</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>A well in ancient Beer-sheba, where Abraham and Isaac dug wells.</graphics-caption>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>Marriage and family are God's creation.</heading>
<p>Elder D. Todd Christofferson gave some reasons why marriage and family are so important to God's plan:
"A family built on the marriage of a man and woman supplies the best setting for God's plan to thrive — the setting for the birth of children, who come in purity and innocence from God, and the environment for the learning and preparation they will need for a successful mortal life and eternal life in the world to come. A critical mass of families built on such marriages is vital for societies to survive and flourish. . . .
". . . But our claims for the role of marriage and family rest not on social science but on the truth that they are God's creation. It is He who in the beginning created Adam and Eve in His image, male and female, and joined them as husband and wife to become one flesh' and to multiply and replenish the earth. Each individual carries the divine image, but it is in the matrimonial union of male and female as one that we attain perhaps the most complete meaning of our having been made in the image of God — male and female. . . . Such marriage. . . is as much a part of the plan of happiness as the Fall and the Atonement" ("Why Marriage, Why Family," Ensign or Liahona, May 2015, 52).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Center your teaching on doctrine.</b>As you invite class members to share, make sure you continually bring the discussion back to the doctrine in the scriptures. You can do this by asking class members to read scripture passages in class, asking questions about what the scriptures say, and inviting class members to share their testimonies of the doctrine being taught.</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<heading type="date">FEBRUARY 28–MARCH 6</heading>
<heading type="ref">Genesis 28–33</heading>
<heading type="title">"SURELY THE LORD IS IN THIS PLACE"</heading>
<p>As you prepare to teach, prayerfully consider which principles in Genesis 28–33 might be most helpful to your class members. The following ideas are meant to add to your personal study and inspiration.</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>One blessing of being gathered in a Sunday School class is that members can help each other find meaning in the scriptures. Encourage class members to share with someone sitting nearby what the Holy Ghost taught them as they studied the scriptures this week. A few could be invited to share with the class what they discussed. This might create a good starting place for your class discussion.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>GENESIS 28:10–22</heading>
<heading>In the temple we make covenants with God.</heading>
<ul>
<li>How might you help class members find meaning in Jacob's experience at Bethel, as described in Genesis 28:10–22? They could start by reviewing Genesis 27:41–45; 28:1–5 and considering Jacob's life at the time. How might Jacob have been feeling? Class members could then explore Genesis 28:10–22. How did this experience bless Jacob? How might he have been comforted? How might Jacob's experience inspire us as we worship in the temple? The class could also sing, read, or listen to "Nearer, My God, to Thee," which is based on these verses (Hymns, no. 100). They could share phrases from the song or from Genesis 28:10–22 that remind them of experiences they have had with trying to draw nearer to the Savior.</li>
<li>The ladder Jacob saw in his dream has often been compared to temple covenants. Maybe you could show or draw a picture of a ladder and a temple. Class members could review Genesis 28:10–22 and talk about what the ladder in Jacob's dream teaches us about the temple. What else do we find in these verses that reminds us of blessings we receive because of our temple covenants? (See "About the Temple Endowment" and "About a Temple Sealing" [temples.ChurchofJesusChrist.org].)</li>
<li>To help class members ponder the promises of the Abrahamic covenant, which the Lord renewed with Jacob, you could invite them to read Genesis 28:10–15 and talk about how we can receive these blessings today (see also Genesis 12:2–3). They could also read President Russell M. Nelson's statement in "Additional Resources," looking for blessings that come from making and keeping covenants. How was Jacob blessed by receiving the promises found in Genesis 28:10–15? What connections do we see between the events in these verses and the events in Genesis 29 and 30 (Jacob getting married and the births of his children)? How does the Lord bless us as we make and keep sacred covenants?</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>Illustration of Jacob and Esau embracing, by Robert T. Barrett</graphics-caption>
<heading>GENESIS 32–33</heading>
<heading>The Savior can help us overcome discord in our families.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Genesis 32–33 could be inspiring to class members who want to find healing in their family relationships. It might be helpful to ask a class member to briefly summarize the events recorded in Genesis 27. This week's outline in<i>Come, Follow Me—For Individuals and Families</i>includes questions to ponder while studying Genesis 32–33. Perhaps class members could select one of these questions and look for answers in the chapters. They may also be willing to share experiences they have had with strengthening strained relationships in their families. Encourage them to talk about how Heavenly Father helped them.</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>We are children of the covenant.</heading>
<p>President Russell M. Nelson taught:
"At baptism we covenant to serve the Lord and keep His commandments. When we partake of the sacrament, we renew that covenant and declare our willingness to take upon ourselves the name of Jesus Christ. Thereby we are adopted as His sons and daughters and are known as brothers and sisters. He is the father of our new life. Ultimately, in the holy temple, we may become joint heirs to the blessings of an eternal family, as once promised to Abraham, Isaac, Jacob, and their posterity. Thus, celestial marriage is the covenant of exaltation.
"When we realize that we are children of the covenant, we know who we are and what God expects of us. His law is written in our hearts. He is our God and we are His people. Committed children of the covenant remain steadfast, even in the midst of adversity. When that doctrine is deeply implanted in our hearts, even the sting of death is soothed and our spiritual stamina is strengthened" ("Covenants," Ensign or Liahona, Nov. 2011, 88).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Help learners act on promptings.</b>"True conversion involves more than just feeling the Spirit confirming truth to our souls; we must also act on those truths. In addition to helping learners feel and recognize the Spirit, help them act on the promptings they receive" (Teaching in the Savior's Way, 10).</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<graphics-caption>Illustration of Joseph of Egypt in prison, by Jeff Ward</graphics-caption>
<heading type="date">MARCH 7–13</heading>
<heading type="ref">Genesis 37–41</heading>
<heading type="title">"THE LORD WAS WITH JOSEPH"</heading>
<p>It is not intended that you teach all of the activities in this outline. As you prepare to teach, pray that the Spirit will help you know which activities (if any) in this outline will best meet the needs of your class.</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>To encourage class members to share what they learned in their personal and family study, you could invite them to find a phrase in Genesis 37–41 that expresses a lesson or principle they feel is important.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>GENESIS 37:1–28; 39; 40:1–19; 41:9–45</heading>
<heading>"The Lord was with Joseph" in his adversity.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Like Joseph, members of your class may be experiencing difficult trials. To help the class find inspiration in Joseph's example, you could divide them into three groups and ask each group to review one of the following scripture passages: Genesis 39; 40:1–19; or 41:9–45. Each group could then share the ways the Lord was with Joseph in his challenges. As appropriate, class members could share experiences when the Lord was with them during a difficult trial. How can we learn to better see the Lord's presence in our lives?</li>
<li>This object lesson can help illustrate how we can rise above adversity: place a lightweight object, such as a small plastic ball, at the bottom of a container filled about halfway with dry rice or beans. Invite someone to shake the container gently until the ball rises to the top. How was Joseph like the ball? Class members could share examples of the Lord helping Joseph rise above adversity from Genesis 37:5–11; 39; 40:1–19; 41:9–45. They could also share times when the Lord helped them in similar ways.</li>
<li>You might ask class members to sing or read the words of a hymn about making righteous choices, such as "Do What Is Right" (Hymns, no. 237). Then class members could find insights or phrases in Genesis 37:1–28; 39; 40:1–19; 41:9–45 that illustrate the hymn's messages. How was Joseph blessed, despite his adversity, when he did what was right? When has the Lord blessed us in times of adversity for doing the right thing?</li>
</ul>
<heading>GENESIS 37:5–11; 40; 41:1–38</heading>
<heading>If we are faithful, the Lord will guide and inspire us.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Although not everyone receives personal revelation through dreams, there are things we can learn about revelation from the experiences of Joseph, Pharaoh's servants, and Pharaoh. You could invite class members to review Genesis 37:5–11; 40:5–8; 41:14–25, 37–38 and share anything they learn about revelation. You could also invite them to share what has helped them prepare to receive, understand, and act on revelation.</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>Joseph Interpreting the Butler and Baker's Dreams, by François Gérard</graphics-caption>
<heading>GENESIS 39:1–20</heading>
<heading>With the Lord's help, we can flee temptation.</heading>
<ul>
<li>You might ask class members to share what they learned about resisting temptation as they read Genesis 39 this week. What did Joseph do to overcome temptation? (see verses 7–12). The videos "Leave the Party" and "Dare to Stand Alone" (ChurchofJesusChrist.org) provide examples of people who resisted temptation. Consider asking class members to make a list of things we can do to draw on God's power when we face temptations. (Class members could find ideas in Matthew 4:1–11 or in the scriptures listed under "Tempt, Temptation" in Guide to the Scriptures [scriptures.ChurchofJesusChrist.org].)</li>
<li>How can you use Joseph's example to help class members resist temptation to commit sexual sin? In addition to reviewing Genesis 39:1–20, class members could watch the video "Chastity: What Are the Limits?" (ChurchofJesusChrist.org) or review "Sexual Purity" (in For the Strength of Youth [2011], 35–37). They could share what they learn about resisting thoughts, words, and actions that lead to sexual sin. Reviewing "Repentance" (in For the Strength of Youth, 28–29) can help class members understand the opportunity that Jesus Christ offers us to repent.</li>
</ul>
<heading>GENESIS 41:15–57</heading>
<heading>We should prepare for possible hardships.</heading>
<ul>
<li>You could ask one class member to describe Pharaoh's dreams (see Genesis 41:15–24) and another one to share Joseph's interpretations (see verses 25–32). What did Joseph propose to do? (see verses 33–36, 47–49). What lessons does this account have for our day? (see President Gordon B. Hinckley's counsel in "Additional Resources").</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>Preparing for times of trouble.</heading>
<p>President Gordon B. Hinckley said: "I urge you to be modest in your expenditures; discipline yourselves in your purchases to avoid debt to the extent possible. Pay off debt as quickly as you can. . . .Have a reserve, even though it be small" ("To the Boys and to the Men," Ensign, Nov. 1998, 54).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Listening is an act of love.</b>"Ask Heavenly Father to help you understand what your class members say. As you pay careful attention to their spoken and unspoken messages, you will come to better understand their needs" (Teaching in the Savior's Way, 34).</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<graphics-caption>Illustration of Joseph of Egypt, by Robert T. Barrett</graphics-caption>
<heading type="date">MARCH 14–20</heading>
<heading type="ref">Genesis 42–50</heading>
<heading type="title">"GOD MEANT IT UNTO GOOD"</heading>
<p>Elder David A. Bednar said, "The spiritual understanding you and I have been blessed to receive. . . simply cannot be given to another person" ("Seek Learning by Faith," Ensign, Sept. 2007, 67). How will you help class members gain spiritual understanding for themselves?</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>To give class members an opportunity to share something they found meaningful in their personal or family scripture study, you could ask questions like these at the beginning of class: What verse in these chapters caught your attention? What verse did you find yourself reading more than once? What verse did you share with someone? What verse led to an insightful discussion with your family or friends?</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>GENESIS 45:1–15; 50:15–21</heading>
<heading>Forgiveness brings peace.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Before you start a discussion about what Joseph's experience teaches about forgiveness, it might help to have someone briefly relate the story in Genesis 37; 39–45. Why might it have been hard for Joseph to forgive his brothers? What experiences or attitudes might have given Joseph the strength to forgive? (see, for example, Genesis 45:1–15 or 50:15–21). How can Joseph's example help us be more forgiving?</li>
<li>The video "Forgiveness: My Burden Was Made Light" (ChurchofJesusChrist.org) provides another inspiring example of forgiveness. How does the Savior help us forgive others?</li>
<li>What blessings came from Joseph's forgiveness of his brothers? It might be interesting to compare the relationships in Jacob's family at the beginning of the story (see, for example, Genesis 37:3–11) with their state at the end (see Genesis 45:9–15; 50:15–21). What role did forgiveness play in the change in Joseph's family? How might things have turned out differently if Joseph had not been willing to forgive? You might invite class members to suggest ways this story could help families today overcome contention and jealousy.</li>
</ul>
<heading>GENESIS 45:5–11; JOSEPH SMITH TRANSLATION, GENESIS 50:24–38 (IN THE BIBLE APPENDIX)</heading>
<ul>
<li>With the additional light of the restored gospel, we know that Joseph, who delivered his family from famine, also prophesied of great blessings that would one day come through Moses and Joseph Smith. And all of these prophets point us to our Great Deliverer, Jesus Christ. To help class members see the Savior in the ministries of these three prophets, you could draw a chart on the board similar to the one found in "Additional Resources." Class members could work together to fill it out. Then they could add columns describing the work of Joseph of Egypt, Moses, and Joseph Smith, using what they learn from Genesis 45:5–11 and Joseph Smith Translation, Genesis 50:24–38 (in the Bible appendix). How do the ministries of these prophets testify of and point to the mission of the Savior? (For some examples of similarities between the life of Joseph of Egypt and the life of the Savior, see Genesis 37:3 and Matthew 3:17; Genesis 37:26–28 and Matthew 26:14–16; Genesis 45:5–7 and Luke 4:18; and Genesis 47:12 and John 6:35; see also Moses 6:63.)</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>Illustration of Joseph of Egypt, by Paul Mann</graphics-caption>
<heading>GENESIS 50:19–21</heading>
<heading>God can help us find meaning in our trials.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Though it may not have been clear while he was going through his severe trials, Joseph was eventually able to look back on his adversity in Egypt and see that "God meant it unto good" (Genesis 50:20). If we could have visited Joseph while he was in the pit or in prison, how might we have comforted him? How might the thought expressed in Genesis 50:19–21 help us in times of trial? Perhaps class members would be willing to talk about ways God has blessed them, even through difficult experiences they've had. For one example, see the video "Unto All the World: The Sam Family" (ChurchofJesusChrist.org). What does Doctrine and Covenants 122 add to our understanding of this principle?</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>The lives of prophets testify of Jesus Christ and His mission.</heading>
<p>The lives of Joseph of Egypt, Moses, and Joseph Smith can remind us of Jesus Christ. Class members could fill out this chart and then add columns for Joseph of Egypt (see Genesis 45:5–11), Moses (see Joseph Smith Translation, Genesis 50:24, 29, 34–36 [in the Bible appendix]), and Joseph Smith (see Joseph Smith Translation, Genesis 50:26–28, 30–33 [in the Bible appendix]).</p>
<table><thead>
<tr>
<th>_</th>
<th>Jesus Christ</th>
</tr></thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Who was delivered?</td>
<td>_</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>What were they delivered from?</td>
<td>_</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>What was done to deliver them?</td>
<td>_</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Ask questions that invite testifying.</b>Asking questions that encourage learners to bear their testimonies can be an effective way to invite the Spirit. For example, when teaching Genesis 45:1–15, you could ask a question like "What blessings have you experienced as a result of forgiving someone?" (see Teaching in the Savior's Way, 32).</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<graphics-caption>Moses and the Burning Bush, by Harry Anderson</graphics-caption>
<heading type="date">MARCH 21–27</heading>
<heading type="ref">Exodus 1–6</heading>
<heading type="title">"I HAVE REMEMBERED MY COVENANT"</heading>
<p>As you read Exodus 1–6, think about the people you teach. What truths in these chapters are most likely to be meaningful to them? How will you help them discover these truths?</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>One idea to encourage class members to share what they are learning is to write a question like this on the board:<i>As you read Exodus 1–6, what did you notice that you hadn't noticed before?</i>Invite class members to share their answers.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>EXODUS 1–2</heading>
<heading>Jesus Christ is our Deliverer.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Even though the Savior is not mentioned by name in Exodus 1–2, this account can help class members build faith in His mission to deliver us from captivity. Class members could find words or phrases in Exodus 1–2 that describe the hardships the Israelites faced. How are these descriptions similar to the spiritual captivity or other hardships we face? How did the children of Israel seek deliverance, and how did God respond to them? (see also Exodus 2:23–25; 3:7–8). How do we draw on God's power when we need deliverance? How does God answer our pleas for help? Class members could look for additional insights in President Russell M. Nelson's message "Drawing the Power of Jesus Christ into Our Lives" (Ensign or Liahona, May 2017, 39–42).</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>Moses in the Bulrushes, Providence Collection/licensed from goodsalt.com</graphics-caption>
<heading>EXODUS 3–4</heading>
<heading>As we do the Lord's work, we can have the Lord's power.</heading>
<ul>
<li>This week's outline in<i>Come, Follow Me—For Individuals and Families</i>suggests searching Exodus 3–4 to find out how the Lord responded to Moses's concerns about the task of delivering the Israelites from bondage. If members of your class did this activity at home, invite them to share what they learned. Or you could do this activity as a class. Specifically, class members could search Exodus 3:11–18; 4:1–17, looking for Moses's concerns and the Lord's responses to each. How could the Lord's responses help us when we have doubts about our abilities to do His work?</li>
</ul>
<heading>EXODUS 3:5</heading>
<heading>We should show reverence for holy things and places.</heading>
<ul>
<li>How can you use Moses's example to inspire a discussion about how we should treat sacred things? For example, after reading Exodus 3:5 together, you could display sacred objects or pictures of sacred things (such as the scriptures or temples) and common objects or pictures of common things (such as secular books or regular buildings). Class members could talk about other things they consider sacred and share how they show reverence for those things (see also Leviticus 19:30; Doctrine and Covenants 6:10–12). Why does the Savior want us to treat sacred things with reverence?</li>
</ul>
<heading>EXODUS 5:4–9, 20–23; 6:1–13</heading>
<heading>The Lord's purposes will be fulfilled in His own time.</heading>
<ul>
<li>It can be discouraging when our sincere efforts to do good don't seem to be working — perhaps a friend is not responding to our ministering efforts or our prayers for a wayward child seem to go unanswered. To learn about a similar experience Moses had, class members could read Exodus 5:4–9, 20–23. How did the Lord help Moses overcome his feelings of discouragement? (see Exodus 6:1–13). Class members could share experiences when they did not see immediate results from their efforts to serve the Lord. What does Moses's experience in these chapters teach us about how we can respond in similar situations? (See also "Additional Resources.")</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>We serve others for the Lord.</heading>
<p>President Joy D. Jones told how she and her husband served faithfully in a ministering assignment but did not see success from their efforts. The couple pondered and prayed for guidance. Recounting the answer to their prayers, President Jones said:
"We realized that we were sincerely striving to serve this family and to serve our bishop, but we had to ask ourselves if we were really serving out of love for the Lord. King Benjamin made clear this distinction when he stated, 'Behold, I say unto you that because I said unto you that I had spent my days in your service, I do not desire to boast, for<i>I have only been in the service of God'</i>[Mosiah 2:16; emphasis added].
"So whom was King Benjamin really serving? Heavenly Father and the Savior. Knowing the<i>who</i>and the<i>why</i>in serving others helps us understand that the highest manifestation of love is devotion to God" ("For Him," Ensign or Liahona, Nov. 2018, 50).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Share spiritual experiences.</b>One way to invite the influence of the Spirit into your class is to encourage class members to share what the Holy Ghost taught them as they studied the scriptures this week.</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<graphics-caption>Illustration of Moses and Aaron in the court of Pharaoh, by Robert T. Barrett</graphics-caption>
<heading type="date">MARCH 28–APRIL 3</heading>
<heading type="ref">Exodus 7–13</heading>
<heading type="title">"REMEMBER THIS DAY, IN WHICH YE CAME OUT FROM EGYPT"</heading>
<p>Your ability to be guided by the Spirit in your teaching will be greatly enhanced as you have your own spiritual experience with studying Exodus 7–13.</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>Think of a question or two that will encourage class members to share insights and experiences they had as they studied Exodus 7–13 individually and with their families. For example, you might ask, "What did you read this week that strengthened your faith in Jesus Christ?" or "What did you read that was a blessing to your family?"</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>EXODUS 7–12</heading>
<heading>We can choose to soften our hearts.</heading>
<ul>
<li>To help class members think about their willingness to yield their hearts to God, you could ask them to each read one of the following scripture passages: Exodus 7:14–25; 8:5–15; 8:16–19; 8:20–32; 9:1–7; 9:8–12; 9:22–26; 10:12–15; 10:21–29; 12:29–33. Then they could write on the board words or phrases that describe how Pharaoh responded to the ten plagues sent by God upon the Egyptians. (You may want to note that Joseph Smith Translation revisions show that Pharaoh hardened his own heart.) Why might Pharaoh have responded the way he did? Why is it sometimes difficult to yield our hearts and wills to God? How do Heavenly Father and Jesus Christ help us overcome these difficulties?</li>
<li>By bringing to class a hard object and a soft object, you could help class members understand what it means to have a hard or a soft heart. You could pass the two objects around the class, while someone reads one of the descriptions of Pharaoh's heart found in Exodus 7–10 (such as Exodus 9:22–35). Why is "hard" a good description of Pharaoh's heart? What do these verses teach about what it means to have a soft heart? (If it helps, class members could look for insights in one or more of these scriptures: 1 Nephi 2:16; Mosiah 3:19; Alma 24:7–8; 62:41; Ether 12:27.) How does the Savior help us soften our hearts? The video "A Change of Heart" (ChurchofJesusChrist.org) could add to their understanding.</li>
<li>To help class members think about why the Lord sent the plagues on Egypt, you could invite each class member to choose one reference from the following list and find possible reasons: Exodus 3:20; 7:5, 17; 9:14–16; 10:1–2. You could also invite class members to share how they have learned that "there is none like [Heavenly Father and Jesus Christ] in all the earth" (Exodus 9:14).</li>
</ul>
<heading>EXODUS 12</heading>
<heading>The Passover and the sacrament teach about deliverance through Jesus Christ.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Celebrating the Feast of the Passover helped the children of Israel remember that the Lord had delivered them from captivity. To help class members understand the symbolism of the Passover, you could create two columns on the board labeled<i>Symbol</i>and<i>Possible Meaning,</i>with a picture of Jesus Christ above the columns. Class members could study Exodus 12:1–13 and write on the board anything from these verses that could symbolize our deliverance through Jesus Christ. They could then discuss what these symbols teach us about the Savior's Atonement (see the table in "Additional Resources" for a few ideas). The video "The Passover" (ChurchofJesusChrist.org) can help them visualize what they read in Exodus 12.</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>Like the Passover meal, the sacrament helps us remember our Deliverer, Jesus Christ.</graphics-caption>
<ul>
<li>For some people, the sacrament is not always as spiritual as it could be. Consider how a discussion of Exodus 12 could help all class members find deeper meaning in the sacrament. For example, after class members review Exodus 12, you might invite them to share what Israelites from that time period might have said if a son or daughter had asked them what the Passover meant to them. Class members could then discuss what they could say if someone asked what the sacrament say means to them, including any insights they gain from the Passover. You might give class members time to ponder what they can do to remember the Savior daily. The video "Always Remember Him" (ChurchofJesusChrist.org) could help them.</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>The Passover teaches about the Savior.</heading>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Symbol</th>
<th>Possible Meaning</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>The lamb (Exodus 12:3–5)</td>
<td>Jesus Christ</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Blood on the doorposts (Exodus 12:7)</td>
<td>The atoning blood of Jesus Christ, who saves us</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Eating the lamb (Exodus 12:8)</td>
<td>Making the Savior part of our lives</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Bitter herbs (Exodus 12:8)</td>
<td>The bitterness of captivity (sin)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Listen.</b>"Listening is an act of love. . . . Ask Heavenly Father to help you understand what your class members say. As you pay careful attention to their spoken and unspoken messages, you will come to better understand their needs, their concerns, and their desires" (Teaching in the Savior's Way, 34).</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<graphics-caption>The Red Sea</graphics-caption>
<heading type="date">APRIL 4–10</heading>
<heading type="ref">Exodus 14–17</heading>
<heading type="title">"STAND STILL, AND SEE THE SALVATION OF THE LORD"</heading>
<p>Think about how the experiences of the children of Israel apply to members of your class. Which experiences will be most helpful for them to discuss?</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>Exodus 14–17 is filled with memorable accounts. A class member could draw a picture of an event from these chapters while other class members guess what he or she is drawing. Ask them to share what they learned from the account.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>EXODUS 14</heading>
<heading>Heavenly Father delivers us as we follow the Spirit.</heading>
<ul>
<li>The Red Sea seemed like a dead end to the Israelites, but God knew things they didn't. Reviewing the account of the miraculous crossing of the Red Sea could remind class members of times when God delivered them from their trials. You might ask class members to review Exodus 14 and share what most inspires them about this account. Also encourage them to share their experiences with being delivered from trials, along with verses from the chapter that build their faith that God can deliver us.</li>
<li>It might also be interesting to read together Doctrine and Covenants 8:2–3. What do these verses teach about Moses? How do these verses affect the way we think about the events in Exodus 14? What do they suggest about how we seek deliverance from our trials? Consider what the statement in "Additional Resources" might add to your discussion.</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>Manna from God fed Israel physically; we also need daily spiritual nourishment. Fresco by Leopold Bruckner</graphics-caption>
<heading>EXODUS 15:23–27; 16:1–15; 17:1–7</heading>
<heading>The Lord will provide for our needs as we journey through life.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Exodus 15–17 gives multiple accounts that can build class members' faith in the Lord's power and willingness to provide for our physical and spiritual needs. Maybe each class member could study one of the following passages, looking for spiritual messages: Exodus 15:23–27; 16:1–15; 17:1–7. Give several class members a chance to share what they found. How might we use these accounts to encourage someone who has unmet temporal or spiritual needs?</li>
<li>Class members could also read these verses and identify examples of murmuring. How might we explain to someone what it means to murmur? What are some of the consequences of murmuring that make it so dangerous? Perhaps class members could share advice on how to avoid the temptation to murmur against the Lord when we experience difficult trials.</li>
<li>It might help class members to compare manna described in Exodus 16 with the nourishment our spirits need. What similarities do we see? What spiritual lessons might the Lord have wanted to teach the Israelites by sending manna in the way He did? (see John 6:31–35, 48–58). You could also show one or more of the videos found in "Additional Resources."</li>
</ul>
<heading>EXODUS 17:8–16</heading>
<heading>We are blessed as we sustain our leaders.</heading>
<ul>
<li>The account of Aaron and Hur holding up the hands of Moses illustrates the importance of sustaining those who are called to lead us. You could invite a few class members to act out the experience as another class member reads it out loud. How are the efforts of Aaron and Hur to hold up Moses's hands similar to our efforts to sustain our leaders? How do we show that we sustain our leaders?</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>You can receive personalized direction.</heading>
<p>Sister Michelle Craig taught:
"As [the Savior's] faithful disciple, you can receive personal inspiration and revelation, consistent with His commandments, that is tailored to you. You have unique missions and roles to perform in life and will be given unique guidance to fulfill them.
"Nephi, the brother of Jared, and even Moses all had a large body of water to cross — and each did it differently. Nephi worked «timbers of curious workmanship» [1 Nephi 18:1]. The brother of Jared built barges that were «tight like unto a dish» [see Ether 6:5–8]. And Moses «walked upon dry land in the midst of the sea» [Exodus 14:29].
"They each received personalized direction, tailored to them, and each trusted and acted. The Lord is mindful of those who obey and, in the words of Nephi, will «prepare a way for [us to] accomplish the thing which he commandeth» [1 Nephi 3:7]. Note that Nephi says, «a way» — not «the way.»
"Do we miss or dismiss personal errands from the Lord because He has prepared «a way» different from the one we expect?" ("Spiritual Capacity," Ensign or Liahona, Nov. 2019, 21).</p>
<heading>Videos</heading>
<p>In the videos "Daily Bread: Pattern," "Daily Bread: Experience," and "Daily Bread: Change" (ChurchofJesusChrist.org), Elder D. Todd Christofferson shared insights about the miracle of manna.</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Encourage others to bear testimony.</b>Many of those you teach have powerful personal witnesses of truth to share. Invite them to share their testimonies by asking simple questions, such as, "How have you been blessed by following the prophet?" (See also Teaching in the Savior's Way, 11.)</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<graphics-caption>Illustration of the empty tomb by Maryna Kriuchenko</graphics-caption>
<heading type="date">APRIL 11–17</heading>
<heading type="ref">Easter</heading>
<heading type="title">"HE WILL SWALLOW UP DEATH IN VICTORY"</heading>
<p>As you prepare to teach on Easter Sunday, consider how you can help class members gain a deeper appreciation for and testimony of Jesus Christ's atoning sacrifice and Resurrection.</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>Perhaps you could invite class members to share what they or their family did to strengthen their faith in Jesus Christ and His Atonement during this Easter season.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>Because the Savior conquered death, we too shall live again.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Since today is Easter Sunday, consider reviewing the scriptural account of the first Easter — the Resurrection of Jesus Christ (see John 20:1–17). You could invite a class member to tell the story in his or her own words. You could also show the video "He Is Risen" (ChurchofJesusChrist.org). Class members might also enjoy singing hymns about the Savior and reading related scriptures (references are listed at the bottom of each song in Hymns). Class members could then share favorite phrases from the hymns and their feelings about the Savior.</li>
<li>To help your class appreciate how the Old Testament testifies of Jesus Christ, you could invite them to review the scriptures in the table in this week's outline in Come, Follow Me—For Individuals and Families, as well as the Book of Mormon passages that accompany the table. What do we learn about the Savior and His mission from these passages? Why is it valuable to know about these prophecies?</li>
</ul>
<heading>We can find peace and joy through the Savior's Atonement.</heading>
<ul>
<li>This week's outline in Come, Follow Me—For Individuals and Families includes a list of scriptures describing the peace and joy that come through Jesus Christ. If class members read these scriptures at home, encourage them to share their thoughts and feelings about them. Or you could read a few scriptures as a class and talk about the peace and joy we feel because of the Savior and His Atonement. How can we share these blessings with people who may be struggling to find peace and joy in their lives? You could also invite a class member to read President Russell M. Nelson's message "Joy and Spiritual Survival" (Ensign or Liahona, Nov. 2016, 81–84) during the week preceding class and to come to class prepared to share what this message teaches about finding joy in the Savior.</li>
<li>You might feel inspired to lead a discussion about how to help others find peace and joy in Christ. You could invite class members to think about someone they know — perhaps someone they minister to — who might need their support, service, or even simply to hear their testimony of Christ and His Atonement. Encourage class members to refer to the scriptures (such as those in "Additional Resources") as they consider service they might give or testimonies they might share to strengthen those around them. Invite a few class members to share their thoughts about serving as Jesus did.</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>Grey Day Golgotha, by J. Kirk Richards</graphics-caption>
<heading>Through His Atonement, Jesus Christ has power to help us overcome sin, death, trials, and weaknesses.</heading>
<ul>
<li>One way to help class members ponder the blessings that come through the Savior's Atonement could be to write on the board the headings Sin, Death, Trials, and Weaknesses. Each class member could read one of the scriptures listed in "Additional Resources" and ponder how the Savior helps us overcome the things written on the board. Class members could write their scripture references under one or more of the headings on the board and share their testimonies of the Savior and His Atonement.</li>
<li>Stories and analogies can help us understand Jesus Christ's Atonement. For instance, you could invite a class member to share one of the stories or analogies in Elder Walter F. Gonz&#225;lez's message "The Savior's Touch" (Ensign or Liahona, Nov. 2019, 90–92) or Sister Neill F. Marriott's message "Abiding in God and Repairing the Breach" (Ensign or Liahona, Nov. 2017, 10–12). What do these stories and analogies teach us about Christ's Atonement? Invite class members to work in pairs to think of their own stories or analogies.</li>
<li>What do we learn from the following verses about the price Jesus Christ paid for our salvation: Isaiah 53:3–5; Mosiah 3:7; Doctrine and Covenants 19:16–19? What price did our Heavenly Father pay? (see John 3:16).</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>Scriptures about the Atonement of Jesus Christ.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Isaiah 61:1–3</li>
<li>Ezekiel 36:26–28</li>
<li>Matthew 11:28–30</li>
<li>Luke 1:46–55</li>
<li>Romans 8:35–39</li>
<li>Alma 7:10–13</li>
<li>Alma 11:42–45</li>
<li>Moroni 10:32–33</li>
<li>Doctrine and Covenants 19:15–19</li>
<li>Moses 5:9–12</li>
</ul>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Thank your learners.</b>"Don't become so absorbed with the lesson that you forget to thank learners for their contributions. They need to know that you appreciate their willingness to share their insights and testimonies" (Teaching in the Savior's Way, 33).</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<graphics-caption>A mountain in Egypt traditionally believed to be Mount Sinai.</graphics-caption>
<heading type="date">APRIL 18–24</heading>
<heading type="ref">Exodus 18–20</heading>
<heading type="title">"ALL THAT THE LORD HATH SPOKEN WE WILL DO"</heading>
<p>Read Exodus 18–20, and record impressions you have about how to help members of your class learn from these chapters. Even simple impressions can lead to meaningful learning experiences.</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>To invite class members to share what they learned, you could write on the board<i>18, 19,</i>and<i>20</i>— the chapters they read in Exodus this week. Ask class members to write next to each chapter number the numbers of verses they would like to discuss from that chapter. As class members share their insights, ask other members of the class if they had insights about the same passages.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>EXODUS 18:13–26</heading>
<heading>We can help "bear the burden" of doing the Lord's work.</heading>
<ul>
<li>You could encourage your class to discuss the counsel Jethro gave to Moses (see Exodus 18:13–26) by asking them to imagine that they're having a conversation with someone who feels that her or his Church callings, family obligations, or other responsibilities are "too heavy" and that he or she will "wear away" (Exodus 18:18). How might the counsel in Exodus 18:13–26 help? What additional advice could we share from our personal experiences?</li>
<li>Talking about Exodus 18:13–26 might offer an opportunity to discuss how ministering can help us "bear the burden with" our leaders in the Lord's work (Exodus 18:22). What characteristics did Jethro suggest Moses look for in those who would serve as "rulers" of the people? (see Exodus 18:21). Why are those characteristics important in our efforts to minister to each other? How does ministering to family members, Church members, and others help "bear the burden" of our Church leaders? As part of your discussion, you could show one of the related videos found at ministering.ChurchofJesusChrist.org.</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>Ministering to others is one way we can take part in the Lord's work.</graphics-caption>
<heading>EXODUS 20:2–11</heading>
<heading>We should put the Lord first in our lives.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Can you think of a task that works better when we complete the most important steps first? (Examples might include solving a math equation or following a recipe). Share with the class some examples you're familiar with, and invite them to think of their own. How does completing the most important steps first relate to the commandments in Exodus 20:2–11? What do the commandments teach us about putting God first in our lives? What are things that we may be tempted to put before Him? (For some examples, see the statement in "Additional Resources.") Reviewing Exodus 20:2–11 can help members of your class reflect on their commitment to put God first.</li>
</ul>
<heading>EXODUS 20:2–17</heading>
<heading>God is merciful.</heading>
<ul>
<li>How can you help members of your class understand the importance of the Ten Commandments in our day? You could divide the class into pairs and invite them to read Exodus 20:2–17 and then discuss how obeying each of the commandments blesses them, their families, and people around them. You could also show the video "Obedience to the Ten Commandments" (ChurchofJesusChrist.org). What blessings does Heavenly Father promise us for obeying His commandments? (see, for example, Mosiah 2:41). How do these commandments demonstrate God's love for us?</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>No other gods.</heading>
<p>President Spencer W. Kimball taught that there are parallels between the ancient worship of graven images and the behavior of people today. He said:
"Idolatry is among the most serious of sins. . . .
"Modern idols or false gods can take such forms as clothes, homes, businesses, machines, automobiles, pleasure boats, and numerous other material deflectors from the path to godhood. . . .
"Intangible things make just as ready gods. Degrees and letters and titles can become idols.
"Many people build and furnish a home and buy the automobile first — and then find they «cannot afford» to pay tithing. Whom do they worship? Certainly not the Lord of heaven and earth. . . .
"Many worship the hunt, the fishing trip, the vacation, the weekend picnics and outings. Others have as their idols the games of sport, baseball, football, the bullfight, or golf. . . .
"Still another image men worship is that of power and prestige. . . . These gods of power, wealth, and influence are most demanding and are quite as real as the golden calves of the children of Israel in the wilderness" (Teachings of Presidents of the Church: Spencer W. Kimball [2006], 146–47).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Focus on a few principles.</b>"There is much to discuss in each lesson, but it is not necessary to cover everything in one class period in order to touch someone's heart — often one or two key points are enough" (Teaching in the Savior's Way, 7).</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<graphics-caption>Illustration of Jehovah appearing to Moses and 70 elders of Israel, by Jerry Harston</graphics-caption>
<heading type="date">APRIL 25–MAY 1</heading>
<heading type="ref">Exodus 24; 31–34</heading>
<heading type="title">"MY PRESENCE SHALL GO WITH THEE"</heading>
<p>Let these words from Elder Jeffrey R. Holland guide your preparation to teach: "Most people don't come to church looking merely for a few new gospel facts. . . . They come seeking a spiritual experience. . . . They want their faith fortified and their hope renewed" ("A Teacher Come from God," Ensign, May 1998, 26).</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>Class members could imagine that a friend says,
"I don't read the Old Testament; it doesn't seem relevant to my life." Ask them to respond by sharing something they have found meaningful in their recent study of the Old Testament.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>EXODUS 31:12–17</heading>
<heading>We honor the Sabbath as a sign of our commitment to the Lord.</heading>
<ul>
<li>You might begin by asking class members if they have ever had to explain to a family member or friend why they treat Sundays differently from other days. Invite them to share what they said or what they might say in the future. Reading Exodus 31:12–17 or the statement in "Additional Resources can give them additional ideas. How do our choices on the Sabbath demonstrate our commitment to Jesus Christ?</li>
<li>Even though the penalties described in Exodus 31:14–15 don't apply today, they do indicate how strongly the Lord feels about the Sabbath. Why is this commandment so important? Discussing these scriptures can help: Exodus 31:12–17; Isaiah 58:13–14; Doctrine and Covenants 59:9–13.</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>By honoring the Sabbath, we show our love for the Lord.</graphics-caption>
<heading>EXODUS 32; 34:1–17</heading>
<heading>Sin is turning away from God, but He offers a way back.</heading>
<ul>
<li>To help class members ponder and personalize the account in Exodus 32, first ask them to review the chapter individually or in groups. Then ask some class members to take the role of Israelites who grew impatient waiting for Moses to return and decided to make a golden idol. What feelings might have led them to idol worship? Other class members could try to persuade them to stay true to the Lord and His prophet. Class members could talk about what inspires them to keep their covenants. What can we do to help those who might be struggling to keep their covenants?</li>
<li>When people read the Old Testament, they are sometimes surprised at the strict punishments the Lord prescribed for sin. Exodus 34:1–9 can help them see that while God does not condone sin, He is also merciful, offering forgiveness to those who repent. Perhaps class members could read this passage and ponder questions like these: What do we learn about the Lord from these verses? Why do we need to know these things about Him? You might point out that Joseph Smith Translation, Exodus 34:7 (in Exodus 34:7, footnote e) clarifies that God will not "clear the rebellious." What might this mean? Perhaps class members could share how they have witnessed God's mercy. How is it possible for God to be both perfectly merciful and perfectly just? (see Alma 42:13–15).</li>
<li>Exodus 34:6–17 can be seen as instruction to help the Israelites repent of their sin of idolatry (described in Exodus 32). What do we find in these verses that might have helped the Israelites repent? What do we learn about the Lord and repentance from this instruction?</li>
</ul>
<heading>EXODUS 33:11–17</heading>
<heading>We need God's presence in our lives.</heading>
<ul>
<li>How will you help class members apply what the Lord said to Moses in Exodus 33:11–17? You could start by reviewing the work that God still needed Moses to fulfill (see Exodus 33:1–3). What do we find in verses 11–17 that would have strengthened and comforted Moses? Class members could think about something God wants them to do — such as fulfilling a Church calling, a family responsibility, or a ministering opportunity. They could then read the verses again. What insights do we gain about how God will support us?</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>The Sabbath is a sign.</heading>
<p>President Russell M. Nelson explained: "In my much younger years, I studied the work of others who had compiled lists of things to do and things not to do on the Sabbath. It wasn't until later that I learned from the scriptures that my conduct and my attitude on the Sabbath constituted a sign between me and my Heavenly Father [see Exodus 31:13; Ezekiel 20:12, 20]. With that understanding, I no longer needed lists of dos and don'ts. When I had to make a decision whether or not an activity was appropriate for the Sabbath, I simply asked myself, «What sign do I want to give to God?» That question made my choices about the Sabbath day crystal clear" ("The Sabbath Is a Delight," Ensign or Liahona, May 2015, 130).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Teach by the Spirit.</b>"The ultimate purpose of everything a gospel teacher does — every question, every scripture, every activity — is to invite the Spirit to build faith and to invite all to come unto Christ" (Teaching in the Savior's Way, 10).</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<heading type="date">MAY 2–8</heading>
<heading type="ref">Exodus 35–40; Leviticus 1; 16; 19</heading>
<heading type="title">"HOLINESS TO THE LORD"</heading>
<p>As you have meaningful experiences studying the scriptures, you will be able to teach and testify when you meet with class members on Sunday. What can you do to encourage class members to do the same?</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>The chapters in this week's reading use symbols to teach about Jesus Christ and His atoning sacrifice. You could begin class by inviting class members to write or draw on the board something they found in Exodus 35–40 or Leviticus 1; 16; 19 that taught them about the Savior. Invite them to talk about what they learned.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>EXODUS 35–40</heading>
<heading>The Lord wants us to become holy as He is.</heading>
<ul>
<li>As class members studied Exodus 35–40 this week, they may have pondered how elements of the ancient tabernacle turn their thoughts to Jesus Christ. If they did, encourage them to share their thoughts. The table in this week's outline in Come, Follow Me—For Individuals and Families could help with this discussion. You could also talk about what these symbols connected with the tabernacle teach about becoming more holy. How does Jesus Christ help us become more holy?</li>
<li>For many, the idea of becoming more holy may seem out of reach. How will you help class members understand that becoming holy is part of Heavenly Father's plan for us? You could read together President Henry B. Eyring's statement in "Additional Resources." What does it mean to become holy? How do our latter-day temples and the work we do there help us become more holy? (see also Doctrine and Covenants 84:19–24; 109:6–26; 128:15–18). You could then ask class members to share how these things have helped them — or others they know — become more holy.</li>
<li>The Israelites' tabernacle in the wilderness is similar in many ways to our latter-day temples. You might invite class members to list things they learned about the tabernacle in Exodus 35–40 that remind them of what we experience in the temple. If they need help, you could point them to verses in Exodus 40 referring to a veil, altars, sacred clothing, washings, and anointings. How does the temple help us come unto Christ? What can we do to focus our time in the temple on Him?</li>
</ul>
<heading>LEVITICUS 1:1–9; 16</heading>
<heading>Through the Atonement of Jesus Christ, we can be forgiven.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Although the idea of animal sacrifice may seem strange to us today, there is much we can learn from this practice about the atoning sacrifice of Jesus Christ. To begin a discussion, you could display pictures of the Savior in Gethsemane and on the cross (see Gospel Art Book, nos. 56, 57). Class members could share words that they feel relate to the atoning sacrifice of Jesus Christ. Then invite class members to review Leviticus 1:1–9 or Leviticus 16, which describe animal sacrifices, and find words that they feel also relate to the Savior's sacrifice. How can these ancient sacrifices help us better understand the Atonement of Jesus Christ? Class members could sing a hymn about the Savior and share their feelings about Him.</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>The children of Israel gave offerings for the tabernacle with "a willing heart" (Exodus 35:5). Illustration by Corbert Gauthier, &#169; Lifeway Collection/licensed from goodsalt.com</graphics-caption>
<ul>
<li>It may be helpful for class members to compare sacrifices the Lord required in Old Testament times with the sacrifices He asks of us today. For example, they could list ways we make sacrifices for the Lord and His work, such as serving in callings, paying fast offerings, doing family history work, or ministering to each other. Then you could read together Leviticus 1:1–9 and invite class members to look for elements of the offerings described in these verses that could relate to offerings the Lord asks us to give today (see 3 Nephi 9:19–20; Doctrine and Covenants 64:34). What can we learn from Moses 5:7 about how we should view our sacrifices for the Lord's work?</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>God can make us holy.</heading>
<p>President Henry B. Eyring taught:
"Greater happiness comes from greater personal holiness. . . . The scriptures teach us that among other things, we can be sanctified or become more holy when we exercise faith in Christ, demonstrate our obedience, repent, sacrifice for Him, receive sacred ordinances, and keep our covenants with Him. . . .
"The hymn «More Holiness Give Me» [Hymns, no. 131] suggests a way to pray for help in becoming more holy. The author wisely suggests that the holiness we seek is a gift from a loving God, granted over time, after all we can do" ("Holiness and the Plan of Happiness," Ensign or Liahona, Nov. 2019, 100–101, 103).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Use sacred music.</b>The messages in hymns can reinforce the doctrine in the scriptures. For instance, singing a hymn like "More Holiness Give Me" or "I Stand All Amazed" (Hymns, nos. 131, 193) could reinforce some of the messages taught in Leviticus 16 and 19.</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<heading type="date">MAY 9–15</heading>
<heading type="ref">Numbers 11–14; 20–24</heading>
<heading type="title">"REBEL NOT YE AGAINST THE LORD, NEITHER FEAR"</heading>
<p>One of the best ways to know what to focus on during class is to ask class members what they found meaningful as they studied the scriptures. This will reveal what is important to them and what they are ready to learn.</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>Sometimes all it takes to encourage class members to share insights from their study is to ask a simple question like "What did the Holy Ghost teach you as you read the scriptures this week?" Then give them time to ponder and respond.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>NUMBERS 12</heading>
<heading>Speaking against the Lord's prophet offends the Lord.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Reading Numbers 12 can help class members understand the seriousness of speaking against the Lord's prophet. You could invite class members to read this chapter and talk about how the Lord feels about His servants. Based on verses 1–2, what do you think it means to speak against the Lord's prophet? What are the dangers of doing so? What can we learn from the actions of Moses and the Israelites in verses 13 and 15?</li>
</ul>
<heading>NUMBERS 12:3</heading>
<heading>"Moses was very meek."</heading>
<ul>
<li>Some people might be surprised to read that a leader as mighty as Moses, who stood before Pharaoh and performed stunning miracles with the Lord's power, was also "very meek." You could use Numbers 12:3 to begin a discussion about what true meekness is. You might refer to the definition in "Meek, Meekness" in Guide to the Scriptures (scriptures.ChurchofJesusChrist.org). As a class, you could also look for indications of Moses's meekness in Numbers 12.</li>
<li>What other evidences of Moses's meekness can we learn from? (see, for example, Exodus 18:13–25; Numbers 11:26–29; Hebrews 11:24–27; Moses 1:10–11). You might also read and discuss how the Savior demonstrated meekness (see Matthew 11:29; 27:11–14; Luke 22:41–42; John 13:4–5). What do the examples of Moses and the Savior — or of people we know — teach us about meekness? Why does God want us to be meek?</li>
</ul>
<heading>NUMBERS 13–14</heading>
<heading>With faith in the Lord, we can have hope for the future.</heading>
<ul>
<li>As you discuss the story about the 12 Israelites scouting out the promised land and giving their report, consider asking class members how they feel this story could apply to situations they face. To help, you could invite class members to list things from Numbers 13:23–33 that could be compared to something in our lives. For example, the promised land might represent something the Lord wants us to accomplish, the clusters of grapes could be blessings, the giants could be the challenges we'll face, and so on. Encourage class members to share what they feel the Lord might want them to learn from this story.</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>Ten of the Israelite spies were afraid; Joshua and Caleb had faith. &#9400; Lifeway Collection/licensed from goodsalt.com</graphics-caption>
<heading>NUMBERS 21:4–9</heading>
<heading>If we look to Jesus Christ in faith, He can heal us spiritually.</heading>
<ul>
<li>To help class members discuss the account in Numbers 21:4–9 and build their faith in the Savior, you could write questions like these on the board:<i>What does the brass serpent represent? What might the snakebites represent? Why did some people refuse to look upon the brass serpent? How can we "look upon" it today?</i>Class members could share answers they find as they read Numbers 21:4–9; 1 Nephi 17:40–41; Alma 33:18–22; Helaman 8:13–15. What are some of the simple things the Savior invites us to do to receive His healing? Why is it sometimes hard to do such simple things? (see "Additional Resources" for some thoughts on this). Perhaps class members could share how doing these things has brought the Savior's power into their lives.</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>"Small and simple things."</heading>
<p>Elder L. Whitney Clayton told of a bishop who counseled ward members facing a variety of difficult challenges in their lives:
"His counsel to ward members very often included getting back to simple practices of faith, such as studying the Book of Mormon [&#8321;] . . . paying tithing, and serving in the Church with devotion. Frequently, however, their response to him was one of skepticism: . . . What does doing any of<i>those</i>things have to do with the issues<i>I'm</i>facing?'
". . . Those who are deliberate about doing the «small and simple things» [Alma 37:6] — obeying in seemingly little ways — are blessed with faith and strength that go far beyond the actual acts of obedience themselves and, in fact, may seem totally unrelated to them" ("Whatsoever He Saith unto You, Do It," Ensign or Liahona, May 2017, 98).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Focus on what's most important.</b>It is not possible to cover every story or every principle. Follow the Spirit, and consider the needs of class members as you decide how to spend class time. Remember that the home, not the classroom, is the center of gospel learning.</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<graphics-caption>Illustration of Moses on Mount Nebo, &#9400; Providence Collection/licensed from goodsalt.com</graphics-caption>
<heading type="date">MAY 16–22</heading>
<heading type="ref">Deuteronomy 6–8; 15; 18; 29–30; 34</heading>
<heading type="title">"BEWARE LEST THOU FORGET THE LORD"</heading>
<p>Moses was inspired to teach the children of Israel based on their needs (see Deuteronomy 6:1). As you study Deuteronomy, seek inspiration to know what principles to teach, based on class members' needs.</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>Because Deuteronomy contains Moses's final words to the children of Israel, you might invite class members to share something they found in Deuteronomy that they would want to include in their final words to their children or grandchildren. As they share, ask them to explain why they chose those words.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>DEUTERONOMY 6:4–7, 20–25; 8:2–5, 11–17; 29:18–20; 30:6–10, 15–20</heading>
<heading>The Lord wants us to love Him with all our hearts.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Throughout Deuteronomy, there are passages that can prompt us to think about the spiritual condition of our hearts. To help class members share their thoughts about these passages, you could draw a heart on the board. Then divide the following scriptures among class members: Deuteronomy 6:4–7, 20–25; 8:2–5, 11–17; 29:18–20; 30:6–10, 15–20. Invite class members to write the reference inside the heart if it teaches about something we should have in our hearts or to write the reference outside the heart if it teaches something we should avoid. What does it mean to devote our whole hearts to Heavenly Father?</li>
<li>How do we explain to our family and others why we obey God's commandments? After pondering this question, class members could read Deuteronomy 6:4–7, 20–25 or the statement in "Additional Resources" and share their thoughts. How do these insights affect the way we feel about commandments or covenants?</li>
</ul>
<heading>DEUTERONOMY 6:4–9, 20–25</heading>
<heading>"Teach [the Lord's words] diligently unto thy children."</heading>
<ul>
<li>Sometimes it helps to hear ideas about ways others are teaching and learning the gospel in their homes. Discussing how class members are following the counsel in Deuteronomy 6:4–9, 20–25 can give your class an opportunity to learn from each other. What do we do to teach and "talk of" (verse 7) the word of God as these verses describe? What experiences can we share in which the Lord guided us in our efforts?</li>
</ul>
<heading>DEUTERONOMY 15:1–15</heading>
<heading>Helping the needy involves generous hands and willing hearts.</heading>
<ul>
<li>We haven't yet arrived at the day "when there shall be no poor among you" (Deuteronomy 15:4), so the principles about helping the poor in Deuteronomy 15 are still valuable, even if the particular practices regarding debts and servants have changed. You could invite class members to review verses 1–15 and find principles about helping the poor and needy that they would like to discuss. Questions like these could help the discussion: What does it mean to "open thine hand wide" to those in need? (verses 8, 11). What role does our heart play in helping others? (see verses 7, 9–10). What can we learn about helping the needy from the Lord's example? (see verse 15).</li>
</ul>
<heading>DEUTERONOMY 29:9; 30:15–20</heading>
<heading>The Lord invites us to choose between "life and good, and death and evil."</heading>
<ul>
<li>It might be interesting to compare Moses's words in Deuteronomy with some of Lehi's final teachings to his family in 2 Nephi 1–4. Perhaps class members could find similarities and differences between these passages: Deuteronomy 29:9 and 2 Nephi 4:4; Deuteronomy 30:15–20 and 2 Nephi 2:26–29. How did Lehi expand on what Moses taught? Why are words like<i>life</i>and<i>death</i>a good way to describe our choices to "keep" or "turn away" from God's commandments? (Deuteronomy 30:16–17). Class members could share what they find in these passages that inspires them to "choose life" (Deuteronomy 30:19).</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>We keep our covenants because we love God.</heading>
<p>President Linda K. Burton taught:
"Of all the reasons we ought to be more diligent in our covenant keeping, this reason is more compelling than all — love. . . .
"«If we fully appreciated the many blessings which are ours through the redemption made for us, there is nothing that the Lord could ask of us that we would not anxiously and willingly do» [Joseph Fielding Smith, «Importance of the Sacrament Meeting,» Relief Society Magazine, Oct. 1943, 592]. According to this statement by President Joseph Fielding Smith, covenant keeping is one way to express our love for the incomprehensible, infinite Atonement of our Savior and Redeemer and the perfect love of our Father in Heaven" ("The Power, Joy, and Love of Covenant Keeping," Ensign or Liahona, Nov. 2013, 114).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Listen.</b>"Listening is an act of love. . . . Ask Heavenly Father to help you understand what your class members say. As you pay careful attention to their spoken and unspoken messages, you will come to better understand their needs, their concerns, and their desires" (Teaching in the Savior's Way, 34).</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<graphics-caption>Illustration of Moses ordaining Joshua, by Darrell Thomas</graphics-caption>
<heading type="date">MAY 23–29</heading>
<heading type="ref">Joshua 1–8; 23–24</heading>
<heading type="title">"BE STRONG AND OF A GOOD COURAGE"</heading>
<p>As you read Joshua 1–8 and 23–24, consider the counsel to "meditate therein day and night" (Joshua 1:8). Pay attention to the promptings that come. These may lead to teaching ideas for your class.</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>Invite class members to share a passage from their reading this week that increased their faith in Jesus Christ. For example, they may have pondered ways Joshua's mission reminds them of Jesus Christ's. Why are we grateful for the stories in the book of Joshua?</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>JOSHUA 1:1–9</heading>
<heading>"Be strong and of a good courage."</heading>
<ul>
<li>Joshua was told, "Be strong and of a good courage" several times (see Deuteronomy 31:7, 23; Joshua 1:6–7, 9). Perhaps class members would benefit from discussing what the Lord means by this phrase. They could search Joshua 1:1–9 for counsel the Lord gave Joshua to help him be strong and courageous. They could also share examples of people they know of who have these traits. How did Joshua show strength and courage in the accounts found in the book of Joshua? (for example, see chapters 3, 6, and 8). Class members could share how they are trying to be strong and courageous for Christ.</li>
</ul>
<heading>JOSHUA 1:8</heading>
<heading>The word of God can make our way prosperous.</heading>
<ul>
<li>To encourage class members in their personal and family scripture study, you could read Joshua 1:8 as a class. What do we learn from this verse about how to study the scriptures? Perhaps class members could share what they are doing to "meditate" in the scriptures "day and night." How has the Lord made our "way prosperous" and given us "good success" as we studied His word?</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>The word of God can "make [our] way prosperous" (Joshua 1:8).</graphics-caption>
<heading>JOSHUA 3–4</heading>
<heading>We can experience God's "wonders."</heading>
<ul>
<li>Perhaps class members would benefit from a brief review of the account of the Israelites crossing the Jordan River. You could divide the class into pairs and invite each pair to tell the story to each other, taking turns saying one sentence at a time (encourage them to look in Joshua 3 if they need help remembering the story). Then, as a class, they could discuss any details that stood out to them. What do we learn from this story that can help us experience the "wonders" of the Lord in our lives? (verse 5). What "wonders" has He done for us? Why is it important that each generation have spiritual experiences that teach them that "the Lord. . . is mighty"? (Joshua 4:24).</li>
<li>Even though we all need to have our own faith-building experiences, remembering what the Lord has done for our ancestors is also important. According to Joshua 4, what did the Israelites do to help future generations remember the crossing of the Jordan River? (see Joshua 4:1–7). What are we doing to ensure that our experiences are not forgotten by future generations?</li>
</ul>
<heading>JOSHUA 6–8</heading>
<heading>Obedience brings God's power into my life.</heading>
<ul>
<li>This week's outline in<i>Come, Follow Me—For Individuals and Families</i>suggests comparing the Israelites' battles against the Canaanites in Joshua 6–8 with our personal battles against temptation. You might ask class members what thoughts or impressions they had as they read these chapters with this comparison in mind. Or you could point them to specific verses that seem relevant to our battles to avoid sin, and they could talk about what those verses teach about gaining access to God's power in our lives. Some of these verses might include Joshua 6:1–5, 18, 20; 7:11–13.</li>
</ul>
<heading>JOSHUA 23–24</heading>
<heading>"Choose you this day whom ye will serve."</heading>
<ul>
<li>Perhaps it would help class members apply Joshua 23–24 to themselves if they imagined that they were Israelites hearing Joshua give this counsel at the end of his life. You might give them a few verses to read silently and then ask them to share something from those verses that would have inspired them to stay faithful to the Lord. They could also share how they have personally made the decision about "whom [they] will serve" (Joshua 24:15). Why did they make this decision?</li>
<li>You could invite class members to pick a phrase from Joshua 23–24 that inspires them to choose to serve God and then create a poster or meme with this phrase to display at home or on social media.</li>
</ul>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Spiritual growth happens at home.</b>Members of your class need to have their own spiritual experiences outside of class in order to stay spiritually strong. Find ways to use the brief time you have with them to inspire them to find spiritual nourishment in the scriptures at home — individually and with their families. (See Teaching in the Savior's Way, 18.)</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<graphics-caption>Illustration of Deborah leading Israel's armies, Lifeway Collection/licensed from goodsalt.com</graphics-caption>
<heading type="date">MAY 30–JUNE 5</heading>
<heading type="ref">Judges 2–4; 6–8; 13–16</heading>
<heading type="title">"THE LORD RAISED UP A DELIVERER"</heading>
<p>Remember that the most important teacher is the Holy Ghost. How can you help class members be taught by the Holy Ghost as you discuss truths from the book of Judges?</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>Write on the board the names of some of the judges found in Judges 2–4; 6–8; 13–16 (such as Deborah, Barak, Gideon, and Samson). Give class members a few minutes to review these chapters and write under one of the names on the board a truth they learned from that person's experience.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>JUDGES 2:11–19; 3:5–12; 4:1–16</heading>
<heading>The Lord offers deliverance when we stray.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Examining Israel's cycle of rebellion, sorrow, repentance, and deliverance can help class members recognize God's power of deliverance in their own lives. Class members could work in small groups to find the cycle described in Judges 2:11–19; 3:5–12. How were the children of Israel delivered from their cycle of sin and suffering? What do we learn from the book of Judges about how we can escape from sin and suffering? What are some ways God delivers us? You could also invite class members to find and share scriptures that testify of the Lord as our Deliverer and Redeemer (for example, 2 Samuel 22:1–3; Psalm 40:16–17; 1 Nephi 1:19–20; Mosiah 23:21–23; Doctrine and Covenants 138:23).</li>
<li>Judges 2:19 records that the Israelites repeatedly turned away from God toward idolatry. Perhaps class members could summarize this verse in the form of a warning for themselves. In what ways do we sometimes "bow down" to "other gods"? How can the Lord help us change our "stubborn way"?</li>
<li>To begin a discussion about how Deborah and Barak delivered Israel from the Canaanites, you could ask a class member to summarize the story for the class (it might help to contact the class member a few days in advance so he or she can be prepared). The class could talk about qualities Deborah had that impress them. How did Deborah inspire the children of Israel to follow the Lord? Perhaps you could read together Judges 4:14 and discuss the meaning of Deborah's faithful declaration: "Is not the Lord gone out before thee?" How does the Lord go out before us? (see also Doctrine and Covenants 84:87–88).</li>
</ul>
<heading>JUDGES 6–8</heading>
<heading>The Lord can work miracles when we trust in His ways.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Studying Gideon's call to serve can inspire class members in their own service. You might ask them to read and discuss Judges 6:11–16. What can we learn from this experience? To help them learn from Judges 7, you could invite one or more class members to pretend to be Gideon's soldiers and tell the story from the soldiers' perspective. Other class members could ask them questions about the soldiers' experience. What parallels do we see between this story and what is happening in our lives? What do we learn about the Lord from this story?</li>
</ul>
<heading>JUDGES 13–16</heading>
<heading>Strength comes from faithfulness to our covenants with God.</heading>
<ul>
<li>How can you help class members discover both the inspiring truths and the important warnings from the story of Samson? One way could be to invite half the class to review Judges 14–16 looking for verses that show that the Lord was with Samson. The other half could look for verses that show that Samson was not fully committed to the Lord. Ask class members to share what they found. What does Samson's life teach us about keeping the covenants we make with God? The statement by Sister Ann M. Dibb in "Additional Resources" may be helpful.</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>Samson Puts Down the Pillars, by James Tissot and others</graphics-caption>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>A lesson from Samson's life.</heading>
<p>Sister Ann M. Dibb taught: "Samson was born with great potential. His mother was promised, «He shall begin to deliver Israel out of the hand of the Philistines» [Judges 13:5]. But as Samson grew, he looked more to the world's temptations than to God's direction. He made choices because they «pleaseth [him] well» [Judges 14:3] rather than because those choices were right. Repeatedly, the scriptures use the phrase «and he went down» [Judges 14:7] as they tell of Samson's journeys, actions, and choices. Instead of arising and shining forth to fulfill his great potential, Samson was overcome by the world, lost his God-given power, and died a tragic, early death" ("Arise and Shine Forth," Ensign or Liahona, May 2012, 118).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Reserve time for learners to share.</b>"When learners share what they are learning, they not only feel the Spirit and strengthen their own testimonies, but they also encourage other class members to discover truths for themselves. . . . Reserve time for student sharing in every lesson." (Teaching in the Savior's Way, 30.)</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<graphics-caption>Whither Thou Goest, by Sandy Freckleton Gagon</graphics-caption>
<heading type="date">JUNE 6–12</heading>
<heading type="ref">Ruth; 1 Samuel 1–3</heading>
<heading type="title">"MY HEART REJOICETH IN THE LORD"</heading>
<p>It's important to be prepared to teach, but make sure that your plans include giving class members opportunities to share what they have learned.</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>To encourage class members to share what they learned this week, you could invite them to write on the board a word or phrase from Ruth 1–4 or 1 Samuel 1–3 that inspired them during their individual or family study. Read a few aloud, asking class members to share how these words and phrases inspired them.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>RUTH; 1 SAMUEL 1–2</heading>
<heading>Christ can turn tragedy into triumph.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Though your class members may have individual trials that are different from those of Ruth and Hannah, they can learn from the ways these faithful women responded to loss and heartache. To help class members do this, you could divide them into small groups and invite each group to read a chapter from Ruth 1–4 or 1 Samuel 1. On the board, you could write questions like these:<i>What trials were Ruth or Hannah facing? How did they show their trust in the Lord during their trials?</i>The groups could look for answers to one or more of the questions and share what they find. What do we learn from these accounts about how the Lord can help us in our trials?</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>For This Child I Prayed, by Elspeth Young</graphics-caption>
<ul>
<li>Not everyone who prays for a child receives one, and not everyone whose spouse dies remarries. But our personal challenges, no matter what they are, can be opportunities to turn to the Savior and strengthen our faith in Him. You might ask class members to read Ruth 2:11–12 and 1 Samuel 1:9–11 and talk about how Ruth's and Hannah's trials affected their relationships with the Lord. Class members could also share how their own faith was strengthened because they turned to Jesus Christ during times of trial. To support this discussion, you could invite one or more class members to come prepared to share insights from one of the following: Sister Reyna I. Aburto's message "Thru Cloud and Sunshine, Lord, Abide with Me!" (Ensign or Liahona, Nov. 2019, 57–60); the section titled "The Joy of Overcoming through Christ" from Elder D. Todd Christofferson's message "The Joy of the Saints" (Ensign or Liahona, Nov. 2019, 16–17); or President Elaine S. Dalton's words in "Additional Resources." Ask class members to share what they learned about how our trials can be opportunities for greater faith in Jesus Christ.</li>
</ul>
<heading>1 SAMUEL 2:18–36; 3</heading>
<heading>We should listen to and obey the voice of the Lord.</heading>
<ul>
<li>There may be people in your class who, like Samuel, have heard the Lord's voice but did not recognize it as His. You might invite class members to review 1 Samuel 3, looking for what Samuel did that could help us in our efforts to hear and obey the Lord's voice. You might also ask two class members to reenact the interactions between Samuel and Eli.</li>
<li>Sometimes we find ourselves in a situation like Eli's — we have an opportunity to help someone recognize the voice of the Lord. Perhaps class members could share how they have done this for friends, family members, or others. What scriptures or experiences have we shared to help others understand how the Lord communicates with us? (see, for example, Doctrine and Covenants 6:22–23; 8:2–3; 9:7–9).</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>We are never alone.</heading>
<p>President Elaine S. Dalton taught: .
"Life's journey sometimes takes us on unexpected paths. There are twists and turns in the road that none of us can anticipate. But with each of these twists and turns there is also opportunity — opportunity to choose our response and our plan of action. Difficulties in life can be opportunities to help us draw closer to the Savior and to trust in Him more fully. In the process of living close to Him each day, we develop Christlike attributes and qualities. . . .
"Like Ruth and Hannah, all of us will experience adversity. We may not always understand the Lord's design for our lives, but it is my testimony that we are never alone. He is ever with us, and He promises us, «Ye cannot behold with your natural eyes, for the present time, the design of your God concerning those things which shall come hereafter, and the glory which shall follow after much tribulation» [Doctrine and Covenants 58:3]" ("Lessons from Ruth and Hannah," Ensign, Apr. 2006, 35, 37).</p>
<p>See also John 14:18; Alma 38:5.</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>It's OK to say "I don't know."</b>While you should try your best to answer questions your class members have, the Lord doesn't expect you to know everything. When you don't know how to answer something, admit that and bear sincere testimony of what you do know. (See 1 Nephi 11:16–17; Teaching in the Savior's Way, 24.)</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<graphics-caption>David and Goliath, by Steve Nethercott</graphics-caption>
<heading type="date">JUNE 13–19</heading>
<heading type="ref">1 Samuel 8–10; 13; 15–18</heading>
<heading type="title">"THE BATTLE IS THE LORD'S"</heading>
<p>As you prepare to teach, remember that class members have likely had meaningful experiences studying the scriptures at home. What can you do to build upon those experiences?</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>To encourage class members to share what they learned this week, give them time to think about any impressions they had about 1 Samuel 8–10; 13; 15–18. Then ask them to share a verse that inspired an impression.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>1 SAMUEL 9:15–17; 10:1–12; 16:1–13</heading>
<heading>God calls people by prophecy to serve in His kingdom.</heading>
<ul>
<li>The accounts of God choosing Saul and David by prophecy and revelation could help class members understand how people are chosen to serve in the Church today. You could invite class members to read 1 Samuel 9:15–17; 10:1–12; and 16:1–13, looking for passages that could help them understand what it means to be "called of God" (Articles of Faith 1:5). What difference does it make, for the people called and for those who sustain them, to know that God chooses people to serve in His Church?</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>Illustration of Samuel anointing Saul, &#169; Lifeway Collection/licensed from goodsalt.com</graphics-caption>
<heading>1 SAMUEL 13:5–14; 15</heading>
<heading>"To obey is better than sacrifice."</heading>
<ul>
<li>To discuss why it is important to be obedient to the Lord, you could invite the class to review 1 Samuel 13:5–14 and look for attitudes and behaviors that led to Saul's downfall. What can we learn from Saul's mistakes?</li>
<li>While we don't know all the reasons Saul was commanded to kill all of the Amalekites and their animals, there are lessons to learn from his response to that commandment. To help class members identify these lessons, you could write on the board<i>To obey is better than</i>. . . and invite class members to ponder this phrase as you review together events from 1 Samuel 15. What are some good things we do in our lives that we sometimes choose instead of obeying God? Why is obedience to God better than those other good things?</li>
</ul>
<heading>1 SAMUEL 16:6–7</heading>
<heading>"The Lord looketh on the heart."</heading>
<ul>
<li>After reading 1 Samuel 16:6–7, class members could share their thoughts about what it means to look "on the heart" (verse 7). How can we learn to see the way the Lord sees? Class members could share experiences that taught them the importance of looking on the heart rather than the outward appearance.</li>
</ul>
<heading>1 SAMUEL 17</heading>
<heading>The Lord can help us overcome any challenge.</heading>
<ul>
<li>In this week's outline in<i>Come, Follow Me—For Individuals and Families,</i>class members may have pondered the words of various people found in 1 Samuel 17. Consider asking the class to share what they learned from this activity. In particular, what did they learn about David?</li>
<li>Some members of your class are likely facing challenges that may seem as daunting as Goliath did to Saul and his army. How can you use the story of David and Goliath to help class members face their challenges with faith in the Lord? Perhaps you could display a picture of David and Goliath (such as the one in this week's outline in<i>Come, Follow Me—For Individuals and Families</i>). Class members could then list on the board some things that might be "Goliaths" in our day. Then they could find verses in 1 Samuel 17 that demonstrate David's faith, which enabled him to defeat Goliath (see also the statement in "Additional Resources"). Perhaps class members could share experiences in which they felt the Lord helping to fight their battles.</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>Overpowering our Goliaths.</heading>
<p>President Gordon B. Hinckley taught:
"There are Goliaths all around you, hulking giants with evil intent to destroy you. These are not nine-foot-tall men, but they are men and institutions that control attractive but evil things that may challenge and weaken and destroy you. . . .
". . . But you need not fear if you have the slingshot of truth in your hands. . . . You have the stones of virtue and honor and integrity to use against these enemies who would like to conquer you. Insofar as you are concerned, you can hit them «between the eyes,» to use a figurative expression. You can triumph over them by disciplining yourselves to avoid them. You can say to the whole lot of them as David said to Goliath, «Thou comest to me with a sword, and with a spear, and with a shield: but I come to thee in the name of the Lord of hosts, the God of the armies of Israel, whom thou hast defied» 1 Samuel 17:45]" ("Overpowering the Goliaths in Our Lives," Ensign, May 1983, 46, 51).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Your call is inspired.</b>As a teacher, you have been called by God to bless His children. As you live worthy of His help, He will give you the revelation you seek. (See Teaching in Savior's Way, 5.)</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<graphics-caption>King David Enthroned, by Jerry Miles Harston</graphics-caption>
<heading type="date">JUNE 20–26</heading>
<heading type="ref">2 Samuel 5–7; 11–12; 1 Kings 3; 8; 11</heading>
<heading type="title">"THY KINGDOM SHALL BE ESTABLISHED FOR EVER"</heading>
<p>As you study the scriptures, prayerfully seek to know which principles will be most meaningful to members of your class so you can focus on their needs.</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>To find out what class members found meaningful in their scripture study, you could ask them to write the reference for a passage that inspired them on slips of paper and then place the papers in a container. Then class members could select papers from the container, and the class could read and discuss the passages.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>2 SAMUEL 6:1–8</heading>
<heading>We must do God's work in His way.</heading>
<ul>
<li>You might ask class members to read 2 Samuel 6:1–8 and consider what warnings this story might have for us today. The statement by Brigham Young in "Additional Resources" could help. What are some ways we might try to do God's work in a way other than how He has directed? Why is this dangerous? Perhaps class members could share experiences in which they learned to trust the direction the Lord gives for accomplishing His work.</li>
</ul>
<heading>2 SAMUEL 11</heading>
<heading>We should always be on guard against sin.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Learning from David's tragic choices recorded in 2 Samuel 11 can help us avoid similar mistakes. Perhaps the class could read together 2 Samuel 11:1–17 and identify choices that David made that led him to sin. What could David have done differently? You could also ask class members to write down a sentence that could help inspire someone to avoid sin, based on what they've learned from 2 Samuel 11. Invite a few class members to share their ideas.</li>
<li>You might use 2 Samuel 11 to discuss the dangers of pornography and other sexual sins. To do this, the class could review together portions of Elder L. Whitney Clayton's message "Blessed Are All the Pure in Heart" (Ensign or Liahona, Nov. 2007, 51–53). What counsel does Elder Clayton give about the dangers of pornography? You could also watch the video "To Look Upon" (ChurchofJesusChrist.org). How can the Savior help us overcome these temptations or behaviors?</li>
<li>Perhaps class members could share ideas they've found helpful in their efforts to protect their families from pornography or overcome the effects of pornography. Sister Linda S. Reeves's message "Protection from Pornography — a Christ-Focused Home" can help (Ensign or Liahona, May 2014, 15–17; see also "Additional Resources").</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>The temple is the house of the Lord.</graphics-caption>
<heading>1 KINGS 8:22–61</heading>
<heading>Temples bring blessings.</heading>
<ul>
<li>1 Kings 8 describes blessings that Solomon sought for his people as the temple was completed. You might divide verses 22–61 among class members and ask them to share something they find in their verses that inspires them in their temple worship. Class members could share how worshipping in the Lord's house has blessed their lives.</li>
</ul>
<heading>1 KINGS 8:61; 11:1–11</heading>
<heading>"His heart was not perfect with the Lord."</heading>
<ul>
<li>What does it mean to "let [our] heart. . . be perfect with the Lord"? (1 Kings 8:61). Is that different from our actions being perfect? How so? As class members ponder these questions, they could read 1 Kings 11:1–11 and notice what the Lord says about Solomon's heart. How can we avoid the mistakes he made?</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>Steadying the ark.</heading>
<p>President Brigham Young taught: "Let the Kingdom alone, the Lord steadies the ark; and if it does jostle, and appear to need steadying, if the way is a little sideling sometimes, and to all appearance threatens its overthrow, be careful how you stretch forth your hand to steady it; let us not be too officious in meddling with that which does not concern us; let it alone, it is the Lord's work" (Discourses of Brigham Young, sel. John A. Widtsoe [1954], 66).</p>
<heading>Protecting families from pornography.</heading>
<p>Sister Linda S. Reeves taught: "How do we protect our children and youth? Filters are useful tools, but the greatest filter in the world, the only one that will ultimately work, is the personal internal filter that comes from a deep and abiding testimony of our Heavenly Father's love and our Savior's atoning sacrifice for each one of us" ("Protection from Pornography — a Christ-Focused Home," Ensign or Liahona, May 2014, 16; see also Joy D. Jones, "Addressing Pornography: Protect, Respond, and Heal," Ensign, Oct. 2019, 22–27).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Ensure you are teaching true doctrine.</b>"Continually ask yourself, «How will what I am teaching help my class members build faith in Christ, repent, make and keep covenants with God, and receive the Holy Ghost?»" (Teaching in the Savior's Way, 20).</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<graphics-caption>Elijah Contends against the Priests of Baal, by Jerry Harston</graphics-caption>
<heading type="date">JUNE 27–JULY 3</heading>
<heading type="ref">1 Kings 17–19</heading>
<heading type="title">"IF THE LORD BE GOD, FOLLOW HIM"</heading>
<p>The purpose of the scriptures — and your class — is to build faith in Heavenly Father and Jesus Christ. Let this purpose guide the decisions you make about what to teach and what questions to ask.</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>To help class members share insights about 1 Kings 17–19, you might invite them to think of a title for each of these chapters. What verses made them think of these titles?</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>1 KINGS 17:8–16; 19:19–21</heading>
<heading>An invitation to sacrifice is an opportunity to exercise our faith.</heading>
<ul>
<li>The example of the widow of Zarephath may inspire members of your class during times when their faith is tested. You might start by asking them to list choices that require faith in Jesus Christ. Then they could read the account in 1 Kings 17:8–16 and talk about what this story teaches them about exercising faith. Encourage class members to share their feelings about the widow and how her example inspires them to exercise their faith. How is her faith similar to the faith Elisha demonstrated in 1 Kings 19:19–21? Perhaps class members would be willing to share sacrifices they have made for the Lord and how He has blessed them.</li>
<li>The story of the widow of Zarephath can also teach us about the blessings that come from sacrifice. You could ask class members to ponder how they would respond to statements like these: "I can't afford to pay tithing" or "I'm too busy to accept a ministering assignment." What does 1 Kings 17:8–16 teach us that might apply to these statements? How does our knowledge of the Savior help us when we are asked to make sacrifices? Elder Lynn G. Robbins's words in "Additional Resources" could also help.</li>
</ul>
<heading>1 KINGS 18:17–39</heading>
<heading>"If the Lord be God, follow him."</heading>
<ul>
<li>A discussion about 1 Kings 18:17–39 could help class members become more committed to following Jesus Christ and trusting Him. After reviewing the story with the class, you could write on the board the question Elijah asked the people of Israel: "How long halt ye between two opinions?" (verse 21). Let class members share what they feel this question means. What are some reasons the people might have been "halting" (which can mean hesitating, wavering, or limping) between following the Lord and following Baal? Why are we sometimes indecisive about following Jesus Christ? Class members could share experiences that have helped them choose to follow the Savior.</li>
</ul>
<heading>1 KINGS 19:1–12</heading>
<heading>The Lord often speaks in quiet, simple ways.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Many people struggle to recognize when the Lord is communicating with them. To help class members better recognize the Lord's voice, you could invite them to read 1 Kings 19:1–12 and share what Elijah learned. Perhaps class members could share experiences that have taught them about different ways the Lord speaks to them. You might want to share the video "How Can I Feel the Holy Ghost More Often?" (from "Face to Face with President Eyring and Elder Holland" [worldwide youth broadcast, Mar. 4, 2017], ChurchofJesusChrist.org).</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>A symbolic depiction of 1 Kings 19:11–12. The Prophet, &#169; Robert Booth Charles/Bridgeman Images</graphics-caption>
<ul>
<li>To help prompt discussion about the phrase "still small voice," you could display objects (or pictures of objects) that might help class members ponder the phrase. Class members could suggest other examples. Why are the words "still" and "small" good ways to describe the voice of the Spirit? For other descriptions, class members could read scriptures like Helaman 5:30; 3 Nephi 11:3–7; Doctrine and Covenants 6:22–23; 8:2–3; 9:8–9; 11:12–14; 36:2. They may be able to share other scriptures about recognizing the Spirit. What do these scriptures suggest about what we must do to hear the Lord's voice? The videos "Feeling the Holy Ghost" or "Voice of the Spirit" could be helpful (ChurchofJesusChrist.org).</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>The widow of Zarephath.</heading>
<p>Elder Lynn G. Robbins said: "Elijah understood the doctrine that blessings come after the trial of our faith [see Ether 12:6; Doctrine and Covenants 132:5]. He wasn't being selfish. As the Lord's servant, Elijah was there to give, not to take [see 1 Kings 17:13–16]. . . . One reason the Lord illustrates doctrines with the most extreme circumstances is to eliminate excuses. If the Lord expects even the poorest widow to pay her mite, where does that leave all others who find that it is not convenient or easy to sacrifice?" ("Tithing — a Commandment Even for the Destitute," Ensign or Liahona, May 2005, 35).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Be a humble instrument of the Spirit.</b>"Your purpose as a teacher is not to make an impressive presentation but rather to help others receive the influence of the Holy Ghost, who is the true teacher" (Teaching in the Savior's Way, 10).</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<graphics-caption>Illustration of Elisha showing his servant the chariots of fire, &#169; Review &amp; Herald Publishing/licensed from goodsalt.com</graphics-caption>
<heading type="date">JULY 4–10</heading>
<heading type="ref">2 Kings 2–7</heading>
<heading type="title">"THERE IS A PROPHET IN ISRAEL"</heading>
<p>As you prepare to teach, read 2 Kings 2–7 seeking inspiration for your own life. Then listen for promptings about messages that will bless members of your class.</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>Sometimes class members need time to briefly review the chapters they read before they can share insights from their personal scripture study. Try providing a few minutes for this at the beginning of class; then invite class members to share something they learned.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>2 KINGS 2–6</heading>
<heading>God can work miracles in our lives.</heading>
<ul>
<li>As you discuss the miracles in 2 Kings 2–6, it might be helpful to ask class members to define the word miracle. You might share this insight from President Howard W. Hunter: "[Miracles] are the manifestations of [God's] power which we are helpless to explain or to fully understand. . . . These signs and marvels were most evident in the life and ministry of Jesus Christ, the very Son of God himself. But startling and wonder-filled as they were, Christ's many miracles were only reflections of those greater marvels which his Father had performed before him and continues to perform all around us. . . . There will always be plenty of miracles if we have eyes to see and ears to hear" ("The God That Doest Wonders," Ensign, May 1989, 15–16). How do these insights help us see God's hand in our lives?</li>
<li>Consider asking class members to list some of the miracles described in 2 Kings 2–6. What do we learn about the Lord from these miracles? Class members might also be willing to talk about miracles — big or small — that they or their families have experienced. How can we better recognize God's miracles in our lives — including those that are different from what we hoped for?</li>
<li>Class members might find it inspiring to compare some of the miracles Elisha performed with some that Jesus Christ performed (see 2 Kings 4:8–37 and Luke 7:11–16; 2 Kings 4:42–44 and John 6:1–13; 2 Kings 5:1–15 and Luke 17:11–19). What do these miracles teach us about the Savior and His prophets?</li>
</ul>
<heading>2 KINGS 5:1–19</heading>
<heading>If we are humble and obedient, Jesus Christ can heal us.</heading>
<ul>
<li>One lesson we can learn from the healing of Naaman's leprosy is the importance of humility. To begin a discussion, you could write on the board Naaman's pride and Naaman's humility. Class members could search 2 Kings 5:1–19 and write on the board phrases that illustrate Naaman's pride or humility. How are we sometimes like Naaman? How are we sometimes like his servants? How have we come to know what Naaman came to know?</li>
<li>Another lesson we can learn from this story is the value of obeying God in small things. You might start by reading 2 Kings 5:9–12 and asking for class members' thoughts about why Naaman "went away in a rage" (verse 12). Why do we sometimes prefer doing "some great thing" God asks of us, rather than simple things? (verse 13). What is the value of doing these simple things?</li>
</ul>
<heading>2 KINGS 6:8–23</heading>
<heading>"They that be with us are more than they that be with them."</heading>
<ul>
<li>We all have moments when we feel alone or afraid. Consider how discussing the account in 2 Kings 6:8–23 might help class members who feel this way. You could begin by simply asking class members what impresses them about these verses. They could also share experiences when "the Lord opened [their] eyes" (verse 17) and helped them see that they weren't alone (see also "Additional Resources"). How can we help each other to "fear not"? (verse 16).</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>"Open our spiritual eyes."</heading>
<p>Referring to the account in 2 Kings 6:8–23, Elder Ronald A. Rasband said:
"We may or may not have chariots of fire sent to dispel our fears and conquer our demons, but the lesson is clear. The Lord is with us, mindful of us and blessing us in ways only He can do. Prayer can call down the strength and the revelation that we need to center our thoughts on Jesus Christ and His atoning sacrifice. The Lord knew that at times we would feel fear. I have been there and so have you. . . . In this Church we may be few in number by the way the world counts influence, but when we open our spiritual eyes, «they that be with us are more than they that be with them» [2 Kings 6:16]" ("Be Not Troubled," Ensign or Liahona, Nov. 2018, 18–19).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Refer learners to the scriptures.</b>Whenever you can, encourage class members to turn to the scriptures and words of living prophets for guidance, answers to questions, and support. The word of God is the greatest source of truth. (See Teaching in the Savior's Way, 21.)</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<graphics-caption>The Flight of the Prisoners, by James Tissot and others</graphics-caption>
<heading type="date">JULY 11–17</heading>
<heading type="ref">2 Kings 17–25</heading>
<heading type="title">"HE TRUSTED IN THE LORD GOD OF ISRAEL"</heading>
<p>Review the impressions you recorded during your personal study of 2 Kings 17–25 this week. What passages from these chapters do you feel will be most meaningful to members of your class?</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>When class members share what they are learning at home in their scripture study, other class members may feel inspired to study the scriptures throughout the week. You could begin class by inviting class members to respond to a question like "What has the Holy Ghost taught you as you have read the assigned chapters this week?"</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>2 KINGS 18:28–36; 19:1–7, 14–19</heading>
<heading>We can stay true to the Lord when our faith is challenged.</heading>
<ul>
<li>The truths in 2 Kings 18–19 can help us know how to respond when our faith is challenged. How will you help class members discover these truths? You could invite class members to share several reasons why they believe in God and His plan. Then they could search 2 Kings 18:28–35, looking for reasons the Assyrians gave the people in Jerusalem not to trust in the Lord. How does Satan try to persuade us to doubt our faith today? Class members could then search 2 Kings 19:1–7, 14–19 for what we can learn from Hezekiah about how to respond when our faith is challenged. How does the Lord help us overcome challenges to our faith? What other suggestions do class members have for renewing their faith and trust in the Lord?</li>
<li>You could invite a class member to come to class prepared to summarize the conversation that the Assyrians had with Hezekiah's officials near the walls of Jerusalem (see 2 Kings 18:17–36). Before he or she tells the story, invite class members to imagine that they are residents of Jerusalem listening to this conversation. What thoughts or feelings might they have? What might they do? You could give class members portions of Elder David A. Bednar's message "Therefore They Hushed Their Fears" (Ensign or Liahona, May 2015, 46–49) and invite them to look for counsel that could sustain them during times of fear or doubt. How has our faith in Jesus Christ sustained us during challenging times?</li>
</ul>
<heading>2 KINGS 22:8–20; 23</heading>
<heading>The scriptures can turn our hearts to the Lord.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Discussing the power the word of God had in the lives of King Josiah and his people can inspire class members to seek that same power in their own lives. You could begin a discussion by inviting class members to imagine how their lives might be different if they did not have the scriptures. Then they could search 2 Kings 22:8–11; 23:1–6, 21, 24 to find out how Josiah and his people changed when they heard the word of God from scriptures that had been recently rediscovered in the temple. How have the scriptures helped us come closer to Heavenly Father and Jesus Christ?</li>
<li>The dramatic changes that the word of God had on Josiah and many people in his kingdom could inspire your class members to seek similar changes in their lives. After discussing these changes (see 2 Kings 23:1–6, 21, 24), class members could share experiences in which a scripture passage or account made a difference in their lives. Perhaps they could talk about why they were receptive to the message of that scripture at that time in their lives. The statement in "Additional Resources" may add to your discussion.</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>The scriptures can help turn our hearts to the Lord.</graphics-caption>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>Rediscover the scriptures.</heading>
<p>President Spencer W. Kimball said:
"I am convinced that each of us, at some time in our lives, must discover the scriptures for ourselves — and not just discover them once, but rediscover them again and again. .
"I feel strongly that we must all of us return to the scriptures just as King Josiah did and let them work mightily within us, impelling us to an unwavering determination to serve the Lord. . . .
"I find that when I get casual in my relationships with divinity and when it seems that no divine ear is listening and no divine voice is speaking, that I am far, far away. If I immerse myself in the scriptures the distance narrows and the spirituality returns. I find myself loving more intensely those whom I must love with all my heart and mind and strength, and loving them more, I find it easier to abide their counsel" (Teachings of Presidents of the Church: Spencer W. Kimball [2006], 62–63, 67).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Use scripture study helps.</b>One way to help class members understand the scriptures is to point them to resources like the Guide to the Scriptures and Gospel Topics articles (ChurchofJesusChrist.org). They can also find helpful information in the "Thoughts to Keep in Mind" sections in Come, Follow Me—For Individuals and Families.</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<graphics-caption>Illustration of the temple of Zerubbabel, by Sam Lawlor</graphics-caption>
<heading type="date">JULY 18–24</heading>
<heading type="ref">Ezra 1; 3–7; Nehemiah 2; 4–6; 8</heading>
<heading type="title">"I AM DOING A GREAT WORK"</heading>
<p>As you invite members of your class to share what stood out to them in the books of Ezra and Nehemiah, also share any impressions you received as you studied.</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>Sometimes writing key words or phrases on the board can remind class members of things they learned from the scriptures and make it easier for them to share. For example, you could write<i>Rebuild, Repair,</i>and<i>Reestablish</i>on the board and invite class members to share verses from their reading that relate to one or more of these words.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>EZRA 3:8–13; 6:16–22</heading>
<heading>Temples can bring us joy.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Reading about the joy the Jews felt as their temple was rebuilt could help class members feel greater appreciation for temples in our day. Perhaps you could invite class members to review Ezra 3:8–13 6:16–22 and then discuss some of the ways the Jews celebrated the rebuilding and dedication of the temple. Why is the building of a temple a cause to celebrate? You could invite class members to share how temples, and the work we do there, bring them joy. The statement in "Additional Resources can encourage class members to experience the joy of temple work.</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>The temple can be a source of joy in our lives.</graphics-caption>
<heading>EZRA 4–5; NEHEMIAH 2; 4; 6</heading>
<heading>We can help the work of God advance despite opposition.</heading>
<ul>
<li>The books of Ezra and Nehemiah describe people accomplishing important work despite opposition from their enemies. To begin a discussion, you might ask class members what Nehemiah's "great work" (Nehemiah 6:3) could be compared to in our lives. What important work has God given us to do? Then you could read Ezra 4:4 and discuss how Satan tries to weaken our hands and trouble us in doing God's work. What do we learn from Nehemiah and his fellow workers in Nehemiah 2:18–20; 4:6–9; and 6:1–3? What does it mean to have "a mind to work" in the service of the Savior? (Nehemiah 4:6). Consider sharing part of President Dieter F. Uchtdorf's message "We Are Doing a Great Work and Cannot Come Down" (Ensign or Liahona, May 2009, 59–62), especially the last two sections.</li>
<li>You may feel inspired to lead a discussion comparing Zerubbabel's efforts to rebuild the temple to our efforts to attend the temple and do saving work there. For example, you could write two headings on the board:<i>Zerubbabel</i>and<i>Us</i>. Under<i>Zerubbabel</i>, class members could write what "the adversaries of Judah and Benjamin" (Ezra 4:1) did to try to stop Zerubbabel and the Jewish people from rebuilding the temple (see Ezra 4). Under<i>Us</i>, class members could list ways the adversary tries to stop us from attending the temple. They could then share advice with each other about how we can seek the Lord's help in overcoming that opposition.</li>
</ul>
<heading>NEHEMIAH 8:1–12</heading>
<heading>We are blessed when we study the scriptures.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Perhaps class members could read Nehemiah 8:1–12 together and discuss how Ezra and his people felt about God and His word. Encourage class members to refer to specific verses that show how they felt. Invite class members to express how they feel about the word of God. How can we improve our efforts to study the word of God?</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>Experience the joy of the temple.</heading>
<p>President Russell M. Nelson taught:
"We can be inspired all day long about temple and family history experiences others have had. But we must do something to actually experience the joy ourselves. I would like to extend a challenge to each one of us so that the wonderful feeling of this work can continue and even increase. I invite you to prayerfully consider what kind of sacrifice — preferably a sacrifice of time — you can make in order to do more temple and family history work this year.
"We are engaged in the work of Almighty God. He lives. Jesus is the Christ. This is His Church. We are His covenant children. He can count on us" (Russell M. Nelson and Wendy W. Nelson, "Open the Heavens through Temple and Family History Work," Ensign, Oct. 2017, 39).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Include parents of youth.</b>If you teach youth, share what you are teaching with their parents. They can help you understand the needs of the youth and how to help them. This can also be a good way to encourage family discussions about what youth are learning in class. (See Teaching in the Savior's Way, 27.)</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<graphics-caption>Esther, by James Johnson</graphics-caption>
<heading type="date">JULY 25–31</heading>
<heading type="ref">Esther</heading>
<heading type="title">"THOU ART COME. . . FOR SUCH A TIME AS THIS"</heading>
<p>How well do you know your class members? Try getting to know one class member better each week. This will help you consider their needs as you prepare to teach (see Teaching in the Savior's Way, 7).</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>Class members could share with someone sitting nearby something the Spirit taught them, something they have come to understand better, or something they likened to their lives as they read the book of Esther. Then a few of them could share with the entire class.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>ESTHER</heading>
<heading>The Lord places us in situations where we can bless others.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Members of your class may have looked for ways the Lord made it possible for Esther to save the Jews, as suggested in this week's outline in<i>Come, Follow Me—For Individuals and Families.</i>Invite them to share what they found. Or you could look for a few examples together (see Esther 2:21–23; 3:10–14; 4:14–16). What can we do to recognize the hand of God in our lives? The statement by Elder Neil L. Andersen in "Additional Resources" contains an answer to this question.</li>
<li>To help members of your class think about how the Lord has prepared them "for such a time as this" (Esther 4:14), invite them to read Esther 4:10–17. How might Mordecai's words to Esther have helped her make the decision to defend her people? Just as God placed Esther in a position where she could save the Jews, what are some situations He places us in so we can bless others? How can we become better instruments in His hands? Reading the statement by Sister Virginia U. Jensen in "Additional Resources" might inspire class members to think of times when they felt they were instruments for the Lord. Ask them to share their experiences, as guided by the Spirit.</li>
</ul>
<heading>ESTHER 4</heading>
<heading>Fasting demonstrates our dependence on the Lord.</heading>
<ul>
<li>You can use Esther 4 to discuss the blessings that come from fasting. You might have a class member review the events that led Esther and the other Jews to fast. Why did they choose to fast? Why do we choose to fast? You may want to review together some additional scriptures about fasting, such as Isaiah 58:6–12 and Matthew 4:1–4; 17:14–21 (see also Guide to the Scriptures, "Fast, Fasting," scriptures.ChurchofJesusChrist.org). Perhaps you or a few class members could share experiences that demonstrate how fasting brings the Lord's power into our lives.</li>
</ul>
<heading>ESTHER 3:1–11; 4:10–17; 5:1–4</heading>
<heading>Doing the right thing often requires great courage.</heading>
<p>The accounts of Mordecai and Esther courageously standing for righteousness can inspire class members to have courage to do the right thing. You could invite half of the class to read about Mordecai (see Esther 3:1–11) and the other half to read about Esther (see Esther 4:10–17; 5:1–4). If they were here today, what might Mordecai and Esther say to encourage us when it is hard to do what is right? Class members could also share situations when they have had to act courageously. You could show the video "Courage" (ChurchofJesusChrist.org) or invite the class to sing or read the words of a song about standing for truth, such as "Do What Is Right" (Hymns, no. 237). Then discuss what the video or song teaches about having courage.</p>
<graphics-caption>Esther before the King, by Minerva K. Teichert</graphics-caption>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>The hand of God.</heading>
<p>Elder Neil L. Andersen taught:
"Sometimes we can see the hand of the Lord in the lives of others but wonder, «How can I more clearly see His hand in my own life?» . . .
"As you keep the commandments and pray in faith to see the Lord's hand in your life, I promise you that He will open your spiritual eyes even wider, and you will see more clearly that you are not alone" ("Thy Kingdom Come," Ensign or Liahona, May 2015, 121–22).</p>
<heading>"For such a time as this."</heading>
<p>Sister Virginia U. Jensen taught: "I do not believe that you I and I are here at this unique time by accident. I believe that, like Esther of old, we are «come to the kingdom for such a time as this» [Esther 4:14], when our influence, our example, our strength, and our faith may stand as a bulwark against the rising tide of evil that threatens to engulf our homes, our families, and our loved ones" ("Creating Places of Security," Ensign, Nov. 1997, 89).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Go to the scriptures first.</b>The scriptures should be your primary source for your study and preparation. Don't forget that the words of modern prophets complement the standard works and are also scripture. (See Teaching in the Savior's Way, 17–18.)</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<graphics-caption>The Judgments of Job, by Joseph Brickey</graphics-caption>
<heading type="date">AUGUST 1–7</heading>
<heading type="ref">Job 1–3; 12–14; 19; 21–24; 38–40; 42</heading>
<heading type="title">"YET WILL I TRUST IN HIM"</heading>
<p>What truths did the Holy Ghost help you learn as you studied the book of Job? What do you want to share with your class?</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>Class members who studied Job this week may have discovered truths that were meaningful to them. To prompt them to share, you could write on the board<i>I learned from Job</i>. . . and ask class members how they would complete this sentence.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>JOB 1–2; 12–13; 19:23–27</heading>
<heading>Our trust in Heavenly Father and Jesus Christ can help us remain faithful in all circumstances.</heading>
<ul>
<li>The first two chapters of Job, which describe Satan questioning the reasons behind Job's faithfulness, could help class members evaluate their own reasons for being faithful to Heavenly Father and Jesus Christ. Class members might start by listing some reasons a person might choose to obey God's commandments. They could then search Job 1:6–12; 2:1–6 to find out what Satan said about Job's faithfulness. Why would it be dangerous to obey the Lord solely for the reason Satan suggested? What does Job's response in Job 1:20–22; 2:9–10 reveal about Job? Class members could talk about why they choose to remain faithful to God.</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>Job, by Gary L. Kapp</graphics-caption>
<ul>
<li>While Job had times when he struggled with doubt and despair, ultimately his trust in the Lord sustained him in his suffering. To learn from Job's example, class members could search some of the following verses to identify some of Job's positive responses to his trials: Job 1:21; 2:10; 12:9–10, 16; 13:15–16; 19:23–27. What can we learn from these responses that can help us be spiritually strong when we face trials? Why is it dangerous to assume that trials are punishments for sin?</li>
<li>Job's declaration in Job 19:23–27 could inspire class members to ponder and share their own conviction that the Redeemer, Jesus Christ, lives. You might start by inviting class members to quietly ponder Job's words in these verses. They could then discuss questions like these: Why is a testimony of our Redeemer so valuable during times of trial like those Job suffered? How has our testimony sustained us in our trials? Singing or reading the lyrics of a hymn about Jesus Christ, such as "I Know That My Redeemer Lives" (Hymns, no. 136), could add insight and spiritual power to your discussion.</li>
</ul>
<heading>JOB 38</heading>
<heading>God's perspective is greater than ours.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Much of the book of Job (chapters 3–37) involves Job and his friends wrestling with the question "Why do bad things happen to righteous people?" While the Lord does not answer this question completely in the book of Job, He does provide an important message. You could help class members discover this message by inviting them to read the questions the Lord asked Job in Job 38:1–7, 18–24. What do we learn from these questions?</li>
<li>The restored gospel of Jesus Christ provides additional light that can help us understand some of the reasons for suffering in the world. Class members could share truths they know because of the Restoration of the gospel that have given them greater perspective and understanding about suffering. They could find some of these truths in the scriptures and statement found in "Additional Resources."</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>latter-day insight on the purposes of suffering.</heading>
<p>The following scriptures provide insights about the purposes of suffering:</p>
<ul>
<li>2 Nephi 2:11–14</li>
<li>Ether 12:27</li>
<li>Doctrine and Covenants 58:3–5</li>
<li>Doctrine and Covenants 122</li>
<li>Moses 5:10–12</li>
</ul>
<p>Spencer W. Kimball taught:
"If we looked at mortality as the whole of existence, then pain, sorrow, failure, and short life would be calamity. But if we look upon life as an eternal thing stretching far into the premortal past and on into the eternal post-death future, then all happenings may be put in proper perspective.
"Is there not wisdom in [God's] giving us trials that we might rise above them, responsibilities that we might achieve, work to harden our muscles, sorrows to try our souls? Are we not exposed to temptations to test our strength, sickness that we might learn patience, death that we might be immortalized and glorified? . . .
"If joy and peace and rewards were instantaneously given the doer of good, there could be no evil — all would do good but not because of the rightness of doing good. There would be no test of strength, no development of character, no growth of powers, no free agency" (Teachings of Presidents of the Church: Spencer W. Kimball [2006], 15).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Follow the Spirit.</b>You can't predict how every lesson will go, but the promptings of the Spirit will guide you. When you are spiritually prepared, the Lord will give you "in the very moment, what ye shall say" (Doctrine and Covenants 100:6), and it may be just what class members need to hear. (See Teaching in the Savior's Way, 10.)</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<graphics-caption>The Lord Is My Shepherd, by Yongsung Kim, havenlight.com</graphics-caption>
<heading type="date">AUGUST 8–14</heading>
<heading type="ref">Psalms 1–2; 8; 19–33; 40; 46</heading>
<heading type="title">"THE LORD IS MY SHEPHERD"</heading>
<p>Plan ways to let class members share the spiritual experiences they are having as they read the Psalms.</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>Inviting class members to share what they discovered in the Psalms can be as simple as asking questions like these: What did the Spirit teach you as you read the Psalms this week? Which psalms helped you feel especially close to the Lord?</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>PSALMS 1; 23; 26–28; 46</heading>
<heading>The Psalms teach us to trust the Lord.</heading>
<ul>
<li>This week's outline in<i>Come, Follow Me—For Individuals and Families</i>suggests reading Psalms 1; 23; 26–28; 46 and looking for the following:
<ul>
<li>Invitations to trust the Lord</li>
<li>Words that describe the Lord</li>
<li>Words that describe the peace, strength, and other blessings He provides</li>
<li>Words that describe those who trust Him</li>
</ul>
You might write these phrases on the board and invite class members to write, next to each phrase, something they found in Psalms 1; 23; 26–28; or 46. If they need help, you might point them to these verses: Psalms 1:1–4; 23:1–6; 26:1, 6–8, 12; 27:1, 3, 8, 14; 28:1, 7; 46:1–3, 10. Class members could share the feelings they had about the Savior as they read these psalms.</li>
<li>Because the Psalms were like hymns for the Israelites, you might invite class members to suggest hymns that remind them of psalms they read this week. They could refer to the "Scriptures" index at the end of the hymnbook for ideas (see also the list in "Additional Resources"). Class members could sing a few of these hymns and identify common themes in the hymns and the psalms. What messages of peace and faith in Jesus Christ do we find?</li>
</ul>
<heading>PSALMS 2; 22; 31:5</heading>
<heading>The Psalms point our minds to the life and ministry of Jesus Christ.</heading>
<ul>
<li><p>Reading the Psalms — especially those that point to the Savior's life — can be a great way to strengthen faith in Jesus Christ. You might divide the class into groups of two or more and give each group one of the following pairs of references: Psalm 2:1–3 and Acts 4:24–28; Psalm 2:7 and Acts 13:30–33; Psalm 22:1 and Matthew 27:45–46; Psalm 22:7–8 and Matthew 27:39–43; Psalm 22:16 and Luke 23:32–33; Psalm 22:18 and Matthew 27:35; Psalm 31:5 and Luke 23:46. Ask each group to find how a prophecy in the Psalms was fulfilled in the Savior's life and discuss how these scriptures strengthen their testimony of the Savior.</p>
<p>Or you could write the scripture references on the board and invite class members to match a passage from Psalms with the corresponding event in the New Testament.</p>
<p>You might also invite class members to share other references to the Savior that they found in their study of the Psalms (such as Psalms 34:20; 41:9; see also Luke 24:44).</p>
<p>After class members discuss these scriptures, they could talk about why these psalms would have been meaningful to Jews who knew the Savior. Why are they meaningful to us?</p></li>
</ul>
<heading>PSALM 23</heading>
<heading>"The Lord is my shepherd."</heading>
<ul>
<li>To help class members discuss the imagery and symbolism in Psalm 23, consider showing pictures that relate to the ideas in the psalm, such as those in<i>Come, Follow Me—For Individuals and Families.</i>You could then ask class members to identify meaningful words or phrases in the psalm and discuss what they might represent. For example, what do phrases like "lie down in green pastures" or "still waters" bring to mind? What could the comforting "rod" and "staff" symbolize? What might it mean for our "cup" to run over? What do these symbols teach us about Jesus Christ? You might suggest that class members restate the psalm, replacing some of the symbols with possible meanings the class discussed.</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>Hymns related to the Psalms.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Psalms 8:3–9; 9:1–2. "How Great Thou Art" (Hymns, no. 86)</li>
<li>Psalm 23. "The Lord Is My Shepherd,"</li>
<li>"The Lord My Pasture Will Prepare" (Hymns, nos. 108, 109)</li>
<li>Psalms 23:6; 150. "Praise to the Lord, the Almighty" (Hymns, no. 72)</li>
<li>Psalm 26:8. "We Love Thy House, O God" (Hymns, no. 247)</li>
<li>Psalm 27:1. "The Lord Is My Light" (Hymns, no. 89)</li>
<li>Psalms 33:1–6; 95:1–6. "For the Beauty of the Earth" (Hymns, no. 92)</li>
<li>Psalm 37:3–9. "Be Still, My Soul" (Hymns, no. 124)</li>
<li>Psalm 148. "All Creatures of Our God and King" (Hymns, no. 62)</li>
</ul>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Use music.</b>"Hymns invite the Spirit of the Lord, create a feeling of reverence, unify us as members, and provide a way for us to offer praises to the Lord. . . . Hymns move us to repentance and good works, build testimony and faith, comfort the weary, console the mourning, and inspire us to endure to the end" (Hymns, ix).</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<graphics-caption>Saving That Which Was Lost, by Michael T. Malm</graphics-caption>
<heading type="date">AUGUST 15–21</heading>
<heading type="ref">Psalms 49–51; 61–66; 69–72; 77–78; 85–86</heading>
<heading type="title">"I WILL DECLARE WHAT HE HATH DONE FOR MY SOUL"</heading>
<p>Consider Elder David A. Bednar's counsel as you prepare to teach: "Talking and telling alone are not teaching. [Teaching] the gospel the Lord's way includes observing and listening and discerning as prerequisites to talking" ("Becoming a Preach My Gospel Missionary," New Era, Oct. 2013, 6).</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>One way to invite class members to share something they read this week is to write on the board<i>"My lips shall greatly rejoice"</i>or<i>"My tongue also shall talk of thy righteousness"</i>(Psalm 71:23, 24). Class members could share what they found that helps them "greatly rejoice" or "talk of [the Lord's] righteousness."</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>PSALMS 51; 85–86</heading>
<heading>"Thou, Lord, art good, and ready to forgive."</heading>
<ul>
<li>Psalm 51 describes the feelings many of us have as we seek to repent and be forgiven. To help class members better understand repentance and feel inspired to repent often, you might suggest that they search Psalm 51 with this question in mind: What does it mean to repent? Then let them share possible answers. ("Additional Resources" contains helpful insights.) Why does repentance sometimes seem undesirable? What do we find in this psalm that can make repentance feel joyful?</li>
<li>How would we describe what it feels like to receive forgiveness of sin through Jesus Christ's atoning power? Invite class members to share their thoughts, and encourage them to find passages in Psalms 51; 85–86 that describe the effect of His cleansing forgiveness in our lives (for example, see Psalms 51:1–2, 7–12; 85:2–9). Consider displaying pictures or objects to help class members visualize these phrases. Class members could then share their feelings about the Savior Jesus Christ and His willingness to atone for our sins so we can be forgiven. You might also sing together a hymn about the Savior's atoning sacrifice, such as "I Stand All Amazed" (Hymns, no. 193).</li>
<li>In order to repent, we need faith not only that Jesus Christ<i>can</i>cleanse us but also that He<i>will</i>. Class members may have found passages in Psalms 51; 85–86 this week that strengthened their faith in the Lord's willingness to forgive. Encourage them to share what they found. You could also point them to Psalm 86:5, 13, 15 and ask what these verses teach about the Lord. What could it mean that He is "plenteous in mercy and truth"? (verse 15). Why is it important for us to know this?</li>
</ul>
<heading>PSALM 66:5–20</heading>
<heading>Our testimony of Jesus Christ can help others come unto Him.</heading>
<ul>
<li>One of the great blessings of meeting together in Sunday School is the opportunity to gain strength from the faith and testimonies of other followers of Jesus Christ. To provide this opportunity for your class, you could ask class members to read Psalm 66:16 and ponder this question: If you were to "declare what [the Lord] hath done for [your] soul," what would you declare? As they ponder, they could read verses 5–20 for ideas. Let them write down their answers. Then invite them to "declare" to each other — in small groups or to the whole class — what Jesus Christ has done for their souls.</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>We can share with others our testimonies of what the Lord has done for us.</graphics-caption>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>Repentance means change.</heading>
<p>President Russell M. Nelson described repentance in this way:
"When Jesus asks you and me to «repent,» He is inviting us to change our mind, our knowledge, our spirit — even the way we breathe. He is asking us to change the way we love, think, serve, spend our time, treat our wives, teach our children, and even care for our bodies.
"Nothing is more liberating, more ennobling, or more crucial to our individual progression than is a regular, daily focus on repentance. Repentance is not an event; it is a process. It is the key to happiness and peace of mind. When coupled with faith, repentance opens our access to the power of the Atonement of Jesus Christ. . . .
"When we choose to repent, we choose to change! We allow the Savior to transform us into the best version of ourselves. We choose to grow spiritually and receive joy — the joy of redemption in Him. When we choose to repent, we choose to become more like Jesus Christ!" ("We Can Do Better and Be Better," Ensign or Liahona, May 2019, 67).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Ask questions that touch the heart and mind.</b>"Ask learners to share how they feel about a scripture passage, how the people in the scriptures may have felt, or how the truths in the passage relate to our lives" (Teaching in the Savior's Way, 31).</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<graphics-caption>Every Knee Shall Bow, by J. Kirk Richards</graphics-caption>
<heading type="date">AUGUST 22–28</heading>
<heading type="ref">Psalms 102–103; 110; 116–119; 127–128; 135–139; 146–150</heading>
<heading type="title">"LET EVERY THING THAT HATH BREATH PRAISE THE LORD"</heading>
<p>Which of the teachings in the Psalms do you feel will be most helpful to members of your class? As you study this week, ponder how you can help class members find meaning in the words of these psalms.</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>Give class members a few minutes to review the psalms they read this week, and invite a few to share a favorite passage. Encourage them to share what the Spirit taught them. How have the Psalms enhanced our personal worship of the Lord?</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>PSALMS 102–3; 116</heading>
<heading>The Lord can comfort us in our suffering.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Have members of your class felt the way the writer of Psalm 102 felt? How can we turn to the Lord when we feel discouraged or distressed? As they studied Psalms 102, 103, and 116 at home this week, class members may have found phrases that inspire them to turn to the Lord in their trials. Encourage them to share what they found, or look for some inspiring phrases together as a class. Class members could also talk about how the Lord has supported them in times of adversity.</li>
<li>Members of your class may enjoy writing their own psalm about how the Lord has helped them during times of trial. These need not be long or complex psalms — just simple expressions of faith, gratitude, and praise. Class members could work alone or in pairs, and they could review Psalms 102, 103, and 116 for ideas. Invite a few people to share their psalms, if they are willing. You could also sing hymns together about how the Lord comforts us, such as "Where Can I Turn for Peace?" (Hymns, no. 129).</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>Healing, by J. Kirk Richards</graphics-caption>
<heading>PSALM 119</heading>
<heading>God's word will keep us on His path.</heading>
<ul>
<li>To begin a discussion about Psalm 119, you might invite class members to talk about a time when they followed a path to reach a destination (it may help to contact someone in advance and ask him or her to be prepared to talk about this). What experiences made it difficult to stay on the path? What helped them stay on it? You might then draw a path on the board and invite class members to write phrases from Psalm 119 that tell what the Lord has done to help us stay on His covenant path. Consider sharing the quotation by President Russell M. Nelson in "Additional Resources" as part of your discussion.</li>
<li>Members of your class may benefit from comparing what Psalm 119 teaches about staying on the Lord's path with other scriptures that teach similar truths. Consider dividing the class into groups and asking each group to review scripture passages like these: Psalm 119:33–40, 105; Proverbs 4:11–19; 1 Nephi 8:20–28; 11:25; 2 Nephi 31:17–21; Alma 7:9, 19–20. Invite each group to share what they learned. Give class members time to ponder what they are inspired to do based on what they learned.</li>
</ul>
<heading>PSALM 139</heading>
<heading>The Lord knows our hearts.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Understanding that the Lord is aware of us&#8213;our thoughts and actions, strengths and weaknesses — and that He loves us can have a powerful influence on the choices we make. You could invite the class to look for phrases in Psalm 139 that teach this important truth. How are our lives affected by knowing this truth? Class members could also invite the Lord to "search me, O God, and know my heart" (verse 23).</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>The strait and narrow path.</heading>
<p>President Russell M. Nelson said:
"If our journey through life is to be successful, we need to follow divine direction. The Lord said, «Look unto me in every thought; doubt not, fear not» [Doctrine and Covenants 6:36]. And the Psalmist wrote, «Thy word is a lamp unto my feet, and a light unto my path» [Psalm 119:105]. . . .
"In your journey through life, you meet many obstacles and make some mistakes. Scriptural guidance helps you to recognize error and make the necessary correction. You stop going in the wrong direction. You carefully study the scriptural road map. Then you proceed with repentance and restitution required to get on the «strait and narrow path which leads to eternal life» [2 Nephi 31:18]" ("Living by Scriptural Guidance," Ensign, Nov. 2000, 17).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Include those who are struggling.</b>Sometimes struggling class members just need to be included in order to feel loved. Consider asking them to play a role in an upcoming lesson, inviting them to class, or making sure they have a ride to church. Don't give up if they don't respond to your efforts at first. (See Teaching in the Savior's Way, 8–9.)</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<heading type="date">AUGUST 29–SEPTEMBER 4</heading>
<heading type="ref">Proverbs 1–4; 15–16; 22; 31; Ecclesiastes 1–3; 11–12</heading>
<heading type="title">"THE FEAR OF THE LORD IS THE BEGINNING OF WISDOM"</heading>
<p>How might the messages in Proverbs and Ecclesiastes bless the lives of those you teach? Follow the promptings and impressions you receive as you study and prepare to teach.</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>There are many beautiful and powerful messages in Proverbs and Ecclesiastes. Before discussing specific passages, such as those suggested below, invite class members to share some of their favorites from their personal or family scripture study this week.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>PROVERBS 1–4; 15–16; ECCLESIASTES 1–3; 11–12</heading>
<heading>"Incline thine ear unto wisdom."</heading>
<ul>
<li>The invitation to seek wisdom and understanding is repeated throughout Proverbs. How can you help class members share what they learned about wisdom during their study? One way might be to write<i>wisdom</i>on the board and invite class members to add verse numbers or phrases from Proverbs or Ecclesiastes that they feel provide insights about wisdom. (If it would be helpful, you might suggest that class members search Proverbs 1–4; 15–16; Ecclesiastes 1–3; 11–12.) What do we learn about wisdom from these scriptures? How are we blessed when we seek wisdom from God?</li>
</ul>
<heading>PROVERBS 1:7; 2:5; 3:7; 8:13; 15:33; 16:6; 31:30; ECCLESIASTES 12:13</heading>
<heading>"Be not wise in thine own eyes: fear the Lord."</heading>
<ul>
<li>Another theme found throughout Proverbs and Ecclesiastes is "the fear of the Lord" (Proverbs 1:7; see also Proverbs 2:5; 3:7; 8:13; 15:33; 16:6; 31:30; Ecclesiastes 12:13). Perhaps class members could read some of these verses and share what they feel it means to fear the Lord. How is fear of the Lord different from other kinds of fear? You could share insights from Elder David A. Bednar's explanation found in "Additional Resources."</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>Learning to Trust the Lord, by Kathleen Peterson</graphics-caption>
<heading>PROVERBS 3:5–7</heading>
<heading>"Trust in the Lord with all thine heart."</heading>
<ul>
<li>Class members might enjoy an object lesson that helps them understand what it means to "trust in the Lord" and "lean not unto [their] own understanding" (Proverbs 3:5). For example, you could invite a class member to lean against something sturdy and stable, like a wall. Then the person could try leaning against something that is not sturdy, like a broom. How does this demonstration help us understand Proverbs 3:5? What does Proverbs 3:5–7 teach about what it means to trust in the Lord? Why is it unwise to lean on our own understanding? How have we felt the Lord direct our paths as we have trusted Him?</li>
</ul>
<heading>PROVERBS 15:1–2, 4, 18, 28; 16:24–32</heading>
<heading>"A soft answer turneth away wrath."</heading>
<ul>
<li>To help class members discuss how they can have more peace and less contention in their lives, you could invite them to read Proverbs 15:1–2, 18; 16:32. Then they could share experiences they have had that illustrate the truths in these verses. For example, when has using "a soft answer" helped to "[turn] away wrath"? (Proverbs 15:1). Or they could think of times when the Savior exemplified what is taught in these verses (see John 8:1–11; 18:1–11). How can we follow His example as we interact with others?</li>
<li>While the writers of Proverbs didn't know about the many communication channels that exist in our day, the counsel in Proverbs 15 and 16 can apply to all forms of communication. To help class members understand this, you could invite each person to pick one of the following scriptures to read: Proverbs 15:1–2, 4, 18, 28; 16:24, 27–30. Class members could then restate their proverb in the form of advice about interacting with others over social media, through texting, or online. They can find additional helpful counsel in "Language" in<i>For the Strength of Youth</i>(2011), 20–21.</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>"Godly fear is loving and trusting in Him."</heading>
<p>Elder David A. Bednar explained:
"Godly fear grows out of a correct understanding of the divine nature and mission of the Lord Jesus Christ, a willingness to submit our will to His will, and a knowledge that every man and woman will be accountable for his or her own sins in the Day of Judgment. . . .
"Godly fear is loving and trusting in Him. As we fear God more completely, we love Him more perfectly. And «perfect love casteth out all fear» (Moroni 8:16). I promise the bright light of godly fear will chase away the dark shadows of mortal fears (see Doctrine and Covenants 50:25) as we look to the Savior, build upon Him as our foundation, and press forward on His covenant path with consecrated commitment" ("Therefore They Hushed Their Fears," Ensign or Liahona, May 2015, 48–49).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Focus on Jesus Christ.</b>There is no better way to increase the faith of those you teach than by centering your lesson on the Savior. Through your teaching, invite class members to build "upon the rock of our Redeemer, who is Christ, the Son of God" (Helaman 5:12).</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<graphics-caption>The Prophet Isaiah Foretells Christ's Birth, by Harry Anderson</graphics-caption>
<heading type="date">SEPTEMBER 5–11</heading>
<heading type="ref">Isaiah 1–12</heading>
<heading type="title">"GOD IS MY SALVATION"</heading>
<p>Consider ways to encourage class members to share impressions and understanding they received during their personal and family study.</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>This week's outline in<i>Come, Follow Me—For Individuals and Families</i>gives ideas for understanding the writings of Isaiah. You could invite class members to share how one of these ideas, or something else, helped them learn from Isaiah 1–12.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>ISAIAH 1–12</heading>
<heading>The words of Isaiah will all be fulfilled.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Speaking of Isaiah, the Savior taught that "all things that he spake have been and shall be, even according to the words which he spake" (3 Nephi 23:3). You might start a discussion about Isaiah by sharing this scripture and the statement in "Additional Resources." You could then write on the board<i>Isaiah's day, The Savior's mortal ministry,</i>and<i>The latter days.</i>Class members could look for passages in Isaiah 1–12 that might apply to one or more of the phrases on the board (for example, Isaiah 2:1–5; 7:1–7; 7:10–14; 9:2–7; 10:20; 11:10; 12:1). Why is it a blessing to have these prophecies available to us today?</li>
</ul>
<heading>ISAIAH 1; 3; 5</heading>
<heading>"Cease to do evil."</heading>
<ul>
<li>You might ask class members to share what they learned from their personal and family study of Isaiah 1, 3, 5 about the spiritual condition of the Kingdom of Judah in the days of Isaiah. Perhaps they could review these chapters and create a list of verses and the conditions they describe. What messages of hope did we find in these chapters? (If needed, you could refer class members to Isaiah 1:16–20, 25–27; 3:10.) If ancient Judah had a message for us, what might it be?</li>
<li>Class members could pretend that they were living in Jerusalem when Isaiah prophesied. You could interview a few of them, asking them what Isaiah said and how they felt about it. For example, you might ask class members to talk about Isaiah's words found in Isaiah 1:16–20; 3:16–26; 5:20–23. What did Isaiah say that inspires us to repent?</li>
</ul>
<heading>ISAIAH 2; 4; 11–12</heading>
<heading>God will do a great work in the latter days.</heading>
<ul>
<li>To help class members ponder how Isaiah's prophecies about the last days are being fulfilled, you could select some verses from Isaiah 2; 4; 11–12 (such as Isaiah 2:2–3; 4:5–6). Then ask class members to find the future-tense verbs in these verses (such as "shall be" or "shall go"). Invite them to replace some of these with present-tense verbs (such as "is being" or "are going"). How are these prophecies being fulfilled in our lives? Why is it important to know about these prophecies?</li>
<li>You might point out that when Moroni visited Joseph Smith in 1823, he quoted Isaiah 11 and said that it was about to be fulfilled (see Joseph Smith History 1:40; see also Doctrine and Covenants 113:1–6). Class members could read a few verses from Isaiah 11 (such as verses 6–12) and summarize in their own words what Isaiah foresaw. What is our role in fulfilling these prophecies?</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>"For unto us a child is born, unto us a son is given" (Isaiah 9:6).</graphics-caption>
<heading>ISAIAH 7–9</heading>
<heading>Isaiah prophesied of Jesus Christ.</heading>
<ul>
<li>You might ask class members what they learn about Jesus Christ from passages such as Isaiah 7:14; 8:13–14; 9:2, 6–7. For example, why is Immanuel a good title for the Savior? (see Matthew 1:23). How has Jesus Christ been a "Counsellor" or "Prince of Peace" to us? Class members could also share other passages they found in Isaiah 1–12 that remind them of Jesus Christ. What do these passages teach us about Him?</li>
<li>Before class, you could invite class members to bring a picture of Christ that they feel represents one of the descriptions of the Savior found in Isaiah 7–9. During class, give them time to show the picture they brought and explain how it relates to Isaiah's words.</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>Isaiah's prophecies can have multiple fulfillments.</heading>
<p>President Dallin H. Oaks taught: "The book of Isaiah contains numerous prophecies that seem to have multiple fulfillments. One seems to involve the people of Isaiah's day or the circumstances of the next generation. Another meaning, often symbolic, seems to refer to events in the meridian of time, when Jerusalem was destroyed and her people scattered after the crucifixion of the Son of God. Still another meaning or fulfillment of the same prophecy seems to relate to the events attending the Second Coming of the Savior. The fact that many of these prophecies can have multiple meanings underscores the importance of our seeking revelation from the Holy Ghost to help us interpret them" ("Scripture Reading and Revelation," Ensign, Jan. 1995, 8).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Invite the Spirit.</b>"Sacred music, the scriptures, words of latter-day prophets, expressions of love and testimony, and moments of quiet contemplation can all invite the presence of the Spirit" (Teaching in the Savior's Way, 10).</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<graphics-caption>Sacred Grove, by Brent Borup</graphics-caption>
<heading type="date">SEPTEMBER 12–18</heading>
<heading type="ref">Isaiah 13–14; 24–30; 35</heading>
<heading type="title">"A MARVELLOUS WORK AND A WONDER"</heading>
<p>Before you can help others discover truths in the book of Isaiah, you need to discover truths for yourself. As you read this week, consider which truths you feel impressed to emphasize in class.</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>To encourage class members to share what they are learning from Isaiah, you could ask them how they would respond to someone who says, "The book of Isaiah is just too hard to understand." What has helped us find meaning in Isaiah's teachings? What scripture passages have inspired us?</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>ISAIAH 24:21–23; 25:6–8; 26:19; 28:16</heading>
<heading>The writings of Isaiah point us to Jesus Christ.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Like Nephi, members of your class may have delighted in Isaiah's witness of Jesus Christ (see 2 Nephi 11:2). You might ask them to share any verses they found in their reading this week that taught them about the Savior. Or you could invite class members to share what they learn about Jesus Christ from Isaiah 24:21–23; 25:6–8; 26:19; 28:16 or other verses that you found in your study. Why are these truths valuable to us?</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>He Comes Again to Rule and Reign, by Mary R. Sauer</graphics-caption>
<heading>ISAIAH 24:1–5; 28:1–8; 29:7–10; 30:8–14</heading>
<heading>Apostasy means turning away from the Lord and His prophets.</heading>
<ul>
<li>This week's outline in Come, Follow Me—For Individuals and Families suggests pondering some of the metaphors Isaiah used to describe the consequences of turning away from the Lord and rejecting His prophets. Invite class members to share what they learned. Or you could invite them to each review one of the following passages: Isaiah 24:1–5; 28:7–8; 29:7–10; 30:8–14. Based on what they read, they could complete this sentence: "If we turn away from the Lord, we are like. . ." What can we do to stay faithful to the Lord and avoid apostasy? (See "Additional Resources" for some suggestions.) How does the Lord bless those who stay faithful to Him?</li>
<li>To begin a discussion about the attitudes and behaviors that can lead us to apostasy, you could invite class members to search Isaiah 24:1–5; 28:1–8; 29:7–10; 30:8–14. Ask them to search for things that people in Isaiah's time were thinking and doing. Make a warning label on the board that says Warning: The following attitudes and behaviors can lead to apostasy. Class members could list on the board what they find in the verses. Give them an opportunity to share how they safeguard themselves or their families from apostasy.</li>
</ul>
<heading>ISAIAH 29:13–24; 30:18–26; 35</heading>
<heading>The Lord can restore things that are lost or broken.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Here's a question you could write on the board that might help class members ponder Isaiah 29: How do Isaiah's writings relate to the Restoration of the gospel in our day? Encourage them to think about this question as they silently read Isaiah 29:13–24. If they need help, they could also review passages like these: 2 Nephi 27:6–26; Joseph Smith — History 1:17–19, 63–65. After they talk about the question on the board, they could discuss why "marvellous" and "wonder" (Isaiah 29:14) are good words to describe the Restoration of the gospel. What do we learn about the Restoration from "The Restoration of the Fulness of the Gospel of Jesus Christ: A Bicentennial Proclamation to the World"? (ChurchofJesusChrist.org).</li>
<li>Chapters 30 and 35 of Isaiah contain several passages that could inspire greater faith in the Lord's power to bless those who turn to Him. To help class members discover these passages, you could invite them to study either Isaiah 30:18–26 or Isaiah 35. Ask them to share words or phrases they find that could help someone turn to the Lord for redemption.</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>Staying faithful to the Lord and His Church.</heading>
<p>President M. Russell Ballard gave the following counsel to help us stay faithful to the Lord and His Church:
"We need to experience a continuing conversion by increasing our faith in Jesus Christ and our faithfulness to His gospel throughout our lives — not just once but regularly [see Alma 5:26]. . . .
". . . The words of the Lord are found in the scriptures and the teachings of the apostles and prophets. They provide us counsel and direction that, when followed, will act like a spiritual life jacket and will help us know how to hold on with both hands. . . .
"In addition to developing the habit of personal scripture reading, we need to be like the sons of Mosiah and give ourselves «to much prayer, and fasting» [Alma 17:3]" ("Stay in the Boat and Hold On!" Ensign or Liahona, Nov. 2014, 90–91).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Express confidence in learners' abilities.</b>Some people in your class may not be confident in their ability to learn the gospel. Reassure them that as they strive to learn, the Holy Ghost will teach them. (See Teaching in the Savior's Way, 29–30.)</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<graphics-caption>Healing the Blind Man, by Carl Heinrich Bloch</graphics-caption>
<heading type="date">SEPTEMBER 19–25</heading>
<heading type="ref">Isaiah 40–49</heading>
<heading type="title">"COMFORT YE MY PEOPLE"</heading>
<p>Some people might hesitate to share their thoughts in class because they feel they don't know the scriptures well. How can you help all class members feel that their spiritual insights are valued?</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>Consider writing a question like the following on the board: What did the Spirit teach you as you studied Isaiah 40–49? Class members could ponder this question and write down answers, and a few could share their thoughts.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>ISAIAH 40–49</heading>
<heading>Jesus Christ can comfort us and give us hope.</heading>
<ul>
<li>This week's outline in Come, Follow Me—For Individuals and Families suggests looking for messages of comfort and hope in Isaiah 40–49 and lists some passages to start with. You might ask class members to share any messages they found. Encourage them to talk about why these messages might have helped the Jews in captivity and how they can help us today. You could also point them to passages you found in your personal study. What does the Lord want us to know about Him? How does He comfort us? You might remind class members that "the Lord" in the Old Testament refers to Jehovah, or Jesus Christ.</li>
<li>The hymn "How Firm a Foundation" (Hymns, no. 85) draws on Isaiah's words in Isaiah 41:10; 43:2–5; 46:4. After reading these scriptures and singing relevant verses of the hymn, class members could talk about times they have felt the Lord was with them and how their experiences helped them to "fear not."</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>"He shall feed his flock like a shepherd" (Isaiah 40:11).</graphics-caption>
<heading>ISAIAH 40:1–3, 9–11; 43:8–13; 48:20–21; 49:1–9</heading>
<heading>"Ye are my witnesses."</heading>
<ul>
<li>What does it mean to be the Lord's "witnesses"? Class members could ponder this question as they read one or more of the following passages: Isaiah 40:1–3, 9–11; 48:20–21; 49:1–9. The statement in "Additional Resources" could also provide some answers. What are the "good tidings" that we share as the Lord's witnesses? What in these verses helps us "be not afraid" to share our witness? (Isaiah 40:9). Class members could talk about opportunities they have to be the Lord's witnesses and how their testimonies can bless others.</li>
<li>To help class members apply the teachings in Isaiah 43:8–13, you could invite them to imagine that they have been called to the witness stand in a court trial. In this trial, Jesus Christ has been charged with making the claim recorded in Isaiah 43:11. If we were called as witnesses in support of Jesus's claim (see verse 10), what testimony could we offer? What evidence from our lives would we present?</li>
</ul>
<heading>ISAIAH 48:10; 49:13–16</heading>
<heading>The Lord can refine us through our afflictions.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Perhaps class members could discuss how these words from Elder Quentin L. Cook help us understand Isaiah 48:10: "Qualities of character and righteousness that are forged in the furnace of affliction perfect and purify us" ("The Songs They Could Not Sing," Ensign or Liahona, Nov. 2011, 106). They could also talk about how their own "furnace of affliction" has helped refine them spiritually. How does Isaiah 49:13–16 help us when we are afflicted? See also the video "The Refiner's Fire" (ChurchofJesusChrist.org).</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>Standing as a witness.</heading>
<p>President Margaret D. Nadauld explained what it means to 'stand as witnesses of God at all times and in all things, and in all places' (Mosiah 18:9):
"In standing as a witness at all times, we promise to love the Lord, to honor Him all the time — daytime and nighttime, summer and winter, good times and bad times — love the Lord and let that love show by the way we live. . . .
"Standing as a witness in all things means all things — big things, little things, in all conversations, in jokes, in games played and books read and music listened to, in causes supported, in service rendered, in clothes worn, in friends made. . . .
"Finally, we say that we will stand as a witness in all places. That means not only in public places but in private places, in secret, in dark or in light places; in church, school, home, or cars; in mountain places or beach places; on the street or in the park. . . .
"When we think of the magnificence of [the Savior's] gift to us, what small thing could we do for Him and for our Heavenly Father who sent Him? We could stand as witnesses of Their love and teachings at all times, in all things, and in all places" ("Stand as a Witness," Ensign, May 2000, 93, 95).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Invite diligent learning.</b>"Learners are ultimately responsible for their own learning. Consider how you can help learners accept and fulfill this responsibility" (Teaching in the Savior's Way, 29).</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<graphics-caption>The Mocking of Christ, by Carl Heinrich Bloch</graphics-caption>
<heading type="date">SEPTEMBER 26–OCTOBER 2</heading>
<heading type="ref">Isaiah 50–57</heading>
<heading type="title">"HE HATH BORNE OUR GRIEFS, AND CARRIED OUR SORROWS"</heading>
<p>The most important way to prepare to teach is to read and ponder the scriptures. What do you feel and learn as you read Isaiah 50–57?</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>To prompt class members to share experiences they had while reading Isaiah 50–57, you could write on the board a sentence like My faith in Jesus Christ was strengthened when I read. . . Invite class members to share how they would finish the sentence.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>ISAIAH 50–52</heading>
<heading>The future is bright for the Lord's people.</heading>
<ul>
<li>We all have times when we feel weak. To help class members rely on the Lord's strength, you could assign them each to read a few verses from Isaiah 51–52 and share something they find that would strengthen someone who feels weak or discouraged. You might also point out that the resurrected Savior repeated some of Isaiah's words to the people in the Americas (see 3 Nephi 20:32–45). What do the Savior's words in 3 Nephi 20:30–34 add to our understanding of when these prophecies will be fulfilled?</li>
<li>This week's outline in Come, Follow Me—For Individuals and Families suggests listing everything in Isaiah 50–52 that the Lord invites His people to do. Perhaps class members could share what they found and talk about what these invitations mean to them. You might want to focus on the invitations in Isaiah 51:1–2, 6–8; 52:1–3, 9–11. How can we act on these invitations? You might point out that Doctrine and Covenants 113:7–10 provides an inspired explanation of Isaiah 52:1–2. What do these words add to our understanding?</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>Because of Love, by sculptor Angela Johnson</graphics-caption>
<heading>ISAIAH 52:13–15; 53</heading>
<heading>Jesus Christ took upon Himself our sins and sorrows.</heading>
<ul>
<li>To help class members visualize Isaiah's words in Isaiah 53, you could display several pictures of the events surrounding the Atonement of Jesus Christ (see Gospel Art Book, nos. 56–60). You could then ask class members to find phrases in Isaiah 53 that describe the events in the pictures. What do Isaiah's words teach about the Savior's suffering for us? What do they suggest about why He suffered for us? What do these teachings inspire us to do?</li>
<li>To invite the Holy Ghost to testify of the truths taught in Isaiah 52:13–15; 53, you might ask class members to read these verses silently while you play a recording of a hymn about the Atonement of Jesus Christ. Invite class members to look for words or phrases in the scriptures that they feel are especially important. Then let them share what they found and how they feel about the Savior. Consider also inviting class members to read Mosiah 15:10–12, where Abinadi explained what is meant by the phrase "his seed." How does this help us understand Isaiah 53:10?</li>
</ul>
<heading>ISAIAH 54</heading>
<heading>Jesus Christ wants us to return to Him.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Studying Isaiah 54 may inspire class members who feel discouraged because of their sins or weaknesses. You could invite class members to search chapter 54 for phrases or verses showing how the Savior feels about us. How does He want us to feel about our past sins and weaknesses? How does He want us to feel about Him? Encourage class members to share anything else they learn about Jesus Christ from this chapter. The statement by President Dieter F. Uchtdorf in "Additional Resources" can add to your discussion.</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>Through Jesus Christ we can have hope.</heading>
<p>President Dieter F. Uchtdorf taught:
"It matters not how completely ruined our lives may seem. It matters not how scarlet our sins, how deep our bitterness, how lonely, abandoned, or broken our hearts may be. Even those who are without hope, who live in despair, who have betrayed trust, surrendered their integrity, or turned away from God can be rebuilt. . . .
"The joyous news of the gospel is this: because of the eternal plan of happiness provided by our loving Heavenly Father and through the infinite sacrifice of Jesus the Christ, we can not only be redeemed from our fallen state and restored to purity, but we can also transcend mortal imagination and become heirs of eternal life and partakers of God's indescribable glory" ("He Will Place You on His Shoulders and Carry You Home," Ensign or Liahona, May 2016, 102).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Live worthy of the Spirit's guidance.</b>When you live the gospel worthily, you live worthy of the Spirit, who is the best teacher. As you seek the guidance of the Holy Ghost, He will give you thoughts, impressions, and creative ideas about how to meet the needs of those you teach. (See Teaching in the Savior's Way, 5.)</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<graphics-caption>Jesus in the Synagogue at Nazareth, by Greg K. Olsen</graphics-caption>
<heading type="date">OCTOBER 3–9</heading>
<heading type="ref">Isaiah 58–66</heading>
<heading type="title">"THE REDEEMER SHALL COME TO ZION"</heading>
<p>As you study the beautiful doctrine in these chapters, invite the Spirit to guide you to the messages that will be most meaningful to class members.</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>You could invite class members to write on the board the references for verses that inspired them during their scripture study this week. As a class, you could then look up those verses and talk about the truths found there. These insights could lead to deeper discussion of one or more of the principles listed below.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>ISAIAH 58:3–12</heading>
<heading>Fasting brings blessings.</heading>
<ul>
<li>To help class members discuss why and how the Lord has commanded us to fast, you could create two columns on the board labeled<i>"Ye Shall Not Fast as Ye Do This Day"</i>and<i>"The Fast That I Have Chosen."</i>Then class members could read Isaiah 58:3–7, filling in the first column with descriptions of how the Israelites were fasting and the second column with descriptions of fasting as the Lord intends. How do these descriptions affect the way we view fasting? Class members could also share how, in their experience, fasting leads to the blessings the Lord promised in verses 8–12.</li>
<li>Some class members might have had experiences explaining to others why we fast. Invite them to share what they said. You could also invite a member of the bishopric to talk about how fast offerings are used. Or you might share an example of how fasting blesses people from President Henry B. Eyring's message "Is Not This the Fast That I Have Chosen?" (Ensign or Liahona, May 2015, 22–25). How do fasting and paying fast offerings help to "undo the heavy burdens" of ourselves and others? (Isaiah 58:6).</li>
</ul>
<heading>ISAIAH 61:1–3; 63:7–9</heading>
<heading>Jesus Christ is our Savior and Redeemer.</heading>
<ul>
<li>When Jesus Christ announced to the people of Nazareth that He was the Messiah, He quoted from Isaiah 61:1–3 (see Luke 4:16–21; see also the video "Jesus Declares He Is the Messiah," ChurchofJesusChrist.org). Perhaps class members could read Isaiah 61:1–3 and talk about why these verses are a good description of the Savior's mission. You might list on the board each thing the Savior was anointed to do and discuss what each one means. How did the Savior fulfill these aspects of His mission during His mortal life? How has He fulfilled them in our lives?</li>
<li>Class members could also read Isaiah 63:7–9 and share how Jesus Christ has blessed them in the ways described.</li>
<li>Isaiah 61:1–3 uses beautiful and poetic language to describe Jesus Christ's power to redeem what seems ruined. To help illustrate these verses, consider sharing a story about something that was thought to be lost or ruined but was turned into something even more beautiful. For examples, see the video "Provo City Center Temple" (ChurchofJesusChrist.org; see also "Additional Resources") or the story at the beginning of President Dieter F. Uchtdorf's message "He Will Place You on His Shoulders and Carry You Home" (Ensign or Liahona, May 2016, 101–4). Class members could talk about how they have seen the Lord give people something beautiful when they thought their lives were ruined.</li>
</ul>
<heading>ISAIAH 65:17–25</heading>
<heading>At His Second Coming, the Lord will "create new heavens and a new earth."</heading>
<ul>
<li>Isaiah 65:17–25 describes conditions on the earth after the Savior's Second Coming. You could invite class members to review these verses searching for answers to questions like these: How will life on the "new earth" be different from the way life currently is on earth? What do you find in these verses that causes you to rejoice?</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>The Lord "does not leave us in the ashes."</heading>
<p>After recounting how a fire nearly destroyed the Provo Tabernacle, allowing it to be rebuilt later as the Provo City Center Temple, Sister Linda S. Reeves said: "The Lord allows us to be tried and tested, sometimes to our maximum capacity. We have seen the lives of loved ones — and maybe our own — figuratively burned to the ground and have wondered why a loving and caring Heavenly Father would allow such things to happen. But He does not leave us in the ashes; He stands with open arms, eagerly inviting us to come to Him. He is building our lives into magnificent temples where His Spirit can dwell eternally" ("Claim the Blessings of Your Covenants," Ensign or Liahona, Nov. 2013, 119).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Get to know those you teach.</b>Each person you teach has a unique background, perspective, and set of talents. Consider these differences as you seek to help all learn in meaningful and memorable ways. (See Teaching in the Savior's Way, 7.)</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<graphics-caption>Jeremiah, by Walter Rane</graphics-caption>
<heading type="date">OCTOBER 10–16</heading>
<heading type="ref">Jeremiah 1–3; 7; 16–18; 20</heading>
<heading type="title">"BEFORE I FORMED THEE IN THE BELLY I KNEW THEE"</heading>
<p>As you study, think about the members of your class, and seek the Spirit's guidance to know what messages may be most important to them.</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>One way you could encourage sharing is to invite class members to write on a slip of paper a gospel truth they learned during their study of Jeremiah this week. You could then collect the slips of paper and choose a few to discuss as a class. How do the writings of Jeremiah help us understand these truths?</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>JEREMIAH 1:4–19</heading>
<heading>Prophets are called to speak the Lord's word.</heading>
<ul>
<li>You might begin a discussion about Jeremiah's call as a prophet by displaying a picture of the living prophet and asking class members to share how they came to know that he was called of God. You could also ask them to share how they have helped others come to know this important truth. How does this knowledge bless our lives? Class members could then list on the board things they learn about prophets from Jeremiah 1:4–19. What do prophets in our day "root out" or "pull down"? What do they "build" and "plant"? (verse 10).</li>
<li>Invite class members to share what Jeremiah learned about himself in Jeremiah 1:5. How might this knowledge have affected his ministry? Class members could read the statement in "Additional Resources" and the following scriptures that support this truth: Alma 13:1–4; Doctrine and Covenants 138:53–56; Abraham 3:22–23. How do these truths about our premortal life affect the way we live our mortal life?</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>People in ancient Israel used cisterns to store precious water.</graphics-caption>
<heading>JEREMIAH 2; 7</heading>
<heading>"They have forsaken me the fountain of living waters."</heading>
<ul>
<li>To prompt a discussion about Jeremiah 2:13, you could draw on the board a cistern (a large underground reservoir) and a fountain (like a natural spring). Class members could then read Jeremiah 2:13 and talk about why it is better to get water from a fountain rather than digging a cistern. What might be the spiritual equivalent of making broken cisterns? You could invite class members to read verses from Jeremiah 2 and 7 and share some of the ways the Israelites had forsaken "the fountain of living waters" (see, for example, Jeremiah 2:26–28; 7:2–11). Why is "living water" a good symbol for what the Savior gives us?</li>
</ul>
<heading>JEREMIAH 3:14–18; 16:14–15</heading>
<heading>The Lord will gather His people.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Because Jeremiah compared the latter-day gathering of Israel to Israel's deliverance from Egypt through Moses, you might show a picture of the Exodus (see the outline for April 4–10 in Come, Follow Me—For Individuals and Families). Invite class members to discuss how meaningful the Exodus was to the Israelites for generations. Class members could then read Jeremiah 16:14–15 and talk about how the latter-day gathering of Israel will be even more important to God's people (see also Jeremiah 3:14–18). Class members who reviewed "Hope of Israel" as part of their personal study could share what they learned about the importance of the gathering of Israel (see Russell M. Nelson and Wendy W. Nelson, "Hope of Israel" [worldwide youth devotional, June 3, 2018], supplement to the New Era and Ensign, Aug. 2018, 2–17, ChurchofJesusChrist.org). Or you could review parts of that message as a class. How is Israel being gathered in our area?</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>Heavenly Father knows you.</heading>
<p>President Russell M. Nelson taught:
"Your spirit is an eternal entity. The Lord said to His prophet Abraham: «Thou wast chosen before thou wast born» [Abraham 3:23]. The Lord said something similar about Jeremiah [see Jeremiah 1:5] and many others [see Alma 13:2–3]. He even said it about you [see Doctrine and Covenants 138:55–56].
"Your Heavenly Father has known you for long time. You, as His son or daughter, were chosen by Him to come to earth at this precise time, to be a leader in His great work on earth. You were chosen not for your bodily characteristics but for your spiritual attributes, such as bravery, courage, integrity of heart, a thirst for truth, a hunger for wisdom, and a desire to serve others.
"You developed some of these attributes premortally. Others you can develop here on earth as you persistently seek them" ("Decisions for Eternity," Ensign or Liahona, Nov. 2013, 107).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Live the gospel with all your heart.</b>You will become a Christlike teacher as you embrace the gospel and live it every day of your life. Christlike teaching doesn't require you to be perfect — just to try and to keep on trying. When you diligently do your best and seek forgiveness when you fall short, you can become the disciple of Christ that He needs you to be. (See Teaching in the Savior's Way, 13–14.)</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<graphics-caption>The Cry of Jeremiah the Prophet, from an engraving by the Nazarene School</graphics-caption>
<heading type="date">OCTOBER 17–23</heading>
<heading type="ref">Jeremiah 30–33; 36; Lamentations 1; 3</heading>
<heading type="title">"I WILL TURN THEIR MOURNING INTO JOY"</heading>
<p>Ponder the impressions you received during your personal study of Jeremiah and Lamentations. What passages from these chapters do you feel will be meaningful to those you teach?</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>To help class members share what they learned from their scripture study, you could write on the board phrases like I have learned that . . ., I have a testimony of. . ., or I have experienced. . . Class members could share something from Jeremiah or Lamentations to complete these statements.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine.</heading>
<heading>JEREMIAH 30–31; 33; LAMENTATIONS 1:1–7; 3:1–5</heading>
<heading>The Lord will bring Israel out of captivity and gather them.</heading>
<ul>
<li>The messages of hope in Jeremiah's prophecies can give class members hope in their own circumstances. Perhaps your class could discuss circumstances that might cause people in our day to feel hopeless like the people in Jeremiah's time felt (see Jeremiah 30:5; 31:15; Lamentations 1:1–7; 3:1–5; and the quotation in "Additional Resources"). You could then divide class members into three groups and invite each group to review Jeremiah 30; 31; and 33 for messages that could bring hope to people today. How has hope in the Lord helped us endure trials?</li>
</ul>
<heading>JEREMIAH 31:31–34; 32:37–42</heading>
<heading>"They shall be my people, and I will be their God."</heading>
<ul>
<li>Reviewing Jeremiah 31:31–34; 32:37–42 can help your class ponder the covenants they have made. One way to encourage a discussion about these verses is to give class members a few minutes to read the verses and then write on a slip of paper a question they would like to ask the class about what they read. For instance, they might want to discuss what it means to have God's law written in our hearts (see Jeremiah 31:33) or how covenants help us to come to know the Lord (see Jeremiah 31:34). You could collect the questions and pick a few to discuss together. What do we learn from these verses that inspires us to be valiant in keeping our covenants?</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>The scriptures can inspire us to repent and turn to the Lord.</graphics-caption>
<heading>JEREMIAH 36</heading>
<heading>The scriptures have power to turn us away from evil.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Members of your class may have gained insights about the scriptures as they studied Jeremiah 36 at home. Invite them to share what they learned. You could also assign class members the name of a person in the chapter and invite them to read about what that person did with the word of God. Class members could study the words and actions of the Lord (see verses 1–3, 27–31); Jeremiah (see verses 4–7, 32); Baruch (see verses 4, 8–10, 14–18); Jehudi and King Jehoiakim (see verses 20–26); and Elnathan, Delaiah, and Gemariah (see verse 25). How do our words and actions show how we feel about the scriptures? :</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>You can always have hope.</heading>
<p>President M. Russell Ballard mentioned some situations that may cause some to lose hope, and he offered counsel about where to find hope:
"Some of us may find our lives laden with frustration, disappointment, and sorrow. Many feel helpless to deal with the chaos that seems to prevail in the world. Others anguish over family members who are being carried downstream in a swift, raging current of weakening values and declining moral standards. . . .Many have even resigned themselves to accept the wickedness and cruelty of the world as being irreparable. They have given up hope. . . .
". . . Some among us may have lost all hope because of sin and transgression. A person can become so deeply immersed in the ways of the world that he sees no way out and loses all hope. My plea to all who have fallen into this trap of the adversary is to never give up! Regardless of how desperate things may seem or how desperate they may yet become, please believe me, you can always have hope. Always" ("The Joy of Hope Fulfilled," Ensign, Nov. 1992, 31–32).
"Quite simply, our one hope for spiritual safety during these turbulent times is to turn our minds and our hearts to Jesus Christ. . . . Faith in God and in His Son, Jesus Christ, is absolutely essential for us to maintain a balanced perspective through times of trial and difficulty" ("The Joy of Hope Fulfilled," 32).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Follow the Spirit.</b>You can't predict how every lesson will go, but as you listen for the promptings of the Spirit, He will guide the lesson. When you are spiritually prepared, the Lord will give you "in the very moment, what ye shall say" (Doctrine and Covenants 100:6; see also Teaching in the Savior's Way, 10).</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<graphics-caption>Come, Follow Me, by Scott Sumner</graphics-caption>
<heading type="date">OCTOBER 24–30</heading>
<heading type="ref">Ezekiel 1–3; 33–34; 36–37; 47</heading>
<heading type="title">"A NEW SPIRIT WILL I PUT WITHIN YOU"</heading>
<p>The words of Ezekiel have been preserved by the Lord for a wise purpose and can bless the members of your class. Ponder this as you study Ezekiel's writings this week.</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>The people who heard Ezekiel thought his words were "lovely" and "pleasant," "but they [did] them not" (see Ezekiel 33:30–33). Class members might share a passage they found in Ezekiel's writings that inspired them to do something.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>EZEKIEL 34</heading>
<heading>The Lord invites us to feed His sheep.</heading>
<ul>
<li>To help class members find personal meaning in Ezekiel 34, you could write on the board situations they might face, such as<i>preparing to serve a mission, raising children,</i>or<i>receiving a ministering assignment.</i>Class members could pick one to ponder as they silently read Ezekiel 34:1–10. Invite them to share what counsel based on these verses they might give to someone in the situation they picked. What does it mean to feed ourselves instead of the Lord's flocks? How can we be shepherds like the Savior is? (see verses 11–16).</li>
<li>You might feel inspired to ask questions that help class members ponder the symbolism in Ezekiel 34:11–31. For example, what might the "good pasture" and "good fold" represent in verse 14? What's the difference between a sheep who is "lost" and one who is "driven away"? (verse 16). How does the Savior rescue both kinds of sheep? Class members could share other symbols they find in these verses and talk about what these symbols teach them about Jesus Christ.</li>
</ul>
<heading>EZEKIEL 37</heading>
<heading>The Lord is gathering His people and giving them new life.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Reading Ezekiel 37 and thinking about the Lord's promise to gather Israel can give us insights about what the gathering means and how we participate in it. To help class members find these insights, you could write on the board questions<i>like What is the Lord trying to accomplish through the gathering of Israel? How is He accomplishing it?</i>You could then ask half of the class to read Ezekiel 37:1–14 and the other half to read Ezekiel 37:15–28 as they search for insights these two passages might provide to the questions on the board. It might help to explain that the sticks of Joseph and Judah mentioned in verses 16–19 represent the Book of Mormon and Bible. As class members share their answers, encourage them to talk about their role in the latter-day gathering of Israel.</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>Ezekiel saw in vision a river flow from the temple and heal the Dead Sea.</graphics-caption>
<heading>EZEKIEL 47:1–12</heading>
<heading>The temple brings spiritual healing.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Pictures could help class members understand the vision described in Ezekiel 47:1–12. For example, you could show a picture of a temple, a river, a desert, and the Dead Sea (see the images in this week's outline in<i>Come, Follow Me—For Individuals and Families</i>and Bible Photographs, no. 3, "Judean Wilderness"). It might help to explain that the Dead Sea is so salty that fish and plants can't live in it. Class members could read verses 1–12 and share what impresses them about the waters described in the vision (see also Revelation 22:1 and the statement in "Additional Resources"). They could also draw pictures of Ezekiel's vision. What might the waters symbolize? What could the trees described in verse 12 represent? Perhaps class members could share how the temple and its blessings have brought them spiritual life and healing.</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>Temple blessings can heal us.</heading>
<p>Referring to the water flowing from the temple in Ezekiel's vision (see Ezekiel 47:1–12), Elder Dale G. Renlund observed:
"Two characteristics of the water are noteworthy. First, though the small stream had no tributaries, it grew into a mighty river, becoming wider and deeper the farther it flowed. Something similar happens with the blessings that flow from the temple as individuals are sealed as families. Meaningful growth occurs going backward and forward through the generations as sealing ordinances weld families together.
"Second, the river renewed everything that it touched. The blessings of the temple likewise have a stunning capacity to heal. Temple blessings can heal hearts and lives and families" ("Family History and Temple Work: Sealing and Healing," Ensign or Liahona, May 2018, 47–48; see also the video "And the River Will Grow," ChurchofJesusChrist.org).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Help others receive the Spirit.</b>"Sometimes teachers may be tempted to think that it is their knowledge or methods or personality that inspires those they teach. . . . Your purpose as a teacher is not to make an impressive presentation but rather to help others receive the influence of the Holy Ghost" (Teaching in the Savior's Way, 10).</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<graphics-caption>Daniel Interprets Nebuchadnezzar's Dream, by Grant Romney Clawson</graphics-caption>
<heading type="date">OCTOBER 31–NOVEMBER 6</heading>
<heading type="ref">Daniel 1–6</heading>
<heading type="title">"THERE IS NO OTHER GOD THAT CAN DELIVER"</heading>
<p>Many class members will be familiar with some of the stories in the book of Daniel. As you study and prepare to teach, seek guidance from the Spirit about how you can help class members find personal meaning from these chapters.</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>It may be helpful to invite class members to share how their personal or family scripture study is going. When class members share an insight about something the Spirit taught them this week, you could ask them what they were doing that led to those insights.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>DANIEL 1; 3; 6</heading>
<heading>We can trust in the Lord when our faith is tried.</heading>
<ul>
<li>To begin a discussion about how Daniel, Shadrach, Meshach, and Abed-nego showed faith in the Lord, you could ask a few class members to summarize the challenges these four men faced, described in Daniel 1, 3, and 6. Why would it have been hard to be faithful in these situations? What situations do we face that challenge our faith? Class members could search Daniel 1:10–13; 3:15–18; 6:10, looking for how these four men responded to their challenges. How can their examples help us in our efforts to be faithful disciples of Jesus Christ?</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>Illustration of Daniel and his friends refusing the king's food, by Brian Call</graphics-caption>
<ul>
<li>Many of us, like Daniel and his friends, have felt pressure to compromise our standards. What are some of the sources of this pressure in our lives? To help class members learn from the example of Daniel and his friends, you could divide the class into three groups and assign each group to review one of the following chapters: Daniel 1, 3, or 6. How did the Lord bless Daniel, Shadrach, Meshach, and Abed-nego when they chose to be faithful despite the pressure they faced? Each group could share with the class what they discovered. Class members could then counsel together about how to stay faithful despite social pressure or other kinds of pressure. They could also discuss the importance of seeking good friends who will support us in our standards.</li>
</ul>
<heading>DANIEL 2</heading>
<heading>The Church of Jesus Christ of latter-day Saints is the kingdom of God on earth.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Discussing Daniel 2 could help your class understand how The Church of Jesus Christ of latter-day Saints is fulfilling its destiny as the prophesied stone "cut out of the mountain" (verse 45). To begin, you could review as a class Daniel's description and interpretation of Nebuchadnezzar's dream, found in Daniel 2:31–45. Then you could show a picture of a stone (or draw one on the board). Invite class members to share what they learn about the kingdom of God by comparing it to the descriptions of the stone in Daniel 2:34–35, 44–45. Perhaps class members might know some of the history of the Church in your area that they can share. How have we seen Daniel's prophecies fulfilled in our individual lives?</li>
</ul>
<heading>DANIEL 2:1–30</heading>
<heading>Receiving revelation requires spiritual preparation.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Perhaps class members would benefit from learning about how Daniel prepared himself to receive the revelation needed to describe and interpret Nebuchadnezzar's dream. You could begin by asking class members to review Daniel 2:1–15 and then share how they would feel if they found themselves in Daniel's position. Invite them to search Daniel 2:16–18 to learn what Daniel did. What do we learn from Daniel 1:17 about how God prepared Daniel? What can we learn from Daniel that can help us as we seek personal revelation? What can we learn from Daniel's words and actions after he received the Lord's help? (see Daniel 2:20–30).</li>
</ul>
<heading>DANIEL 3</heading>
<heading>When the outcome is uncertain, we can still choose faith.</heading>
<ul>
<li>The experience of Shadrach, Meshach, and Abed-nego found in Daniel 3 can help your class members more fully understand what it means to have faith in Jesus Christ. You could invite class members to summarize the challenge Shadrach, Meshach, and Abed-nego faced (see Daniel 3:1–12) and then discuss how they responded (see Daniel 3:13–18). What do we learn about faith from the response of these men? You could write on the board the phrases Our God is able to . . . and But if not. . . from verses 17–18. Class members could suggest how they might fill in the blanks with situations they might face. For example, they might suggest "Our God is able to answer all my questions" and "But if not, I will patiently trust Him." As class members share examples, encourage them to talk about how the Savior supports and strengthens us even when we don't know how things will turn out.</li>
</ul>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Use visual aids.</b>"Art, including pictures, videos, and dramatizations, can help engage learners — especially visual learners — and make scriptural accounts more memorable" (Teaching in the Savior's Way, 22).</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<heading type="date">NOVEMBER 7–13</heading>
<heading type="ref">Hosea 1–6; 10–14; Joel</heading>
<heading type="title">"I WILL LOVE THEM FREELY"</heading>
<p>As you study and prepare this week, consider which of the beautiful and uplifting messages from the books of Hosea and Joel might help meet the needs of those you teach.</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>To help class members share what they learned this week, you could invite them to write on the board a word or phrase that inspired them during their study. Then they could share why the word or phrase is meaningful to them. These words and phrases may help guide the rest of your discussion.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>HOSEA 1–3; 14</heading>
<heading>The Lord always invites us to return to Him.</heading>
<ul>
<li>You might begin a discussion of Hosea 1–3 by writing<i>marriage</i>on the board and asking class members to list words that they associate with marriage. How is making a covenant with the Lord like entering into a marriage? How is breaking that covenant like being unfaithful to a spouse? (see Hosea 2:5–7, 13). Then the class could talk about how the relationship between Hosea and Gomer symbolizes the relationship between the Lord and His people. What do Hosea 2:14–23 and Hosea 14 teach us about the Lord's love and mercy? How do we show the Lord our love and loyalty to Him?</li>
<li>Hosea 14 describes many beautiful promises the Lord made to the house of Israel if they would return to Him. Perhaps class members could search this chapter looking for these promises. What did the Lord say He would do? What might the phrase "love them freely" mean? (verse 4). What do the plant metaphors in verses 5–8 teach us about the Lord's blessings to us, including the blessings of repentance?</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>Sinful Gomer, who represents Israel, was offered redemption by the Lord. Illustration by Deb Minnard, licensed from goodsalt.com</graphics-caption>
<heading>HOSEA 6:6; JOEL 2:12–13</heading>
<heading>Devotion to God must be felt inwardly, not just expressed outwardly.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Hosea 6:6 and Joel 2:12–13 refer to animal sacrifice and tearing clothing as signs of remorse. While such practices may be unfamiliar today, these verses can lead to a discussion about what is most important to the Lord. You might read together Hosea 6:6 and discuss what this verse might mean. Invite some class members to read Matthew 9:10–13 and others to read Matthew 12:1–8. Then class members could teach each other how these events in the Savior's ministry help us understand the principle taught in Hosea 6:6. How can we live this principle in our day?</li>
<li>You could also read together Joel 2:12–13 and discuss what it might mean to rend our hearts and not just our garments. What do we learn from these verses about what it means to be true disciples of Jesus Christ?</li>
</ul>
<heading>JOEL 2</heading>
<heading>"I will pour out my spirit upon all flesh."</heading>
<ul>
<li>To begin a discussion of Joel 2, you could share with the class what Moroni said about this prophecy when he visited Joseph Smith in 1823 (see Joseph Smith — History 1:41). Class members could share how they feel the prophecies in Joel 2:28–32 are being fulfilled in our day. You could also discuss how Elder David A. Bednar's words in "Additional Resources" relate to Joel's prophecy. Class members might discuss what it means to them to feel an outpouring of the Holy Ghost in their daily life. What can we do if we feel like we aren't receiving that outpouring? How can we help "[our] sons and [our] daughters" receive it? (verse 28).</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>"We can count on the Holy Ghost guiding us."</heading>
<p>Elder David A. Bednar taught:
"We often make it hard on ourselves to receive personal revelation. By that I mean, the covenant promise is that as we honor our covenants, we may always have the Holy Ghost to be our constant companion. But we talk about it and we treat it as if hearing the voice of the Lord through His Spirit is the rare event. . . . [The Spirit] ought to be with us all of the time. Not every nanosecond, but if a person is doing his or her best — you don't have to be perfect — but if you and I are doing our best and we're not committing serious transgression, then we can count on the Holy Ghost guiding us. . . .
". . . We seem to believe that the Holy Ghost is dramatic and big and sudden, when it's still and small and incremental over time. You don't have to recognize that you are receiving revelation in the moment that you are receiving revelation" ("Elder David A. Bednar Discussion" [evening with a General Authority, Feb. 7, 2020], broadcasts.ChurchofJesusChrist.org).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Be welcoming.</b>Learners need to know that you care about them and their spiritual growth. One good way to show them this is by greeting them warmly as they arrive to class. (See Teaching in the Savior's Way, 15.)</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<graphics-caption>Bread of Life, by Chris Young</graphics-caption>
<heading type="date">NOVEMBER 14–20</heading>
<heading type="ref">Amos; Obadiah</heading>
<heading type="title">"SEEK THE LORD, AND YE SHALL LIVE"</heading>
<p>As you study Amos and Obadiah, be open to impressions about what you should teach to your class members. Record these thoughts, and look for opportunities to share them in your Sunday class.</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>Just as Amos and Obadiah gave warnings to the people in their day, their words also provide warnings to us today. You might invite class members to share teachings from Amos and Obadiah that apply to us.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>AMOS 3:7–8; 7:10–15</heading>
<heading>The Lord reveals truth through His prophets.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Invite class members to share truths about prophets that they found in their personal or family study of Amos 3 and Amos 7. You could make a list of their responses on the board. What other truths about prophets do we know? (For some ideas, see the Gospel Topics article "Prophets" [topics.ChurchofJesusChrist.org].) Encourage several class members to share how they gained their testimonies of the important role prophets play in God's plan.</li>
<li>How might we share with a friend why it is important to have a prophet in our day? You could list on the board questions that someone who is not a member of the Church might ask about prophets. How could we answer some of these questions using Amos 3:7–8 and 7:10–15?</li>
<li>As part of your discussion about prophets, you might share one of the following videos: "We Need Living Prophets" or "Words of the Prophets" (ChurchofJesusChrist.org). How have latter-day prophets helped us draw closer to Jesus Christ?</li>
</ul>
<heading>AMOS 5; 8:11–12</heading>
<heading>Apostasy is like a famine of hearing the words of the Lord.</heading>
<ul>
<li>To begin a conversation about the famine Amos described in Amos 8:11–12, you might find it helpful to briefly review the spiritual condition of the people he was preaching to. How had the Israelites turned away from the Lord? (see, for example, Amos 2:6–8; 5:11–12). Why is it helpful to know about their downfall? Class members could then read Amos 8:11–12 and talk about why "famine" and "thirst" are good words to describe the condition of those who turn away from the Lord. Class members could also search Amos 5 for verses that can help us avoid apostasy in our lives (see, for example, verses 4, 11–12, 14–15, 25–26).</li>
<li>Understanding the spiritual hunger that accompanies apostasy helps us understand the spiritual feast we enjoy because of the Restoration. You might write a few questions about the Apostasy and Restoration on the board, such as<i>Why was there an Apostasy? What impact did the Apostasy have on God's children? What impact did the Restoration have?</i>Encourage class members to find answers to these and other questions using resources like the following: "The Message of the Restoration of the Gospel of Jesus Christ" in chapter 3 of<i>Preach My Gospel</i>([2019], 36–39); the Gospel Topics article "Apostasy" (topics.ChurchofJesusChrist.org); the video "The Great Apostasy" (ChurchofJesusChrist.org); and the quotation in "Additional Resources." Invite class members to talk about truths restored in our day that are especially meaningful to them.</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>We can become saviors on Mount Zion by doing temple and family history work.</graphics-caption>
<heading>OBADIAH 1:21</heading>
<heading>"Saviours shall come up on Mount Zion."</heading>
<ul>
<li>Why is the phrase "saviours. . . on mount Zion" (Obadiah 1:21) a good description for us when we do temple and family history work? How does the work we do for our ancestors in the temple help us feel closer to the Savior Jesus Christ? Class members could share recent experiences they have had doing temple and family history work.</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>Lessons from the past.</heading>
<p>President M. Russell Ballard taught:
"In the relatively short span of years covered by the New Testament, . . . the people turned against Christ and His Apostles. The collapse was so great we have come to know it as the Great Apostasy, which led to the centuries of spiritual stagnation and ignorance called the Dark Ages.
". . . Our Heavenly Father loves all of His children, and He wants them all to have the blessings of the gospel in their lives. Spiritual light is not lost because God turns His back on His children. Rather, spiritual darkness results when His children turn their collective backs on Him. It is a natural consequence of bad choices made by individuals, communities, countries, and entire civilizations. This has been proven again and again throughout the course of time. One of great lessons of this historical pattern is that our choices, both individually and collectively, do result in spiritual consequences for ourselves and for our posterity" ("Learning the Lessons of the Past," Ensign or Liahona, May 2009, 32).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Help learners recognize the Holy Ghost.</b>"As prompted by the Holy Ghost, ask learners what they are feeling and what they feel prompted to do. Help them associate their spiritual feelings with the influence of the Holy Ghost" (Teaching in the Savior's Way, 11).</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<graphics-caption>Jonah on the Beach at Nineveh, by Daniel A. Lewis</graphics-caption>
<heading type="date">NOVEMBER 21–27</heading>
<heading type="ref">Jonah; Micah</heading>
<heading type="title">"HE DELIGHTETH IN MERCY"</heading>
<p>Lasting conversion requires more than an inspiring Sunday School lesson every other week. Encourage class members to seek personal spiritual experiences throughout their lives.</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>Consider writing phrases like the following on the board:<i>A truth I was reminded of, Something new I learned,</i>and<i>Something I would like to study further.</i>Give class members time to review what they studied in Jonah and Micah that relates to one of the phrases on the board.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>JONAH 1–4; MICAH 7:18–19</heading>
<heading>The Lord is merciful to all who turn to Him.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Reminding your class of the Lord's mercy can help them feel His love for them and inspire them to repent. You could invite the class to read Micah 7:18–19 and list on the board some events from Jonah 1–4 that show the Lord delights in mercy. What other experiences of God's mercy can we share — from the scriptures or our own lives?</li>
<li>Experiencing the Lord's mercy can inspire us to be more merciful. Here is one idea that could help your class members learn about mercy from the book of Jonah. You could write a question like this on the board:<i>What can God's mercy, as demonstrated in Jonah 1–4, teach me about being more merciful?</i>Each class member could choose a chapter to review and look for answers to the question. Give class members time to reflect on opportunities they have to replace judgmental attitudes with merciful ones toward themselves or others.</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>We can share the gospel with God's children.</graphics-caption>
<heading>JONAH 1; 3–4</heading>
<heading>All of God's children need to hear the gospel.</heading>
<ul>
<li>One way to draw lessons from Jonah's story is to compare it with accounts of missionaries in the Book of Mormon. Consider creating two columns on the board with the headings<i>Jonah</i>and<i>Alma and the Sons of Mosiah.</i>Invite the class to contrast Jonah's attitude about teaching the people of Nineveh (see Jonah 1; 3–4) with the attitude of the sons of Mosiah about teaching the Lamanites (see Mosiah 28:1–5; Alma 17:23–25). What do we learn from this exercise about sharing the gospel with all of God's children?</li>
<li>Like Jonah, many of us may feel hesitant to invite others to turn to the Lord. What are some possible reasons Jonah fled from his calling to warn the people of Nineveh? Why might we sometimes hesitate to share the gospel? Class members could share ways the Lord has helped them overcome their hesitation. The counsel by President Henry B. Eyring in "Additional Resources" might help class members identify principles that can empower our efforts to share the gospel.</li>
</ul>
<heading>MICAH 6:6–8</heading>
<heading>"What doth the Lord require of thee?"</heading>
<ul>
<li>Micah 6:6–7 mentions several elements of ancient Jewish rituals. But some things are more important to God than outward rites. Invite class members to find those important things in verse 8. Perhaps class members could identify key phrases in this verse and discuss what each phrase means. They could then pick their favorite phrases, find related scriptures in the Guide to the Scriptures or a related hymn in the hymnbook, and share what they learn. Why are these principles important to the Lord?</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>Love, example, and testimony.</heading>
<p>After discussing Jonah's warning to the people of Nineveh, President Henry B. Eyring shared an experience in which his mother gave him a warning:
"I can still remember my mother speaking softly to me one Saturday afternoon when, as a little boy, I asked her for permission to do something I thought was perfectly reasonable and which she knew was dangerous. I still am amazed at the power she was granted, I believe from the Lord, to turn me around with so few words. As I remember them, they were: «Oh, I suppose you<i>could</i>do that. But the<i>choice</i>is yours.» The only warning was in the emphasis she put on the words<i>could</i>and<i>choice</i>. Yet that was enough for me.
"Her power to warn with so few words sprang from three things I knew about her. First, I knew she loved me. Second, I knew she had already done what she wanted me to do and been blessed by it. And third, she had conveyed to me her sure testimony that the choice I had to make was so important that the Lord would tell me what to do if I asked Him. Love, example, and testimony: those were keys that day" ("A Voice of Warning," Ensign, Nov. 1998, 32).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Prepare yourself.</b>Powerful gospel teaching begins with preparing ourselves. Before you prepare your lesson, focus on filling your heart with the Holy Ghost through meaningful study and prayer. (See Teaching in the Savior's Way, 12.)</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<graphics-caption>"His ways are everlasting" (Habakkuk 3:6).<i>In the Beginning was the Word,</i>by Eva Timothy</graphics-caption>
<heading type="date">NOVEMBER 28–DECEMBER 4</heading>
<heading type="ref">Nahum; Habakkuk; Zephaniah</heading>
<heading type="title">"HIS WAYS ARE EVERLASTING"</heading>
<p>Your example as a gospel learner can bless members of your class. Share with them how the Holy Ghost is helping you understand the scriptures, and express your confidence that He can help them too.</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>To give class members an opportunity to share insights from their scripture study, you could write<i>Nahum, Habakkuk,</i>and<i>Zephaniah</i>as headings on the board. Then class members could write under the headings a word or phrase that stood out to them and the chapter and verse where they found it. Give them time to explain why these words or phrases were meaningful and what the Holy Ghost taught them.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>NAHUM 1</heading>
<heading>The Lord is both powerful and merciful.</heading>
<ul>
<li>This week's outline in<i>Come, Follow Me—For Individuals and Families</i>suggests searching Nahum 1 for verses that describe the Lord's attributes. You might ask class members what they learned about the Lord from their personal study. For example, what do we learn about Him from verses 1–9? You might point out that Nahum prophesied of the Lord's judgments against Nineveh, the capital of Assyria, and that Assyria had oppressed the Israelites for many years. Why was it important for the Israelites to hear Nahum's message about God? Why is it important for us today?</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>The Lord is good, a strong hold in the day of trouble" (Nahum 1:7).</graphics-caption>
<heading>HABAKKUK 1:1–4; 2:1–4; 3</heading>
<heading>We can trust the Lord's will and His timing.</heading>
<ul>
<li>It might be helpful for class members to know that, like many of us, Habakkuk was troubled by what he saw in the world around him. Perhaps class members could read Habakkuk 1:1–4 and summarize Habakkuk's concerns. They could also compare his questions with others in the scriptures, such as those found in Mark 4:37–38 and Doctrine and Covenants 121:1–6. What similar questions do people ask about God today? What counsel did the Lord give in Habakkuk 2:1–4 that helps you trust His will and timing? (see also Mark 4:39–40; Doctrine and Covenants 121:7–8). Class members could find other helpful insights in "Additional Resources." They could also share how the Savior has helped them "live by [their] faith" even when they have unanswered questions.</li>
<li>To begin a discussion of Habakkuk 3, you could invite class members to review the chapter and share expressions of praise and faith they find. To help them apply these words to themselves, you might invite each class member to write a list of blessings God has given him or her. Invite them to ponder what would happen if they lost some of their temporal blessings. Read together Habakkuk 3:17–19, and discuss why it might be hard to "rejoice in the Lord" (verse 18) during hardships like those described in verse 17. How can we develop faith like Habakkuk's?</li>
</ul>
<heading>ZEPHANIAH 3:14–20</heading>
<heading>The Lord will rejoice with His people</heading>
<ul>
<li>To help class members find hope for the future in Zephaniah 3:14–20, you could write on the board<i>"Be glad and rejoice with all the heart" because. . .</i>Then class members could search these verses for blessings promised for the future that can help them rejoice today. How do these promises help us during difficult times?</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>Faith means trusting God's wisdom, compassion, and timing.</heading>
<p>Elder Jeffrey R. Holland said:
"How long do we wait for relief from hardships that come upon us? What about enduring personal trials while we wait and wait, and help seems so slow in coming? Why the delay when burdens seem more than we can bear?. . . 
". . . There will be times in our lives when even our best spiritual effort and earnest, pleading prayers do not yield the victories for which we have yearned, whether that be regarding the large global matters or the small personal ones. So while we work and wait together for the answers to some of our prayers, I offer you my apostolic promise that they are heard and they are answered, though perhaps not at the time or in the way we wanted. But they are<i>always</i>answered at the time and in the way an omniscient and eternally compassionate parent should answer in Zion.
". . . Faith means trusting God in good times and bad, even if that includes some suffering until we see His arm revealed in our behalf" ("Waiting on the Lord," Ensign or Liahona, Nov. 2020, 115–16).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Ask open-ended questions.</b>When asking class members about their experiences with the scriptures, "let them know that you aren't looking for a specific answer but that you are sincerely interested in what they are learning" (Teaching in the Savior's Way, 29). For some examples of open-ended questions, see<i>Teaching in the Savior's Way,</i>31–32.</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<graphics-caption>Laie Hawaii Temple</graphics-caption>
<heading type="date">DECEMBER 5–11</heading>
<heading type="ref">Haggai; Zechariah 1–3; 7–14</heading>
<heading type="title">"HOLINESS UNTO THE LORD"</heading>
<p>As you study Haggai and Zechariah, ponder how you can help class members find meaning in these prophecies.</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>Class members could share verses from Haggai and Zechariah that they pondered or discussed with others this week and discuss how these verses helped them draw closer to the Lord.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>HAGGAI 1; 2:1–9</heading>
<heading>"Consider your ways."</heading>
<ul>
<li>The counsel in Haggai 1 can help class members think about their priorities. You could invite them to read Haggai 1:1–7 and identify how the people in Jerusalem were failing to prioritize what the Lord wanted them to do. What are some things the Lord has asked us to make high priorities in our lives? What can distract us from focusing on Heavenly Father and the Savior and Their priorities? Perhaps class members could share experiences that have helped them "consider [their] ways" and their priorities.</li>
<li>To help class members think about how they can focus more completely on the Lord's priorities, you could ask them to review Haggai 2:1–9. What counsel did the Lord give that can help us do His work? Class members could share how they are able to put the Lord's priorities first in their lives as they deal with their many other important responsibilities. What does Haggai 2:1–9 teach about how the Lord blesses us when we put Him first in our lives? (see also "Additional Resources"). Give class members time to write down what they feel inspired to do because of this discussion.</li>
</ul>
<heading>ZECHARIAH 1–3; 7–8; 14</heading>
<heading>The Lord can make us holy.</heading>
<ul>
<li>To begin a discussion about holiness, you could read together Zechariah 14:20–21. Class members could share what the phrase "Holiness unto the Lord" means to them. What influence might it have on people if they saw the phrase "Holiness unto the Lord" inscribed on everyday objects? How does this phrase affect us when we see it on temples today? Class members could then read Zechariah 1:1–6; 3:1–7; 7:8–10; 8:16–17 and discuss what they learn about what it means to be holy. Why is our personal holiness important to the Lord? How does He help us become holy?</li>
<li>Class members could review Zechariah 2:10–11; 8:1–8; 14:9–11, 20–21 and share their impressions about what it would be like to live with the Savior in a state of holiness. How does the Lord prepare us to live in the conditions Zechariah described? How can we access His power to help us become more holy?</li>
</ul>
<heading>ZECHARIAH 9:9–11; 11:12–13; 12:10; 13:6–7</heading>
<heading>Jesus Christ is the promised Messiah.</heading>
<ul>
<li>To help class members see connections between Zechariah's words and the Savior's life, as the people in Jesus's time did, you might divide the class into two groups. Give class members in the first group one of these passages: Zechariah 9:9–11; 11:12–13; 12:10; 13:6–7. Give class members in the other group one of these passages: Matthew 21:1–11; 26:14–16; 26:31; John 19:37. Each class member could try to find someone from the other group who has a scripture passage that matches theirs. What do we learn about the Savior from these verses?</li>
<li>To help class members ponder Zechariah 9:9–11, you might show a picture of the Savior's triumphal entry into Jerusalem (see this week's outline in<i>Come, Follow Me—For Individuals and Families</i>). Or you could show the video "The Lord's Triumphal Entry into Jerusalem" (ChurchofJesusChrist.org). Class members could discuss what it might have felt like to be among the people welcoming Jesus into the city. How do we welcome Him into our lives, our homes, and our communities?</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>"Consider your ways."</heading>
<p>After quoting Haggai 1:4–7, Elder Terence M. Vinson taught:
"We can feel enduring joy when our Savior and His gospel become the framework around which we build our lives. However, it's so easy for that framework to become, instead, the things of the world, where the gospel sits as an optional extra or as simply attending church for two hours on Sundays. When this is the case, it is tantamount to putting wages into «a bag with holes.»
"Haggai is telling us to be committed. . . .
"There is no treasure, nor any hobby, nor any status, nor any social media, nor any video games, nor any sport, nor any association with a celebrity, nor anything on earth that is more precious than eternal life. So the Lord's counsel to every person is «consider your ways»" ("True Disciples of the Savior," Ensign or Liahona, Nov. 2019, 9, 11).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Listen.</b>Listening is an act of love. One way to listen effectively is to look at the person who is speaking. This allows you to notice any nonverbal communication. (See Teaching in the Savior's Way, 34.)</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<heading type="date">DECEMBER 12–18</heading>
<heading type="ref">Malachi</heading>
<heading type="title">"I HAVE LOVED YOU, SAITH THE LORD"</heading>
<p>Some messages in Malachi may be especially important for your class to learn. As you study, pray to discern what those messages might be. Doing this will also help you feel the love that the Lord has for those you teach.</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>You might begin a discussion about the book of Malachi by writing the word<i>Message</i>on the board. Encourage class members to share important messages that they found in each chapter of Malachi. To help class members remember and ponder what is shared, you could write those messages on the board.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>MALACHI 1:6–14</heading>
<heading>The Lord asks for "a pure offering."</heading>
<ul>
<li>To encourage class members to share what they learned about offerings from Malachi 1:6–14, you could invite them to review these verses silently and discuss with another class member something that the Israelite priests did not understand about offerings. Why does the Lord ask for the best from us? Class members could make a list of offerings, or sacrifices, that we make to the Lord today. For each item on the list, they could discuss what might make it a "polluted" offering or a "pure" offering (Malachi 1:7, 11).</li>
</ul>
<heading>MALACHI 3–4</heading>
<heading>Malachi's prophecies are being fulfilled in the latter days.</heading>
<ul>
<li>You could begin a discussion about Malachi 3–4 by pointing out that Moroni shared verses from these chapters when he appeared to Joseph Smith (see Joseph Smith — History 1:36–39). What truths in these chapters do class members feel might have been especially important for Joseph — and us — to know? Class members could get into small groups and list as many truths as they can. Encourage groups to share their lists and discuss why these truths are important in the latter days.</li>
</ul>
<heading>MALACHI 3:8–12</heading>
<heading>The Lord opens the windows of heaven when we pay our tithing.</heading>
<ul>
<li>To encourage class members to share their testimonies of the law of tithing, you could invite them to find principles in Malachi 3:8–12 and to share how they came to know these principles are true. They could talk about how the Lord has blessed them — spiritually and temporally — for paying tithing. Or they could discuss lessons about tithing that Elder David A. Bednar shared in his message "The Windows of Heaven" (Ensign or Liahona, Nov. 2013, 17–20) and share what they have learned as they have strived to live this law.</li>
<li>Ask class members to read Malachi 3:8–12 silently while pondering how they might teach someone why the Lord asks us to pay tithing. They could also read the statement by President Gordon B. Hinckley in "Additional Resources." What would we want others to understand about tithing? For example, what does it mean to pay tithing? Why does the Lord want us to do it? How are the "windows of heaven" (verse 10) opened when we pay tithing? What concerns might someone have about paying tithing, and how would we respond? Ask class members to share how keeping this commandment has strengthened their faith in Heavenly Father and Jesus Christ.</li>
</ul>
<heading>MALACHI 4:5–6</heading>
<heading>"I will send you Elijah the prophet."</heading>
<ul>
<li>Class members might gain helpful insights about Malachi 4:5–6 by comparing these verses to the way Moroni quoted them to Joseph Smith in Joseph Smith — History 1:38–39. (It might help to have someone write each version side by side on the board.) What does Moroni's wording add to our understanding of the verses in Malachi? You might also discuss questions like these: Who are "the fathers"? (see Deuteronomy 29:13). How do our hearts turn to our fathers, and how do their hearts turn to us? To help your class understand how Malachi's prophecy was fulfilled, they could read about when Elijah committed the sealing keys to Joseph Smith (see Doctrine and Covenants 110:13–16). Why are class members grateful these keys have been restored?</li>
<li>Malachi 4:5–6 provides a great opportunity to talk about temple and family history work. Perhaps class members could share experiences they have had while doing this work and how those experiences have helped them turn their hearts to their fathers. What can we do to help future generations turn their hearts toward us?</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>Illustration of Elijah appearing to Joseph Smith and Oliver Cowdery in the Kirtland Temple, by Robert T. Barrett</graphics-caption>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>Tithing is a matter of faith.</heading>
<p>President Gordon B. Hinckley said, "We<i>can</i>pay our tithing. This is not so much a matter of money as it is a matter of faith. I have yet to find a faithful tithe payer who cannot testify that in a very literal and wonderful way the windows of heaven have been opened and blessings have been poured out upon him or her" ("Let Us Move This Work Forward, "Ensign, Nov. 1985, 85).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Share your struggles and your faith.</b>Sometimes people who are experiencing trials feel alone. It may be appropriate to occasionally share a personal experience about a time when you struggled and how the Savior helped you.</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<graphics-caption>For unto Us a Child Is Born, by Simon Dewey</graphics-caption>
<heading type="date">DECEMBER 19–25</heading>
<heading type="ref">Christmas</heading>
<heading type="title">"WE HAVE WAITED FOR HIM, AND HE WILL SAVE US"</heading>
<p>During your personal study and preparation to teach, consider how you can help class members feel the resounding joy of the Savior's birth. Invite the Spirit to testify to them of Jesus Christ's redeeming love.</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>Christmastime might be a good opportunity to invite class members to share how studying the Old Testament has strengthened their faith in Jesus Christ.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>We rejoice in our Redeemer.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Even though Christmas is known as a season of joy, there are many whose circumstances make it hard to find joy, even during this time of year. An important message of Christmas is that the Savior can ease our burdens and help us find peace and even joy. To share this message, you could write on the board the following scripture references: Psalm 35:9; Isaiah 25:8–9; 44:21–24; 51:11; Zephaniah 3:14–20; Moses 5:5–11. Then you could write on the board a question for class members to ponder as they read the passages, like<i>What reasons do these scripture passages give to be joyful?</i>Ask them to share what they find. Perhaps you could also give class members time to write about their own joy in the Savior. They might find additional insights from President Russell M. Nelson's message in "Additional Resources."</li>
<li>Christmas provides opportunities to spread the joy of Christ by serving others. Ahead of class, you might invite a class member to review Elder Ulisses Soares's message "A Modern Angelic Host" (First Presidency Christmas devotional, Dec. 8, 2019, broadcasts.ChurchofJesusChrist.org) and come prepared to share how an act of service helped Elder Soares and his family feel the joy of Christmas. You could also share portions of his message in class. Class members could share their own experiences of giving or receiving acts of service at Christmastime. How can we act on Elder Soares's invitation to follow the Savior's "perfect example of love and goodwill toward men"?</li>
</ul>
<heading>Symbols can help us remember Jesus Christ.</heading>
<ul>
<li>This week's outline in<i>Come, Follow Me—For Individuals and Families</i>lists some symbols in the Old Testament that teach about Jesus Christ. Class members could share what they learned about the Savior from these and other symbols they found in their study. What have we learned about finding the Savior in the scriptures? What experiences have taught us that "all things are created and made to bear record of [Him]"? (Moses 6:63).</li>
</ul>
<heading>God gave us the gift of His Son.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Gift giving is a Christmas tradition in most cultures. You could lead a discussion with class members about the gifts God has given us, especially the gift of His Son, Jesus Christ. To do this, you could share the video "He Is the Gift" (ChurchofJesusChrist.org) and invite class members to share what the gift of the Savior means to them. How can we show Heavenly Father our gratitude for this gift?</li>
</ul>
<heading>ISAIAH 7:14; 9:6</heading>
<heading>"His name shall be called Wonderful."</heading>
<ul>
<li>The prophet Isaiah used many names and titles to describe the Messiah, who would be born in Bethlehem (see for example, Isaiah 7:14; 9:6). Perhaps class members would enjoy learning more about the Savior and His mission by learning about these titles. They could pick a title and find other scripture passages that help them understand what it means. For example, they might learn more about the title "Prince of Peace" (Isaiah 9:6) by reading Psalm 85:8; Isaiah 52:7; Luke 2:14; or John 16:33. To help class members find other scriptures, suggest that they look in Guide to the Scriptures (scriptures.ChurchofJesusChrist.org). What do these titles suggest about the Savior and what He does for us?</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>Jesus Christ offers peace and joy.</heading>
<p>President Russell M. Nelson taught:
"When the focus of our lives is on God's plan of salvation. . . and Jesus Christ and His gospel, we can feel joy regardless of what is happening — or not happening — in our lives. Joy comes from and because of Him. He is the source of all joy. We feel it at Christmastime when we sing, «Joy to the world, the Lord is come» [Hymns, no. 201]. And we can feel it all year round. For latter-day Saints, Jesus Christ is joy!. . .
"Just as the Savior offers peace that «passeth all understanding» [Philippians 4:7], He also offers an intensity, depth, and breadth of joy that defy human logic or mortal comprehension" ("Joy and Spiritual Survival," Ensign or Liahona, Nov. 2016, 82).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Prepare with people in mind.</b>"Let your understanding of the people you teach guide your plans. . . . Christlike teachers are not committed to a particular style or method; they are committed to helping people build faith in Jesus Christ" (Teaching in the Savior's Way, 7).</p>
</chapter>
</text>