<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text>
<header
		manual-title="New Testament 2023 Come, Follow Me—For Sunday School"
		audience="adult-teacher"
		copyright="2022"
		usage-years="2023"
		standard-work="new-testament"
		edition="updated-significant"
		era="come-follow-me">
	</header>
<chapter type="cover">
<heading>NEW TESTAMENT 2023</heading>
<heading>Come, Follow Me—For Sunday School</heading>
<heading>Living, Learning, and Teaching the Gospel of Jesus Christ</heading>
</chapter>
<chapter type="copyright">
<heading>NEW TESTAMENT 2023</heading>
<heading>Come, Follow Me—For Sunday School</heading>
<heading>Living, Learning, and Teaching the Gospel of Jesus Christ</heading>
<p>Published by
The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints
Salt Lake City, Utah</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="title-page">
<p>© 2022 by Intellectual Reserve, Inc.
All rights reserved.
Version: 9/20
17849 000
Printed in the United States of America
Comments and corrections are appreciated. Please send them, including errors, to ComeFollowMe@ChurchofJesusChrist.org.</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="teacher-help">
<heading>You Are a Teacher in the Church of Jesus Christ</heading>
<p>You have been called of God to teach His children in the Savior's way. You were set apart to this calling by the authority of His holy priesthood. Even if you are not an experienced teacher, as you live worthily, pray daily, and study the scriptures, Heavenly Father will grant you the influence and power of the Holy Ghost to help you succeed (see 2 Nephi 33:1).</p>
<p>Those entrusted to your care are Heavenly Father's children, and He knows what they need and how best to reach them. As you prayerfully seek the influence of the Holy Ghost, He will guide you as you prepare and while you are teaching. He will reveal to you what you should say and what you should do (see 2 Nephi 32:5).</p>
<p>The essential purpose of gospel teaching and learning is to deepen conversion to Heavenly Father and Jesus Christ. Your goal as a teacher is to help those you teach do all they can to become more converted an effort that extends far beyond class time. Invite those you teach to actively participate in learning about Jesus Christ and His gospel and to act on what they learn. Encourage them to make their individual and family study outside of class the primary source of their gospel learning. As they act in faith by studying as individuals and families, they will invite the Spirit into their lives, and it is the Spirit that brings about true conversion. Everything you do as a teacher should point to this sacred objective.</p>
<p>Teach only the doctrine of the restored gospel of Jesus Christ as found in the scriptures and the words of latter-day prophets. Pure doctrine — eternal, unchanging truth taught by God and His servants — invites the Spirit and has the power to change lives.</p>
<p>The calling to teach is a sacred trust, and it is normal to feel overwhelmed at times. But remember that your Heavenly Father called you, and He will never forsake you. This is the Lord's work, and as you serve "with all your heart, might, mind and strength" (Doctrine and Covenants 4:2), He will enlarge your capacities, gifts, and talents, and your service will bless the lives of those you teach.</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="teacher-help">
<heading>Using Come, Follow Me—For Sunday School</heading>
<heading>Preparing to Teach in Sunday School</heading>
<p>Personal and family study at home should be the center of gospel learning. This is true for you and for those you teach. As you prepare to teach, start by having your own experiences in the scriptures. Your most important preparation will occur as you live the gospel, search the scriptures, and seek the inspiration of the Holy Ghost.</p>
<p>Come, Follow Me—For Individuals and Families is an important part of both your personal study and your preparation to teach. It will help you gain a deeper understanding of the doctrinal principles found in the scriptures. It will also enable you to inspire and invite class members to use Come, Follow Me—For Individuals and Families to enhance their personal and family scripture study (for help doing this, see "Ideas for Encouraging Personal and Family Study" in this resource). As you do, remember to be sensitive to class members whose family circumstances may not support regular family scripture study and home evening.</p>
<p>During your preparation, thoughts and impressions will come to you about the people you teach. You will receive insights about how the principles in the scriptures will bless their lives. You will be guided to inspire them to discover those principles as they learn from the scriptures for themselves.</p>
<heading>Teaching Ideas</heading>
<p>As you prepare to teach, you might gain additional inspiration by exploring the teaching outlines in this resource. Don't think of these ideas as step-by-step instructions but rather as suggestions to spark your own inspiration. You know your class members, and you will get to know them even better as you learn together in class. The Lord knows them too, and He will inspire you with the best ways to help class members build on their gospel learning at home.</p>
<p>Many other resources are available for you to use as you prepare, including ideas in Come, Follow Me—For Individuals and Families and Church magazines. For more information about these and other resources, see "Additional Resources" in this resource.</p>
<heading>Some Things to Keep in Mind</heading>
<ul>
<li>Gospel learning is most effective when it is centered in the home. As a teacher, you have an important responsibility to support, encourage, and build upon class members' gospel learning at home.</li>
<li>Class members' conversion to Jesus Christ and His gospel will deepen as they understand and apply true doctrine. Encourage them to record and act on the impressions they receive from the Holy Ghost.</li>
<li>Teaching is more than lecturing, but it is also more than simply leading a discussion. Part of your role is to encourage participation that edifies and is based on the scriptures. You should also share the inspired insights you received as you studied the scriptures.</li>
<li>Remember that many class members are having meaningful experiences studying at home the same scriptures that you will be discussing in class. You can support their scripture study by providing them with frequent opportunities to share what they are learning at home.</li>
<li>Heavenly Father wants you to succeed as a teacher. He has provided many resources to help you, including teacher council meetings. In these meetings you can counsel with other teachers about challenges you face. You can also discuss and practice principles of Christlike teaching.</li>
<li>People learn best when they have opportunities to teach. On occasion, consider allowing class members, including youth, to teach a part of the lesson. Base this decision on the needs and abilities of class members. If you do invite a class member to teach, take the time to help him or her prepare in advance by using the ideas found in this resource and in Come, Follow Me—For Individuals and Families. Remember that as the called teacher, you are ultimately responsible for what is taught in class. </li>
</ul>
<p>This resource includes teaching outlines for every week of the year. On Sundays when Sunday School is not held because of general conference, stake conference, or any other reason, class members are encouraged to continue reading the New Testament at home according to the schedule outlined in Come, Follow Me—For Individuals and Families. When Sunday School is held, you may choose to either skip or combine outlines.</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="teacher-help">
<heading>Ideas for Encouraging Personal and Family Study</heading>
<p>Here are some ideas to help you encourage class members to study the word of God at home, both individually and as families. Be sensitive to the fact that not all class members can study the scriptures with their families (for example, some members live alone or in part-member families).</p>
<ul>
<li>Invite class members to share experiences they had studying the scriptures at home. For example, you could ask them to share a verse that impressed them and to explain why they found it meaningful.</li>
<li>Ask class members to give examples of what they are doing to make personal or family scripture study more meaningful. (Some ideas can be found under "Ideas to Improve Your Personal Scripture Study" and "Ideas to Improve Your Family Scripture Study" in Come, Follow Me—For Individuals and Families.)</li>
<li>Invite class members to share how they acted on impressions they received during their personal or family scripture study. </li>
<li>Spend a few minutes showing class members some of the resources provided by the Church to help members study the gospel. These resources include the scripture study helps found at scriptures.ChurchofJesusChrist.org; "Scripture Stories" found at children. ChurchofJesusChrist.org; teaching outlines and other resources in Come, Follow Me—For Primary; youth-focused content at youth.ChurchofJesusChrist.org; seminary and institute manuals; and videos, audio recordings, and images found at GospelMedia.ChurchofJesusChrist.org. Many of these are also in the Gospel Library app.</li>
<li>Spend a few minutes explaining how to use the Gospel Library app to study the scriptures, including how to mark verses and record impressions.</li>
<li>Invite one or more class members to share how they have taught or learned a specific gospel principle in their families.</li>
</ul>
</chapter>
<chapter type="teacher-help">
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<p>These resources can be found in the Gospel Library app and at Churchof Jesus Christ.org.</p>
<heading>Come, Follow Me—For Individuals and Families</heading>
<p>You can adapt any activities from Come, Follow Me For Individuals and Families for use in your Sunday School class. If class members have used these activities in their personal or family scripture study, encourage them to share their experiences and insights.</p>
<heading>Hymns and Children's Songbook</heading>
<p>Sacred music invites the Spirit, helps us feel the love of God, and teaches doctrine in a memorable way. In addition to using the print versions of Hymns and the Children's Songbook, you can find video and audio recordings of many hymns and children's songs at music.ChurchofJesusChrist.org and in the Sacred Music and Gospel Media apps.</p>
<heading>Seminary and Institute Manuals</heading>
<p>Seminary and Institute Manuals provide historical background and doctrinal commentary for principles and accounts found in the scriptures. They may also inspire teaching ideas for Sunday School classes.</p>
<heading>Church Magazines</heading>
<p>The Liahona and For the Strength of Youth magazines provide articles and other features that can supplement the principles you are teaching from Come, Follow Me—For Sunday School.</p>
<heading>Gospel Topics</heading>
<p>In Gospel Topics (topics.ChurchofJesusChrist.org), you can find basic information about a variety of gospel topics, along with links to helpful resources, such as related general conference messages, articles, scriptures, and videos. You can also find Gospel Topics Essays, which offer in-depth information about doctrinal and historical issues, as well as answers to a variety of questions about the Church and its teachings.</p>
<heading>Preach My Gospel</heading>
<p>This guide for missionaries provides an overview of the basic principles of the gospel.</p>
<heading>For the Strength of Youth (booklet)</heading>
<p>This resource outlines Church standards that can help us live the gospel and enjoy the companionship of the Spirit. Consider referring to it often, especially if you are teaching youth.</p>
<heading>Videos and Art</heading>
<p>Artwork, videos, and other media can help those you teach understand doctrine and visualize stories related to the scriptures. Visit Gospel Media at GospelMedia.ChurchofJesusChrist.org to browse the Church's collection of media resources. Gospel Media is also available as a mobile app. Many images that you can use in class are found in the Gospel Art Book.</p>
<heading>Teaching in the Savior's Way</heading>
<p>Teaching in the Savior's Way can help you learn about and apply principles of Christlike teaching. These principles are discussed and practiced in teacher council meetings.</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="teacher-help">
<heading>A Pattern for Teaching</heading>
<p>Each outline in this resource follows a pattern of inviting, sharing, and teaching the doctrine.</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>As part of every class, invite class members to share insights and experiences they had during the previous week as they studied the scriptures as individuals and families and applied what they learned. Help class members see that their personal learning outside of class is important. Their individual conversion to Heavenly Father and Jesus Christ will come not only through Sunday learning but also through their daily experiences. When class members hear each other's experiences and testimonies of Jesus Christ and His gospel, they are more likely to seek similar experiences of their own.</p>
<p>Not everyone will have read the chapters for each lesson, and even some who did may not feel comfortable sharing. Make sure all class members feel they are a valued part of the class, whether or not they have something to share.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<p>You and your class members should focus on Jesus Christ and His doctrine — the eternal truths of the gospel — found in the assigned scripture passages. Come, Follow Me—For Individuals and Families can help you better understand the doctrine you will teach. As you discuss doctrine from the scriptures, what verses, quotations, experiences, questions, and additional resources might you share? How might you use these resources to help class members discover and understand gospel principles? How can you help them build their faith in Heavenly Father and Jesus Christ?</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<heading>DECEMBER 26–JANUARY 1</heading>
<heading>We Are Responsible for Our Own Learning</heading>
<p>As you read and ponder the scripture passages in this outline, record the spiritual impressions you receive. This will invite the Spirit into your preparation.<i>Come, Follow Me—For Individuals and Families</i>and the following ideas can help you inspire the people in your class to study the New Testament this year.</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>One of your objectives as a teacher is to encourage class members to learn from the scriptures on their own and with their families. Hearing the experiences of others can inspire them to seek their own experiences. So, at the beginning of each class, ask class members to share scriptures from their study that inspired or impressed them.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>Learning requires acting in faith.</heading>
<ul>
<li>How can you inspire your class members to take a more active role in their learning, rather than placing sole responsibility on the teacher? Here's an idea. Toss a soft object to a class member, whom you have previously asked to make no effort to catch it. Use this activity to begin a discussion about the roles of learners and teachers in gospel learning. As learners, how do we "catch" what is taught in our classes? The statements found in "Additional Resources" could help in this discussion.</li>
<li>All class members have responsibility to invite the Spirit into the class. To help class members understand this, ask them to read Alma 1:26 and Doctrine and Covenants 50:13–22; 88:122–23 and share what teachers and students can do to invite the Spirit. It might be helpful to write their responses on the board under headings such as these:<i>What the teacher can do</i>and<i>What the learners can do.</i>Class members could create a poster with their responses that could be displayed for the next few weeks.</li>
</ul>
<heading>We need to know the truth for ourselves.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Many passages in the New Testament teach principles that can guide our search for truth. Examples include Luke 11:9–13; John 5:39; 7:14–17; and 1 Corinthians 2:9–11. You could invite members of your class who read these passages in their personal study to share what they learned. Or you could read these passages as a class and invite class members to share how they gained their testimonies.</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>Seeking learning by faith will help us gain our own testimonies.</graphics-caption>
<ul>
<li>Acts 17:10–12 describes Saints who searched the scriptures and gained their own witness of the truth. To encourage class members to follow their example, read these verses together and invite class members to share scripture passages that have strengthened their testimonies of the gospel.</li>
</ul>
<heading>How can we make our scripture study more meaningful?</heading>
<ul>
<li>Developing the habit of scripture study may be challenging for class members who feel that they don't have the necessary time, understanding, or skills. What can you do to help them be successful? To help class members gain the confidence to study the scriptures, you could share information from "Ideas to Improve Your Personal Scripture Study" in<i>Come, Follow Me—For Individuals and Families.</i>Perhaps you or other class members could share experiences with using some of these ideas or other meaningful experiences studying the scriptures. You could also select a chapter in the New Testament and try studying it as a class using some of these ideas.</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>Claiming spiritual knowledge for ourselves.</heading>
<p>The Prophet Joseph Smith taught: "The things of God are of deep import; and time, and experience, and careful and ponderous and solemn thoughts can only find them out. Thy mind, O man! if thou wilt lead a soul unto salvation, must stretch as high as the utmost heavens, and search into and contemplate the darkest abyss, and the broad expanse of eternity — thou must commune with God. How much more dignified and noble are the thoughts of God, than the vain imaginations of the human heart!" (Teachings of Presidents of the Church: Joseph Smith [2007], 267).</p>
<p>Elder David A. Bednar explained: "If all you or I know about Jesus Christ and His restored gospel is what other people teach or tell us, then the foundation of our testimony of Him and His glorious latter-day work is built upon sand. We cannot rely exclusively upon or borrow gospel light and knowledge from other people — even those whom we love and trust" ("Prepared to Obtain Every Needful Thing," Ensign or Liahona, May 2019, 102).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Stay focused on doctrine.</b>Ensure that class discussions remain grounded in the scriptures and the teachings of the prophets. You can do this by asking questions like these: "What gospel truths do we learn from the comments we have heard?" or "Can someone share a scripture that relates to what we've discussed?" (See Teaching in the Savior's Way, 20–21.)</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<heading>JANUARY 2–8</heading>
<heading>Matthew 1; Luke 1</heading>
<heading>"BE IT UNTO ME ACCORDING TO THY WORD"</heading>
<p>Before read additional study materials, read and ponder Matthew 1 and Luke 1, you any and record your spiritual impressions. Let the Spirit guide your preparation. Then explore the ideas in this outline and in<i>Come, Follow Me—For Individuals and Families.</i></p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>A main purpose of Matthew, Luke, and the other Gospel writers was to testify that Jesus Christ is the Son of God. Give class members a few minutes to review Matthew 1 or Luke 1 and share a verse that builds their faith in Jesus Christ. Suggest to the class that as they study the New Testament this year, they might keep a list of passages that testify that Jesus Christ is the Son of God. You could even keep this list as a class.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>MATTHEW 1:18–25; LUKE 1:5–80</heading>
<heading>Heavenly Father works through His faithful children to accomplish His purposes.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Class members are more likely to have meaningful experiences while studying the New Testament this year if they can draw lessons from the experiences of the people they read about. To help them do this, you could write the names of the people in Matthew 1 and Luke 1 on the board, along with scripture references about these individuals, as follows:
<ul>
<li>Mary (Luke 1:26–56)</li>
<li>Joseph (Matthew 1:18–25)</li>
<li>Elisabeth (Luke 1:5–7, 24–25, 40–45, 57–60)</li>
<li>Zacharias (Luke 1:5–23, 59–64)</li>
</ul>
What can we learn from these accounts that will help us today?</li>
<li>To help class members think more deeply about Mary and her role in the Father's plan, you could show the videos "An Angel Foretells Christ's Birth to Mary" and "Mary and Elisabeth Rejoice Together" (ChurchofJesusChrist.org). Or you could read together Luke 1:26–38, 46–56, looking for things Mary said that reveal something about her character. What else do we learn from Mary?</li>
</ul>
<heading>LUKE 1:5–25</heading>
<heading>God's blessings come in His own time.</heading>
<ul>
<li>There may be people in your class who, like Elisabeth and Zacharias, are living righteously and yet have not received a hoped-for blessing. Consider inviting the class to search Luke 1:5–25, looking for lessons they can learn from Elisabeth and Zacharias about waiting on the Lord. What other examples of waiting on the Lord's timing can class members share from their own lives or from accounts in the scriptures? What do we learn from these examples? Class members could also discuss the statement in "Additional Resources."</li>
</ul>
<heading>LUKE 1:26–38</heading>
<heading>"With God nothing shall be impossible."</heading>
<ul>
<li>Class members may at times wonder — as Mary did — how God's plans for them or promises to them can be fulfilled. To help class members understand that through God's power all things are possible, you could display the picture The Annunciation: The Angel Gabriel Appears to Mary (Gospel Art Book, no. 28) and invite them to read together Luke 1:26–38. What can we learn about overcoming the seemingly impossible by studying Mary's words and actions? Ask class members to share experiences in which God helped them accomplish something they thought was impossible.</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>Waiting on the Lord.</heading>
<p>Acknowledging that many of us question why we have to wait for God's blessings, Elder Jeffrey R. Holland said:
"The answer to such questions is «Yes, God can provide miracles instantaneously, but sooner or later we learn that the times and seasons of our mortal journey are His and His alone to direct.» . . . Faith means trusting God in good times and bad, even if that includes some suffering until we see His arm revealed in our behalf. . . .
". . . Those who «<i>wait upon the Lord</i>shall renew their strength [and] shall mount up with wings as eagles; they shall run, and not be weary; . . . they shall walk, and not faint» [Isaiah 40:31; emphasis added]. I pray that «by and by» — soon or late — those blessings will come to every one of you who seeks relief from your sorrow and freedom from your grief. I bear witness of God's love and of the Restoration of His glorious gospel, which is, in one way or another, the answer issue we face in life" ("Waiting on the Lord," Ensign or Liahona, Nov. 2020, 116–17).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Encourage class members to study the scriptures at home.</b>One way you can encourage scripture study at home is to provide time for class members to share discoveries and insights from their personal and family study (see Teaching in the Savior's Way, 29).</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<graphics-caption>Let Us Adore Him, by Dana Mario Wood</graphics-caption>
<heading>JANUARY 9–15</heading>
<heading>Matthew 2; Luke 2</heading>
<heading>WE HAVE COME TO WORSHIP HIM</heading>
<p>Before you read the ideas in this outline, study Matthew 2 and Luke 2, and record your spiritual impressions. This will help you receive revelation on how to best meet the needs of your class.</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>How can you encourage class members to share insights and experiences they had as they studied the scriptures individually and with their families? Though they are likely familiar with the accounts of the Savior's birth in Matthew 2 and Luke 2, they can always gain new spiritual insights. Consider inviting a few class members to share a message they found that impressed them in a new way.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>MATTHEW 2:1–12; LUKE 2:1–38</heading>
<heading>There are many witnesses of the birth of Christ.</heading>
<ul>
<li>The accounts of worshippers in Matthew 2:1–12 and Luke 2:1–38 can help your class members ponder the ways they show their love for the Savior. Review the chart about witnesses of Christ's birth in this week's outline in<i>Come, Follow Me—For Individuals and Families.</i>Some people your class may have insights to share from this activity, or you could do the activity as a class. Why is it significant that these witnesses of Christ came from various walks of life? How can we follow their examples?</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>The shepherds became some of the first witnesses of the Savior's birth.</graphics-caption>
<ul>
<li>Before these witnesses worshipped the Christ child, they sought after Him. To help class members learn from their example, you could write on the board the following headings:<i>Shepherds, Anna, Simeon,</i>and<i>Wise Men.</i>Then class members could search Matthew 2 and Luke 2 and write on the board what these people did to seek the Savior. What do these accounts suggest about some of the ways we can seek Christ?</li>
</ul>
<heading>MATTHEW 2:13–23</heading>
<heading>Parents can receive revelation to protect their families.</heading>
<ul>
<li>To begin a discussion about how Heavenly Father guided Joseph and Mary in their role as the Savior's parents, consider inviting class members to list on the board some of the dangers we face today. What do we learn from Matthew 2:13–23 about how to find protection from these dangers? How has personal revelation helped us protect our families or other loved ones from danger? What counsel have prophets and apostles given to help us find spiritual safety?</li>
</ul>
<heading>LUKE 2:40–52</heading>
<heading>Even as a youth, Jesus was focused on doing His Father's will.</heading>
<ul>
<li>The story of Jesus teaching in the temple when He was only 12 years old can be especially powerful to youth who wonder about the contribution they can make to the work of God. You could divide the class into pairs to read Luke 2:40–52 together (see the insight from the Joseph Smith Translation found in Luke 2:46, footnote c). Each pair could take a few minutes to share with each other what inspires them about this account. What opportunities do we have to share what we know about the gospel? What experiences can we share?</li>
<li>What does Luke 2:40–52 teach us about what Jesus was like as a youth? The pattern for personal growth suggested in Luke 2:52 could inspire a discussion on what we are doing to become more like Christ. You might suggest that class members ponder how they are increasing in wisdom (intellectually), stature (physically), favor with God (spiritually) Jesus was like as a youth? The pattern for personal growth suggested in Luke 2:52 could inspire a discussion on what we are doing to become more like Christ. You might suggest that class members ponder how they are increasing in wisdom (intellectually), stature (physically), favor with God (spiritually), and favor with others (socially). They could even set goals in one or more of these areas. If you would like to continue a discussion about becoming like Christ in these areas, especially if you teach youth, consider using the statement in "Additional Resources."</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>Helping children and youth grow "in wisdom and stature, and in favour with God and man."</heading>
<p>President Steven J. Lund described the Children and Youth program, which is based in part on Luke 2:52, in this way: "Children and Youth is a tool to help every Primary child and youth to grow in discipleship and to gain a faith-filled vision of what the way of happiness looks like. They can come to anticipate and yearn for the way stations and signposts along the covenant path, where they will be baptized and confirmed with the gift of the Holy Ghost and soon belong to quorums and Young Women classes, where they will feel the joy of helping others through a succession of Christlike acts of service. They will set goals, large and small, that will bring balance to their lives as they become more like the Savior" ("Finding Joy in Christ," Ensign or Liahona, Nov. 2020, 36–37).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Include learners who didn't study the scriptures at home.</b>Even though some class members may not have been able to read Matthew 2 and Luke 2 before class, they can still share meaningful insights. Make sure all class members have opportunities to participate and contribute to the discussion.</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<heading>JANUARY 16–22</heading>
<heading>John 1</heading>
<heading>WE HAVE FOUND THE MESSIAH</heading>
<p>As you read and ponder John 1, pray for spiritual guidance in your responsibility to teach about John's testimony. Record the impressions you receive.<i>Come, Follow Me—For Individuals and Families</i>and the ideas in this outline can help you inspire the people in your class to understand and apply the doctrine in this chapter.</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>To help class members share what they are learning, you might ask them to write questions, comments, or insights from their reading on strips of paper and put them into a container. Draw strips from the container to discuss as a class.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>JOHN 1:1–5</heading>
<heading>Jesus Christ was "in the beginning with God."</heading>
<ul>
<li>What did John teach about the premortal Christ? Why is it important to know about Christ's premortal roles? It might help to write these questions on the board and ask class members to look for answers in John 1:1–5 (see also Joseph Smith Translation, John 1:1–5 [in the Bible appendix]; Moses 1:32–33; Topical Guide, "Jesus Christ, Antemortal Existence of"). Class members could also share what they learn about Christ's premortal roles from "The Living Christ: The Testimony of the Apostles" (ChurchofJesusChrist.org).</li>
<li>If you would like to use these verses to talk about the Lord's creations, you could read John 1:3 and show pictures that depict the beauty of the earth. You might show the video "Our Home" (ChurchofJesusChrist.org). Invite class members to share how the Savior's creations help them feel His love.</li>
</ul>
<heading>JOHN 1:1–14</heading>
<heading>Jesus Christ is the Light.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Consider asking class members to find every instance of the word<i>light</i>in John 1:1–14. Why is<i>light</i>a good word to describe Jesus Christ? Class members could share how the Savior and His gospel provide spiritual light in their lives. As part of this discussion, you might invite class members to read more about the Light of Christ in Doctrine and Covenants 84:45–46; 88:11–13, or you might refer them to "Light of Christ" in the Bible Dictionary. How can we share the Savior's light with others?</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>The Savior and His gospel provide spiritual light.</graphics-caption>
<ul>
<li>To help class members visualize what is taught about the Savior in John 1, you could display several pictures (including the one from this week's outline in Come, Follow Me—For Individuals and Families) that depict aspects of Jesus Christ's life and divine mission. Class members could search John 1:1–14, looking for words or phrases that could serve as titles for the pictures.</li>
</ul>
<heading>JOHN 1:35–51</heading>
<heading>We can gain our own witness of the Savior and then invite others to "come and see."</heading>
<ul>
<li>In John 1, the invitation to "come and see" appears twice (see verses 39, 46). We may have the chance to see the Savior physically the way Andrew and Nathanael did, but we can respond to the same invitation. What might it mean to "come and see" in our day?</li>
<li>Class members could read John 1:35–51 and share what they learn from these verses about inviting others to learn about Christ (see also "Additional Resources" or the video "Inviting Others to «Come and See»" on ChurchofJesusChrist.org). They could also share how they have found simple and natural ways to invite others to "come and see."</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>We can invite others to "come and see."</heading>
<p>Elder Neil L. Andersen taught:
"The Savior taught us how to share the gospel. I like the story of Andrew, who asked, «Master, where dwellest thou?» [John 1:38]. Jesus could have responded with the location of where He lived. But instead He said to Andrew, «Come and see» [John 1:39]. I like to think that the Savior was saying, «Come and see not only where I live but how I live. Come and see who I am. Come and feel the Spirit.» We don't know everything about that day, but we do know that when Andrew found his brother Simon, he declared, «We have found . . . the Christ» [John 1:41]. 
"To those who show an interest in our conversations, we can follow the Savior's example by inviting them to come and see.' Some will accept our invitation, and others will not. We all know someone who has been invited several times before accepting an invitation to come and see" ("It's a Miracle," Ensign or Liahona, May 2013, 79).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Help learners liken the scriptures to themselves.</b>The same invitation Christ gave to His disciples — to come and see — can help those you teach desire to follow the Savior. Encourage learners to apply the principles found in the scriptures to their own lives and to invite others to do the same. (See 1 Nephi 19:23; Teaching in the Savior's Way, 21.)</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<graphics-caption>Stained-glass window in Nauvoo Illinois Temple, by Tom Holdman</graphics-caption>
<heading>JANUARY 23–29</heading>
<heading>Matthew 3; Mark 1; Luke 3</heading>
<heading>"PREPARE YE THE WAY OF THE LORD"</heading>
<p>As you read and ponder Matthew 3; Mark 1; and Luke 3, record the impressions you receive. This will invite the Spirit as you prepare to teach. In addition to the teaching ideas in this outline, the study ideas in<i>Come, Follow Me—For Individuals and Families</i>can be adapted to use with your class.</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>To help class members share how learning from the New Testament is blessing their lives, you could write the following question on the board:<i>What did you do because of what you read in the New Testament this week?</i>Invite class members to share their answers.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>MATTHEW 3:1–12; LUKE 3:2–18</heading>
<heading>Disciples prepare themselves and others to receive Jesus Christ.</heading>
<ul>
<li>How do we prepare for the visit of an important guest? A question like this can help you introduce a discussion about how John the Baptist prepared people to receive Jesus Christ. You could then divide the class into three groups. Each group could read either Matthew 3:1–6; Matthew 3:7–12; or Luke 3:10–15, looking for how John the Baptist prepared people to receive Jesus Christ into their lives. Let each group take a turn sharing what they found.</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>John the Baptist Preaching in the Wilderness, by Robert T. Barrett</graphics-caption>
<heading>LUKE 3:2–14</heading>
<heading>We need to bring forth "fruits worthy of repentance."</heading>
<ul>
<li>In Luke 3:8, John the Baptist taught the people that before they could be baptized, they needed to show "fruits," or evidence, of their repentance. How can you help class members recognize the evidence of their own repentance? You might ask them to search Luke 3:8–14 and look for what John considered "fruits" of repentance. They could also review Moroni 6:1–3 and Doctrine and Covenants 20:37. You might draw a fruit tree on the board and let class members label the fruit on the tree with the "fruits" of repentance they find. This could also be a good time to talk about what it means to truly repent.</li>
</ul>
<heading>MATTHEW 3:13–17</heading>
<heading>We follow Jesus Christ by being baptized and receiving the Holy Ghost.</heading>
<ul>
<li>To review the story of Jesus Christ's baptism, try this idea: Ask class members how they could use Matthew 3:13–17 to teach someone, such as a child or someone of another faith, about baptism. (They could also use the picture in this week's outline in Come, Follow Me—For Individuals and Families.) What important elements of baptism would they emphasize? They could practice their ideas by teaching each other.</li>
<li>To help class members reflect on the importance of living their baptismal covenants, you might invite someone to read Elder Bednar's statement in "Additional Resources." Class members might enjoy sharing their feelings about their own baptisms and their baptismal covenants. They could also sing a hymn about following the Savior, such as "Come, Follow Me" (Hymns, no. 116).</li>
<li>John the Baptist taught that the Savior would baptize "with the Holy Ghost, and with fire" (Matthew 3:11). The baptism of fire happens when we are confirmed and we receive the gift of the Holy Ghost. Why must we have the gift of the Holy Ghost to progress in God's kingdom? What effect does the baptism of fire and the Holy Ghost have on us? (see Alma 5:14). The video "Baptism of the Holy Ghost" (ChurchofJesusChrist.org) could help with this discussion.</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>Our baptismal covenants.</heading>
<p>Elder David A. Bednar taught: "The baptismal covenant includes three fundamental commitments: (1) to be willing to take upon ourselves the name of Jesus Christ, (2) to always remember Him, and (3) to keep His commandments. The promised blessing for honoring this covenant is «that [we] may always have his Spirit to be with [us]» [Doctrine and Covenants 20:77]. Thus, baptism is the essential preparation to receive the authorized opportunity for the constant companionship of the third member of the Godhead" ("Always Retain a Remission of Your Sins," Ensign or Liahona, May 2016, 60).</p>
<p>For an example of a young boy keeping his baptismal covenants, see the story at the beginning of Sister Carole M. Stephens's message "We Have Great Reason to Rejoice" (Ensign or Liahona, Nov. 2013, 115–17).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Teach basic doctrine.</b>Hyrum Smith taught, "Preach the first principles of the Gospel — preach them over again; you will find that day after day, new ideas and additional light concerning them will be revealed to you. You can enlarge upon them so as to comprehend them clearly. You will then be able to make them more plainly understood by those you teach" (in History, 1838–1856 [Manuscript History of the Church], volume E-1, 1994, josephsmithpapers.org).</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<graphics-caption>Into the Wilderness, by Eva Koleva Timothy</graphics-caption>
<heading>JANUARY 30–FEBRUARY 5</heading>
<heading>Matthew 4; Luke 4–5</heading>
<heading>"THE SPIRIT OF THE LORD IS UPON ME"</heading>
<p>As you study Matthew 4 and Luke 4–5, record your spiritual impressions. This will invite inspiration on how to best meet the needs of your class. You might also consider using<i>Come, Follow Me—For Individuals and Families</i>as well as this outline to find additional ideas.</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>This week's reading includes this statement: "They were astonished at his doctrine: for his word was with power" (Luke 4:32; see also Mark 1:22). Invite class members to share verses from Matthew 4 and Luke 4–5 that helped them feel that doctrinal power for themselves.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>MATTHEW 4:1–11; LUKE 4:1–13</heading>
<heading>Heavenly Father has given us the power and means to resist temptation.</heading>
<ul>
<li>The account of the Savior resisting Satan could help class members recognize ways in which Satan tries to tempt them. Class members could select one of the temptations in Matthew 4:1–11 or Luke 4:1–13 and think of a modern, related temptation (the statement in "Additional Resources" might help). Why is it helpful to know that the Savior faced temptations similar to those we face today? Why was Christ able to resist temptation? For other scriptural examples of people resisting Satan, see Genesis 39:7–20; 2 Nephi 4:16–35; and Moses 1:10–22.</li>
<li>What could help class members resist temptation? You could ask them to review Matthew 4:1–11 or Luke 4:1–13 to learn how the Savior's knowledge of the scriptures helped Him respond to Satan, as He did when He said, "It is written." Give class members time to look under "Temptation" in the Topical Guide entry for scriptures that could fortify and strengthen them when they feel tempted.</li>
</ul>
<heading>LUKE 4:16–32</heading>
<heading>Jesus Christ is the prophesied Messiah.</heading>
<ul>
<li>To help your class members better understand the account in Luke 4:16–32, you might explain that the titles Messiah and Christ both mean "the anointed." As class members read Luke 4:18–21, ask them to think about what it means to say that Jesus is the Christ, the Messiah, or the Anointed One. They may also find it helpful to read "Anointed One" in the Bible Dictionary. How does Jesus declare that He is the Messiah today? Class members could share how they have come to know that Jesus Christ is their Savior.</li>
<li>There may be some helpful lessons to learn by exploring why the people of Nazareth did not accept Jesus as the prophesied Messiah. What reasons, for example, are suggested in Luke 4:22–24? Class members could then contrast these attitudes with those of the widow of Zarephath and Naaman in the Old Testament, people who were not Israelites (see Luke 4:25–27). You could contact some class members in advance and ask them to come prepared to summarize each of these accounts (see 1 Kings 17:8–24; 2 Kings 5:1–17; Luke 4:16–30). What do these accounts teach us about having faith in Jesus Christ? Do we see any messages for us in the Savior's words to the people of Nazareth?</li>
</ul>
<heading>MATTHEW 4:18–22; LUKE 5:1–11</heading>
<heading>Following Christ means forsaking our will and accepting His.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Sometimes the direction the Lord gives us doesn't make sense at first Sometimes the direction the Lord gives us doesn't make sense at first. Class members could search Luke 5:1–11, looking for what the Savior asked of Peter and why Peter might have doubted His instructions. How might this experience have affected Peter's feelings about the Savior and himself? You could invite class members to share experiences in which they demonstrated their faith in divine guidance despite not having a complete understanding. What was the result when they exercised their faith?</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>"Follow me, and I will make you fishers of men" (Matthew 4:19).</graphics-caption>
<ul>
<li>Just as the fishermen "forsook all" to follow Jesus Christ (Luke 5:11), there are things we have to forsake to become His disciples. What do we learn from Matthew 4:18–22 about the attitudes and faith of Peter, Andrew, James, and John? It might be helpful to bring a fishing net to class. Then invite class members to write down things they are willing to forsake or have already forsaken to follow Christ and place them in the net. Consider inviting a few class members to share how their lives have changed as they have chosen to forsake all to follow the Savior.</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>Types of temptation.</heading>
<p>After speaking of the temptations the Savior faced in the wilderness, President David O. McKay identified three categories of temptations:
"(1) A temptation of the appetite or passion;
"(2) A yielding to pride, fashion, or vanity;
"(3) A desire for worldly riches or power and dominion over lands or earthly possessions of men" (Teachings of Presidents of the Church: David O. McKay [2003], 82).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Thank your learners.</b>"Don't become so absorbed with the lesson that you forget to thank learners for their contributions. They need to know that you appreciate their willingness to share their insights and testimonies" (Teaching in the Savior's Way, 33).</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<heading>FEBRUARY 6–12</heading>
<heading>John 2–4</heading>
<heading>"YE MUST BE BORN AGAIN"</heading>
<p>Reading John 2–4 is a good way to start preparing to teach. Record any spiritual impressions you receive, and use this outline to find additional insights and teaching ideas.</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>Write three headings on the board:<i>John 2, John 3,</i>and<i>John 4.</i>Class members could take a few minutes to review these chapters and then write under each heading a verse that helped them understand the doctrine and events in that chapter. Discuss the verses they wrote.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>JOHN 2:1–11</heading>
<heading>Jesus Christ's miracles "manifested forth his glory."</heading>
<ul>
<li>This week's outline in<i>Come, Follow Me—For Individuals and Families</i>suggests reading John 2:1–11 from the perspective of someone who was present when Jesus turned water into wine. Perhaps class members could share insights they gained from doing this. What do we learn about the Savior from these verses? How did this miracle manifest the glory of God? (see verse 11).</li>
</ul>
<heading>JOHN 2:13–22</heading>
<heading>We can defend sacred places and things.</heading>
<ul>
<li>To help class members learn from the account of Jesus driving the money changers out of the temple, you might ask them to think of other things, in addition to temples, that the Lord considers sacred. How can we help preserve the sanctity of these sacred things?</li>
</ul>
<heading>JOHN 3:1–21</heading>
<heading>We must be born again to enter the kingdom of God.</heading>
<ul>
<li>How might we explain to someone what it means to be born again? Consider inviting class members to practice how they would answer this question with the person sitting next to them. As they do, they could discuss questions like these: What do we learn from Jesus's words in John 3:3–7? How do repentance, baptism, and confirmation help us be born again? The statements in "Additional Resources" could add to this discussion.</li>
<li>Some people believe that a person can't really change. Nicodemus, however, is an example of someone who did change as a result of following the gospel of Jesus Christ. To help class members see this, you could invite them to search John 3:1–2; John 7:45–52 and John 19:38–40. What do we learn from these passages about Nicodemus's attitudes and beliefs? How did he change over time? What examples can we share of people who have changed because of the gospel?</li>
</ul>
<heading>JOHN 4:5–34</heading>
<heading>Jesus Christ offers us "living water" and the "meat" of doing God's work.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Our bodies need food and water daily. Jesus referred to these universal needs when He taught both the Samaritan woman and His disciples (see John 4:5–34). To help class members understand what the Savior was teaching, you could put pictures of food and water on the board and invite class members to write under each picture the truths about spiritual food and water that Jesus taught. How does the Savior satisfy our spiritual hunger and spiritual thirst?</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>Jesus Christ offers us living water.</graphics-caption>
<ul>
<li>Reflecting on the progression of the Samaritan woman's testimony of Jesus Christ can help your class members ponder how they have come to know He is the Messiah. As a class, look for the terms the Samaritan woman used to refer to the Savior in John 4:6–30. What do these terms imply about her knowledge of who Jesus was? How have we grown in our testimonies that He is our Savior?</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>What it means to be born again.</heading>
<p>Elder David A. Bednar taught: "Conversion. . . is mighty, not minor — a spiritual rebirth and fundamental change of what we feel and desire, what we think and do, and what we are. Indeed, the essence of the gospel of Jesus Christ entails a fundamental and permanent change in our very nature made possible through our reliance upon the merits, and mercy, and grace of the Holy Messiah' (2 Nephi 2:8). As we choose to follow the Master, we choose to be changed to be spiritually reborn" ("Ye Must Be Born Again," Ensign or Liahona, May 2007, 20).</p>
<p>President Dallin H. Oaks taught: "We were born again when we entered into a covenant relationship with our Savior by being born of water and of the Spirit and by taking upon us the name of Jesus Christ. We can renew that rebirth each Sabbath when we partake of the sacrament. Latter-day Saints affirm that those who have been born again in this way are spiritually begotten sons and daughters of Jesus Christ (see Mosiah 5:7; 15:9–13; 27:25). Nevertheless, in order to realize the intended blessings of this born-again status, we must still keep our covenants and endure to the end" ("Have You Been Saved?," Ensign, May 1998, 56).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>The teacher is no better than the learner.</b>Your role as a teacher is important, but you are not the sole source of inspiration in the class. Help class members learn from the Spirit and share with each other what they learn.</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<graphics-caption>Jesus Preaching Sermon on the Mount, by Gustave Doré</graphics-caption>
<heading>FEBRUARY 13–19</heading>
<heading>Matthew 5; Luke 6</heading>
<heading>"BLESSED ARE YE"</heading>
<p>Record your spiritual impressions as you study Matthew 5 and Luke 6. Revelation will come as you seek to meet the needs of your class.</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>President Joseph Fielding Smith said that the Sermon on the Mount is "the greatest [sermon] that was ever preached, so far as we know" (Teachings of Presidents of the Church: Joseph Fielding Smith [2013], 234). Invite class members to share their feelings about why this is true.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>MATTHEW 5:1–12</heading>
<heading>Lasting happiness comes from living the way Jesus Christ taught.</heading>
<ul>
<li>In the Sermon on the Mount, the Savior invited His disciples to rethink what it means to live a blessed life — a life of lasting happiness. To begin a discussion about lasting happiness, you could ask class members to share what makes them happy. According to Matthew 5:1–12, what did Jesus say makes a person "blessed," or eternally happy? How are Jesus's teachings different from other ways people try to find happiness?</li>
<li>Consider listing on the board some attributes or qualities from verses 3–12, like "pure in heart" or "peacemakers." Then invite class members to suggest the opposite of each term. What do we learn about these qualities by considering their opposites? Ask class members to ponder what they could change in order to be the type of person described in these verses. What does 3 Nephi 12:3, 6 add to our understanding of Matthew 5:3, 6?</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>The Savior taught how to live happily and become like our Father in Heaven.</graphics-caption>
<heading>MATTHEW 5:14–16</heading>
<heading>The Savior's disciples are to be the light of the world.</heading>
<ul>
<li>What does it mean to be "the light of the world"? (verse 14). What does it mean to hide our light "under a bushel" (verse 15), and why might we be tempted to do this? The statement by President Bonnie H. Cordon in "Additional Resources" and 3 Nephi 18:24 might help class members be more intentional about being a light to others. They could also talk about people who have been a light to them and led them toward Jesus Christ. How can we emulate these people?</li>
</ul>
<heading>MATTHEW 5:17–48</heading>
<heading>Jesus Christ taught a higher law that can lead us toward perfection.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Some of the situations described in Matthew 5 were specific to the Savior's day, but the principles He taught are universal. To help class members see the applications to their lives, invite them to select one of the following passages and think of a modern-day example that illustrates what the Savior was teaching: verses 21–24; 27–30; 33–37; 38–39; 40–42; and 43–44. They could do this individually or in small groups and share their examples with the class.</li>
<li>How can you help class members see that the Savior's command to be "perfect" (Matthew 5:48) means, as President Russell M. Nelson explained, to be "complete" or "finished"? ("Perfection Pending," Ensign, Nov. 1995, 86–88). You could cut a picture of Jesus into a puzzle, and invite class members to write on the back of each piece a teaching from Matthew 5 that they feel inspired to apply to their life. Let them work together to complete the puzzle. How does Jesus Christ's Atonement help us become "complete" or "finished"? (see Bible Dictionary, "Grace"). What do President Joy D. Jones's words in "Additional Resources" add to our understanding of this process?</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>Being a light.</heading>
<p>President Bonnie H. Cordon taught: "The Lord's invitation to let our light so shine is not just about randomly waving a beam of light and making the world generally brighter. It is about focusing our light so others may see the way to Christ. It is gathering Israel<i>on this side of the veil</i>— helping others see the next step forward in making and keeping sacred covenants with God" ("That They May See," Ensign or Liahona, May 2020, 79).</p>
<heading>Seeking perfection.</heading>
<p>President Joy D. Jones explained: "The Lord loves effort, and effort brings rewards. We keep practicing. We are always progressing as long as we are striving to follow the Lord. He doesn't expect perfection today. We keep climbing our personal Mount Sinai. As in times past, our journey does indeed take effort, hard work, and study, but our commitment to progress brings eternal rewards. . . .
"Let us boldly declare our devotion to our Heavenly Father and our Savior, «with unshaken faith in him, relying wholly upon the merits of him who is mighty to save» [2 Nephi 31:19]. Let us joyfully continue this journey toward our highest spiritual potential" ("An Especially Noble Calling," Ensign or Liahona, May 2020, 16–17).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Increase the participation of class members.</b>Many activities can be done as a class, in small groups, in pairs, or as a panel discussion. Use a variety of methods to allow people to participate who might otherwise have a chance. (Se Teaching in the Savior's Way, 33.)</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<graphics-caption>Jesus Teaching the People by the Seashore, by James Tissot</graphics-caption>
<heading>FEBRUARY 20–26</heading>
<heading>Matthew 6–7</heading>
<heading>"HE TAUGHT THEM AS ONE HAVING AUTHORITY"</heading>
<p>As you prepare to teach, begin by preparing yourself. Study Matthew 6–7, and record your spiritual impressions. This will help you receive revelation on how to best meet the needs of your class. Then search this outline for teaching ideas.</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>Invite class members to share which of the passages in the Sermon on the Mount they feel are most needed today. Encourage class members to add to each other's insights.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>MATTHEW 6–7</heading>
<heading>If we hear and act on the Lord's teachings, our lives will be built on a firm foundation.</heading>
<ul>
<li>What specific teachings from Matthew 6–7 will be most beneficial to those you teach? Consider writing on the board several references from Matthew 6–7 that contain these teachings. Class members could select one of the references to study silently and then write on the board any spiritual truths they learn. How have these teachings influenced our lives?</li>
<li>The Savior concluded His sermon with a parable that might help your class better understand the importance of living by the Savior's teachings (see Matthew 7:24–27; see also Helaman 5:12). To visualize this parable, class members could work together to build a strong foundation using blocks, cups, or other materials and then test the strength of their foundations. Perhaps they could also label their building materials with things they can do to apply the Savior's teachings. How could doing these things help us withstand the storms of life?</li>
</ul>
<heading>MATTHEW 6:5–13</heading>
<heading>The Savior taught us how to pray.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Studying the Lord's Prayer might help class members identify how they can improve their own prayers by following the Lord's example. You could invite them to write on the board phrases from Matthew 6:9–13 (or Luke 11:1–4) that stand out to them. As we ponder the Savior's words, what do we learn about prayer? It may be instructive for class members to paraphrase some of the Savior's phrases as things they might say in their own prayers. For instance, "Give us this day our daily bread" could be paraphrased as "Please help me in my efforts to provide for my family."</li>
<li>After reading Matthew 6:5–13 as a class, you could discuss questions such as these: How has prayer strengthened your relationship with Heavenly Father? How has prayer helped you come to know God's will?</li>
</ul>
<heading>MATTHEW 7:7–11</heading>
<heading>Heavenly Father answers prayers.</heading>
<ul>
<li>To help class members strengthen their faith that God will hear and answer their prayers, you could write ask, seek, and knock on the board. Then class members could search the scriptures for examples of people who "asked," "sought," and "knocked" (for examples, see 1 Nephi 11:1; Ether 2:18–3:6; Joseph Smith–History 1:11–17). What do we learn from these examples about receiving answers to our prayers?</li>
<li>Some important context for Matthew 7:7–11 can be found in the Joseph Smith Translation of Matthew 7:12–17 (in the Bible appendix). In these verses, Jesus's disciples anticipated some reasons people might give for not seeking truth from Heavenly Father. You might ask class members to imagine they have a friend who is reluctant to seek guidance or blessings from the Lord. What might class members say to encourage this friend? How might they use the Savior's words in Matthew 7:7–11?</li>
</ul>
<heading>MATTHEW 7:15–20</heading>
<heading>We can identify true and false prophets by their fruits.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Members of your class have likely come across false philosophies and other deceptions of the adversary, whether on the internet or from other sources. They may have also heard others criticize the Lord's servants. How can you help them understand how to discern false prophets and teachings from true ones? You could display several pieces of fruit and ask what we can assume about the trees they came from. How does this exercise help us understand Matthew 7:15–20? You could also read together some recent messages from the living prophets. What "fruits" or outcomes does following their counsel produce?</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>We can know true prophets by their fruits.</graphics-caption>
<ul>
<li>Matthew 7:15–20 could help build class members' faith in the divine mission of the Prophet Joseph Smith. What are the fruits of the work Joseph Smith accomplished? For some ideas, see Elder Neil L. Andersen's message "Joseph Smith" (Ensign or Liahona, Nov. 2014, 28–31). How could we use the Savior's analogy in Matthew 7:15–20 to bear testimony to our friends and family about the Prophet Joseph?</li>
</ul>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Don't be afraid of silence.</b>"Good questions take time to answer. They require pondering, searching, and inspiration. The time you spend waiting for answers to a question can be a sacred time of pondering. Avoid the temptation to end this time too soon by answering your own question or moving on to something else" (Teaching in the Savior's Way, 31).</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<heading>FEBRUARY 27–MARCH 5</heading>
<heading>Matthew 8; Mark 2–4; Luke 7</heading>
<heading>"THY FAITH HATH SAVED THEE"</heading>
<p>Your preparation to teach begins as you prayerfully study Matthew 8; Mark 2–4; and Luke 7.<i>Come, Follow Me—For Individuals and Families</i>can enhance your study and prompt teaching ideas in addition to those presented here.</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>Members of your class may have found powerful insights during their personal study of the miracles in these chapters (see the list of the Savior's healings in this week's outline in Come, Follow Me—For Individuals and Families). Consider inviting class members to share their insights with a partner or with the whole class.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>MATTHEW 8; MARK 2; LUKE 7</heading>
<heading>Miracles occur according to God's will and our faith in Jesus Christ.</heading>
<ul>
<li>How can you use the accounts of the Savior's miracles to help class members increase their faith in Him? You might ask them to list on the board several of the miraculous healings from Matthew 8; Mark 2; and Luke 7. Class members could discuss how the people who were healed showed their faith in Christ. What do these accounts teach about faith and miracles? Class members could share additional truths about faith and miracles from Mormon 9:15–21; Ether 12:12–16; Moroni 7:27–37; and Doctrine and Covenants 35:8 (see also Bible Dictionary, "Miracles"). When have we seen miracles as we have exercised faith in Jesus Christ?</li>
<li>The account of the miracle in Mark 2:1–12 teaches, among other things, the value of working together in unity to assist the Savior in ministering to those in spiritual or physical need. Consider inviting class members to review the account from the scriptures and share additional insights from Elder Chi Hong (Sam) Wong's message "Rescue in Unity" (Ensign or Liahona, Nov. 2014, 14–16; see also "Additional Resources"). What can we learn from Mark 2:1–12 about the value of working in unity to serve those in need? (see also Mark 3:24–25).</li>
</ul>
<heading>MARK 4:35–41</heading>
<heading>Jesus Christ has power to bring peace in the midst of life's storms.</heading>
<ul>
<li>You may be aware of some of the challenges your class members are facing. Because we all have trials at some time in our lives, reviewing the account in Mark 4:35–41 can build class members' faith that the Savior can bring them peace. Give each person a piece of paper, and ask them to write on one side a trial they have experienced. On the other side, ask them to write something from Mark 4:35–41 that inspires them to turn to the Savior during their trials. Encourage class members to share what they wrote, if they feel comfortable doing so.</li>
<li>The hymn "Master, the Tempest Is Raging" (Hymns, no. 105) is based on the story in Mark 4:35–41. Perhaps class members could find lyrics in the hymn that relate to phrases in the scriptures. You could also show a picture depicting the scene (see Gospel Art Book, no. 40) and discuss what moment the artist is depicting. What are other ways you could help class members understand the meaning and power of this miracle?</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>From Fear to Faith, by Howard Lyon</graphics-caption>
<heading>LUKE 7:36–50</heading>
<heading>As we are forgiven of our sins, our love for the Savior deepens.</heading>
<ul>
<li>What can we learn from the woman's example and the Savior's teachings in Luke 7:36–50 as we seek forgiveness for our own sins? How does repentance help us draw closer to Jesus Christ? How does this account influence the way we view those who have sinned?</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>"When Jesus saw their faith."</heading>
<p>Elder Chi Hong (Sam) Wong shared the following insight about the account in Mark 2:1–12:
"May I share with you one more hidden treasure found in this scripture account. It is in verse 5: «When Jesus saw<i>their</i>faith» (emphasis added). I had not noticed this in the past —<i>their</i>faith. . . .
"Who were those people that Jesus mentioned? They could well include the four who carried the man with palsy, the man himself, the people who had prayed for him, and all those who were there listening to the preaching of Jesus and cheering quietly in their hearts for the soon-to-come miracle. They could also include a spouse, a parent, a son or a daughter, a missionary, a quorum president, a Relief Society president, a bishop, and a faraway friend. We can all help one another. We should always be anxiously engaged in seeking to rescue those in need" ("Rescue in Unity," Ensign or Liahona, Nov. 2014, 16).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Bear testimony often.</b>Your simple, sincere witness of spiritual truths can have a powerful influence on those you teach. Your witness does not need to be eloquent or lengthy. It may, for example, be a simple testimony of the miracle of having the gospel in your life.</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<heading>MARCH 6–12</heading>
<heading>Matthew 9–10; Mark 5; Luke 9</heading>
<heading>"THESE TWELVE JESUS SENT FORTH"</heading>
<p>As you read Matthew 9–10; Mark 5; and Luke 9, seek inspiration from the Holy Ghost about the needs of those you teach. Recording your spiritual impressions can help you prepare for an experience that will bless you and the members of your class.</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>You could ask class members to each write on a slip of paper a truth they learned from the scriptures this week, including the scripture verses. After collecting the papers, select several to read to the class. How can we apply these truths to our lives?</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>MATTHEW 9</heading>
<heading>Christ has power to heal us physically and spiritually.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Many of the Savior's miraculous healings also teach spiritual truths. To help class members understand this, you could divide the class into four groups and assign each group one of the following passages: Matthew 9:2–8; Matthew 9:18–19, 23–26; Matthew 9:20–22; and Matthew 9:27–31. Ask each group to study the miracle described in their passage and then summarize it for the class. What spiritual truths can we learn from these miracles?</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>Trust in the Lord, by Liz Lemon Swindle</graphics-caption>
<heading>MATTHEW 10</heading>
<heading>The Lord gives His servants power to do His work.</heading>
<ul>
<li>The Savior's commission to His Apostles can help us in our individual responsibilities. Class members may have had insights into this topic through their personal study; for example, there is an activity on this topic in<i>Come, Follow Me—For Individuals and Families.</i>Invite them to share what they learned or work in small groups to complete the activity in class. Invite class members to share experiences when they felt the Savior's power as they fulfilled their callings.</li>
<li>How can studying the commission Christ gave to His Apostles in Matthew 10 help your class members understand the role of modern prophets and apostles? It might be helpful to compare the Savior's commission to the Twelve to the commission given to the first Quorum of the Twelve Apostles in this dispensation, found in "Additional Resources." Perhaps class members could share how they have been influenced by the ministry of the living Apostles. Bear your testimony of the divine calling of the living prophets and apostles, and invite class members to bear theirs.</li>
</ul>
<heading>MATTHEW 10:17–20</heading>
<heading>When we are in the Lord's service, He will inspire us with what to say.</heading>
<ul>
<li>People sometimes feel nervous when teaching or talking with others about the gospel. But the Lord promised the disciples that He would help them know what to say. What do we need to do to receive the Lord's promised help for ourselves? Invite class members to read Matthew 10:19–20; Doctrine and Covenants 84:85; and Doctrine and Covenants 100:5–8 to find answers to this question. When has the Holy Ghost helped you know what to say? You might share your experiences and invite class members to share their own.</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>A commission to latter-day Apostles.</heading>
<p>When some of the first members of the Quorum of the Twelve Apostles in this dispensation were called, Oliver Cowdery gave them a commission similar to the one Jesus Christ gave in Matthew 10. He said:
"You will have to combat all the prejudices of all nations. . . . I, therefore, warn you to cultivate great humility, for I know the pride of the human heart.Beware, lest the flatterers of the world lift you up. Beware lest your affections are captivated by worldly objects. Let your ministry be first. . . . [It] is necessary that you receive a testimony from Heaven for yourselves, so that you can bear testimony to the truth. . . . 
"'. . . You are to bear this message to those who consider themselves wise. And such may persecute you; they may seek your life. The adversary has always sought the life of the servants of God. You are, therefore, to be prepared at all times to make a sacrifice of your lives, should God require them in the advancement and building up of His cause. . . . 
"He then took them separately by the hand and said, «Do you with full purpose of heart take part in this ministry, to proclaim the gospel with all diligence with these your brethren, according to the tenor and intent of the charge you have received?» Each of which answered in the affirmative" (in "Minutes and Blessings, 21 February 1835," Minute Book 1, 159–161, 164, josephsmithpapers.org; spelling and punctuation modernized). </p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Testify of blessings.</b>When you extend invitations to act, testify to your learners that they will receive the blessings God has promised when they act with faith on His teachings. Blessings shouldn't be our primary motivation for obedience, but Heavenly Father desires to bless all His children. (See Teaching in the Savior's Way, 35.)</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<graphics-caption>Be Not Afraid, by Michael Malm</graphics-caption>
<heading>MARCH 13–19</heading>
<heading>Matthew 11–12; Luke 11</heading>
<heading>"I WILL GIVE YOU REST"</heading>
<p>Read Matthew 11–12 and Luke 11 during the week before you teach. This will give you time to ponder and to receive revelation about what to focus on in class.</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>Applying the principles we find in the scriptures to our lives is an important way to experience the power of God's word. Encourage class members to share what they found in their scripture study this week that they can apply to their lives. Sharing an example of how you applied the scriptures could help inspire class members to share their own examples.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>MATTHEW 11:28–30</heading>
<heading>Jesus Christ will give us rest as we rely on Him.</heading>
<ul>
<li>In Matthew 11:28–30, the Savior taught that He will help us carry our heavy burdens if we accept His invitation "Take my yoke upon you" (verse 29). To help class members better understand this promise, you could show a picture of a yoke (see this week's outline in Come, Follow Me—For Individuals and Families) and share facts like these: yokes are designed to help animals carry heavy loads or to get work done, and yokes are often custom fitted to the animal. What do these details add to our understanding of Matthew 11:28–30? What invitations do we find in these verses? What blessings are we promised? You might also share the promise by President Russell M. Nelson found in "Additional Resources."</li>
<li>We all have burdens that can be made lighter through Jesus Christ's power. To encourage discussion about this, you could invite class members to read and discuss Matthew 11:28–30 with someone else in the class. They could include questions like these in their discussion: What are some examples of burdens a person might carry? What do we need to do to come unto Christ? What does it mean to take the Savior's yoke upon ourselves? How have you felt the Savior lighten your burdens as you have turned to Him? Class members may find additional insights in Elder David A. Bednar's message "Bear Up Their Burdens with Ease" (Ensign or Liahona, May 2014, 87–90).</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>The Disciples Eat Wheat on the Sabbath, by James Tissot</graphics-caption>
<heading>MATTHEW 12:1–13</heading>
<heading>The Sabbath is a day to do good.</heading>
<ul>
<li>In their zeal to keep the Sabbath day holy, the Pharisees had implemented strict rules and man-made traditions, which eventually clouded their understanding of the true purpose of the Sabbath. To begin a discussion about why the Lord gave us the Sabbath day, you might invite class members to review Matthew 12:1–13 and Joseph Smith Translation, Mark 2:26–27 (in the Bible appendix). What do these accounts teach about the purpose of the Sabbath? What additional insights about the Sabbath do we gain from Exodus 31:16–17; Isaiah 58:13–14; and Doctrine and Covenants 59:9–13? How has our relationship with the Savior changed as we have tried to keep His day holy?</li>
<li>While the Pharisees emphasized numerous detailed rules regarding the Sabbath, the Savior taught a simple principle: "It is lawful to do well on the sabbath" (Matthew 12:12). What other principles help us keep the Sabbath day holy? (see the statement by President Russell M. Nelson in "Additional Resources"). Why are principles more effective than lists of rules as we strive to develop spiritual self-reliance?</li>
<li>President Russell M. Nelson's message "The Sabbath Is a Delight" (Ensign or Liahona, May 2015, 129–32) and the videos with Elder Jeffrey R. Holland's counsel in "Additional Resources" might add to a discussion about the Sabbath day.</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>Yoked with Jesus Christ.</heading>
<p>President Russell M. Nelson taught: "You come unto Christ to be yoked with Him and withHis power, so that you're not pulling life's load alone. You're pulling life's load yoked with the Savior and Redeemer of the world, and suddenly your problems, no matter how serious they are, become lighter" ("The Mission and Ministry of the Savior: A Discussion with Elder Russell M. Nelson," Ensign, June 2005, 18).</p>
<heading>"What<i>sign</i>do I want to give to God?"</heading>
<p>President Russell M. Nelson taught: "When I had to make a decision whether or not an activity was appropriate for the Sabbath, I simply asked myself, «What<i>sign</i>do I want to give to God?» That question made my choices about the Sabbath day crystal clear" ("The Sabbath Is a Delight," Ensign or Liahona, May 2015, 130).</p>
<heading>The blessings of Sabbath day observance.</heading>
<p>In a series of three videos, Elder Jeffrey R. Holland taught about the blessings of observing the Sabbath day: "Upon My Holy Day — Getting Closer to God," "Upon My Holy Day — Honoring the Sabbath," and "Upon My Holy Day — Rest and Renewal" (Churchof Jesus Christ.org).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Encourage sharing.</b>"Each individual in your class is a rich source of testimony, insights, and experiences with living the gospel. Invite them to share with and lift each other" (Teaching in the Savior's Way, 5).</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<heading>MARCH 20–26</heading>
<heading>Matthew 13; Luke 8; 13</heading>
<heading>"WHO HATH EARS TO HEAR, LET HIM HEAR"</heading>
<p>As you read, think of questions members of your class may have as they try to understand the messages of the parables. What could be difficult to understand? How can your study prepare you to answer their questions?</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>Review with the class "Ideas to Improve Your Personal Scripture Study" in<i>Come, Follow Me—For Individuals and Families.</i>Invite class members to share methods they used to study Matthew 13 and Luke 8; 13.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>MATTHEW 13:1–23</heading>
<heading>Our hearts must be prepared to receive the word of God.</heading>
<ul>
<li>How can you use the parable of the sower to inspire your class members to prepare their hearts to receive the word of God? You could write<i>Disciples</i>and<i>Others</i>on the board. Invite class members to read Matthew 13:10–17 and look for how the Savior described the differences between His disciples and others who heard His parables. Then ask class members to search verses 18–23, looking for what might cause our ears to become "dull of hearing" or our eyes to be closed to spiritual things. What direction are we receiving in our day from God and His servants? How can we cultivate "good ground" to receive their direction? (verse 23).</li>
<li>You might invite a few class members to each come prepared to teach a section from President Dallin H. Oaks's message "The Parable of the Sower" (Ensign or Liahona, May 2015, 32–35). What does his message add to our understanding of the parable?</li>
</ul>
<heading>MATTHEW 13:24–35, 44–53</heading>
<heading>Jesus's parables help us understand the growth, destiny, and value of His Church.</heading>
<ul>
<li>How can you help class members understand the truths about the Church that are taught in Jesus's parables in Matthew 13? You could list a few of the parables on the board (see this week's outline in Come, Follow Me—For Individuals and Families and Teachings of Presidents of the Church: Joseph Smith [2007], 293–303). Class members could study one or more parables individually or in small groups and share what they learn about the growth and destiny of Christ's Church.</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>The kingdom of heaven is like a fisherman's net.</graphics-caption>
<ul>
<li>What do we learn about the value of belonging to the Church from the parables of the treasure in the field and the pearl of great price, found in Matthew 13:44–46? Some members of your class (or people they know) may have made sacrifices — big or small — to become members of the Church. Invite class members to share sacrifices they have made or seen others make in order to belong to the Church. What blessings have come as a result? Invite class members to ponder what they feel prompted to sacrifice for the Savior.</li>
</ul>
<heading>MATTHEW 13:24–30, 36–43</heading>
<heading>At the end of the world, the Lord will gather the righteous and destroy the wicked.</heading>
<ul>
<li>How can you help your class draw lessons from the parable of the wheat and the tares that will help them remain faithful Latter-day Saints? Start by inviting a class member to summarize the parable and its interpretation. What are some lessons in this parable for our day? Why is it important to know that the Lord allows His Saints to "grow together" (Matthew 13:30) with the wicked until the time of the harvest? How can we keep our faith in Jesus Christ strong when wickedness is all around us? How can Christ help us? Doctrine and Covenants 86:1–7 and Elder L. Tom Perry's statement in "Additional Resources" can give additional insights into the latter-day application of this parable.</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>We should nourish the good.</heading>
<p>Elder L. Tom Perry taught: "That old enemy of all mankind has found as many devices as he can think of to scatter tares far and wide. He has found ways to have them penetrate even the sanctity of our own homes. The wicked and worldly ways have become so widespread there seems to be no real way of weeding them out. They come by wire and through the air into the very devices we have developed to educate and entertain us. The wheat and the tares have grown close together. A steward managing the field must, with all his or her power, nourish that which is good and make it so strong and beautiful the tares will have no appeal either to the eye or the ear" ("Finding Lasting Peace and Building Eternal Families," Ensign or Liahona, Nov. 2014, 44).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Center your teaching on doctrine.</b>Make sure your class discussions focus on the foundational doctrine in the scriptures. You can do this by asking students to read scriptures in advance, centering your class discussions on the scriptures, and asking class members to share their testimonies of true doctrine. (See Teaching in the Savior's Way, 20–21.)</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<heading>MARCH 27–APRIL 2</heading>
<heading>Matthew 14; Mark 6; John 5–6</heading>
<heading>"BE NOT AFRAID"</heading>
<p>As you prepare to teach from Matthew 14; Mark 6; and John 5–6, look for messages that are relevant to your class. As you do, consider how to engage class members in a meaningful experience with the scriptures.</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>One way to begin a discussion is to invite a few class members to each select a chapter from the reading and share a message from that chapter that was meaningful to them. As they share, other class members could ask questions or add insights.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>JOHN 5:16–47</heading>
<heading>Jesus Christ is the Beloved Son of Heavenly Father.</heading>
<ul>
<li>In John 5, Jesus provided several insights about Himself, His Father, and His relationship to the Father. To help class members discover these insights, try dividing them into groups and giving them a few minutes to list as many truths as they can find in verses 16–47 about the character of God and Jesus Christ and about Their relationship. Invite the groups to take turns reading truths from their lists. How do these truths help us better understand our Heavenly Father and His Son? How can we follow Jesus Christ's example of obedience to the Father?</li>
<li>An activity in this week's outline in<i>Come, Follow Me—For Individuals and Families</i>suggests noting every time Jesus used the word<i>Father</i>in John 5:16–47. Invite a few class members to share what they learned as they completed the activity. Ask them to share insights they gained about Heavenly Father and His Beloved Son.</li>
</ul>
<heading>MATTHEW 14:15–21; MARK 6:33–44; JOHN 6:5–14</heading>
<heading>The Savior can magnify our humble offerings to accomplish His purposes.</heading>
<ul>
<li>What could help class members find personal meaning in the miracle of Jesus feeding the five thousand? You might ask how reading about the miracle increases their faith in the Savior's ability to bless them personally. They could talk about a time when they felt that the Savior magnified or multiplied their efforts to help them accomplish something that seemed impossible. Also, before class, you could ask class members to bring to class a picture or object that represents their experience.</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>Jesus miraculously fed five thousand people with five loaves and two fishes.</graphics-caption>
<ul>
<li>The video "The Feeding of the 5,000 (ChurchofJesusChrist.org) may help class members ponder the miracle described in these passages. What details in this account increase our faith in the Savior? In what ways can the Savior feed us spiritually? When have we been fed and sustained by Jesus Christ?</li>
</ul>
<heading>MATTHEW 14:22–33</heading>
<heading>Jesus Christ invites us to set aside our fears and doubts so that we can more fully come unto Him.</heading>
<ul>
<li>The account in Matthew 14:22–33 can help class members increase their faith in the Savior and their desire to follow Him. Invite class members to read this account, paying special attention to the words spoken by Christ, Peter, and the other Apostles. How might Jesus's words have helped Peter have faith to leave the boat and walk on the water? How do Jesus's admonitions to "be of good cheer" and "be not afraid" (verse 27) apply to us today? What can we learn from Peter about what it means to be a disciple of Jesus Christ and to trust Him? You might encourage class members to think about and share experiences in which they, like Peter, took action to follow the Savior, even when the outcome was uncertain. Ask them to share what they learned from their experiences. How has Jesus Christ come to our rescue in our moments of fear or doubt?</li>
</ul>
<heading>JOHN 6:22–71</heading>
<heading>As disciples of Christ, we must be willing to believe and accept the truth, even when it is hard to do.</heading>
<ul>
<li>The events in John 6 can provide a helpful perspective when people have questions about the doctrine, history, or policies of Christ's Church. To help your class members understand these events, you could write questions like the following on the board for them to answer:<i>What were the people expecting?</i>(see verse 26).<i>What did Christ offer them instead?</i>(see verse 51).<i>What did the people misunderstand?</i>(see verses 41–42, 52). You could also ask questions like these to help class members apply this account to their lives: What are some ways we can choose to walk with Christ even when we have questions or doubts? (see verse 66). What are some doctrines, ordinances, or other "words of eternal life" that can be found only in Christ's restored Church? (see verses 67–69). For insights from a modern Apostle, see President M. Russell Ballard's message "To Whom Shall We Go?," (Ensign or Liahona, Nov. 2016, 90–92).</li>
</ul>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Listen.</b>"Listening is an act of love. . . . Ask Heavenly Father to help you understand what your class members say. As you pay careful attention to their spoken and unspoken messages, you will come to better understand their needs, their concerns, and their desires" (Teaching in the Savior's Way, 34).</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<heading>APRIL 3–9</heading>
<heading>Easter</heading>
<heading>"O GRAVE, WHERE IS THY VICTORY?"</heading>
<p>As you prepare to teach this week, consider how your class's discussion on Easter Sunday can build faith in Jesus Christ and His Atonement.</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>Ask class members how they would respond to questions like "What is the Atonement of Jesus Christ?" and "How can I receive the blessings of Christ's Atonement?" Invite them to share any scriptures they read this week that help answer these questions.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>Jesus Christ delivers us from sin and death, strengthens us in our weaknesses, and comforts us in our trials.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Do your class members understand that Jesus comforts us in our trials and strengthens us in our weaknesses, as well as delivering us from sin and death? One way to help them discover these principles could be to write these words on the board:<i>Sin, Death, Trials, Weaknesses.</i>Each class member could read one of the scriptures listed in "Additional Resources" and ponder how the Savior helps us overcome or endure these things. Class members could then write what they learn from these scriptures under each heading and share their testimony of the Savior and His Atonement.</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>Crucifixion, by Louise Parker</graphics-caption>
<ul>
<li>Perhaps a simple object lesson could help illustrate the difference between being cleansed from sin and being perfected: You could write on the board the first few lines from Moroni 10:32, but include spelling or grammatical errors. Then invite a class member to erase (but not correct) the errors. Did this solve the problem? What lessons do we learn from this scripture and this object lesson about the effect the Savior's Atonement can have on us? This statement from President Dieter F. Uchtdorf might also help: "If salvation means only erasing our mistakes and sins, then salvation — as wonderful as it is — does not fulfill the Father's aspirations for us. His aim is much higher: He wants His sons and daughters to become like Him" ("The Gift of Grace," Ensign or Liahona, May 2015, 108).</li>
<li>Stories and analogies can help us better understand Christ's Atonement. You may want to share a story or analogy from one of the general conference messages in "Additional Resources." Or you could watch together "Handel's Messiah: Debtor's Prison" (video), ChurchofJesusChrist.org, and discuss how Jesus Christ's Atonement frees us from our prisons. Class members could then share any thoughts or feelings they have about the Savior and His Atonement for us.</li>
</ul>
<heading>MATTHEW 28:1–10; LUKE 24:13–35; JOHN 20:1–29; 1 CORINTHIANS 15:3–8, 55–58</heading>
<heading>Witnesses in the New Testament bore testimony that Jesus Christ conquered death.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Consider reviewing the scriptural account of the first Easter the Resurrection of Jesus Christ. You could invite a class member to retell the story in his or her own words (see John 20:1–17). You could also show a Bible video, such as "He Is Risen" (ChurchofJesusChrist.org).</li>
<li>Perhaps your class would gain deeper understanding of the importance of the witnesses of Jesus Christ's Resurrection if they imagine they are lawyers or news reporters investigating the claim that Christ was resurrected. Invite them to find people in the scriptures who could serve as witnesses (see Matthew 28:1–10; Luke 24:13–35; John 20:19–29; 1 Corinthians 15:3–8, 55–58). They could even write a brief summary of what these people might say when testifying in court or when being interviewed for a news report.</li>
<li>One way to deepen our appreciation for the Savior's Resurrection is to think about how we would explain our beliefs to others. How would class members share their testimonies of Jesus Christ in the following situations: a family member has been diagnosed with a serious illness; a friend has lost a loved one; a neighbor asks why you celebrate Easter. Encourage them to refer to the scriptures (such as those in "Additional Resources") as they plan their responses. Invite a few class members to share their thoughts.</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>Scriptures about the Savior's Atonement and Resurrection.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Isaiah 25:8; 53:3–6</li>
<li>John 20:11–17</li>
<li>Romans 8:31–39</li>
<li>2 Nephi 9:5–12</li>
<li>Mosiah 3:5–10</li>
<li>Alma 7:10–14; 11:42–44</li>
<li>3 Nephi 11:8–17; 27:13–20</li>
<li>Moroni 7:41</li>
<li>Doctrine and Covenants 19:15–19</li>
</ul>
<heading>Messages about the Savior's Atonement and Resurrection.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Dale G. Renlund, "Consider the Goodness and Greatness of God," Ensign or Liahona, May 2020, 41–44</li>
<li>Gerrit W. Gong, "Good Shepherd, Lamb of God," Ensign or Liahona, May 2019, 97–100</li>
<li>Sharon Eubank, "Christ: The Light That Shines in Darkness," Ensign or Liahona, May 2019, 73–76</li>
<li>Cristina B. Franco, "The Healing Power of Jesus Christ," Ensign or Liahona, Nov. 2020, 60–62</li>
</ul>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Be an instrument of the Spirit.</b>"Your purpose as a teacher is not to make an impressive presentation but rather to help others receive the influence of the Holy Ghost, who is the true teacher" (Teaching in the Savior's Way, 10).</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<graphics-caption>The Transfiguration, by Carl Heinrich Bloch</graphics-caption>
<heading>APRIL 10–16</heading>
<heading>Matthew 15–17; Mark 7–9</heading>
<heading>"THOU ART THE CHRIST"</heading>
<p>One of your main objectives as a teacher is to help others build their faith in Jesus Christ. Keep this in mind as you study the scriptures this week. What do you find that could help class members believe in Him more deeply?</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>One way you can encourage class members to study the scriptures personally and with their families is to invite them to share each week how their study of the scriptures helped them receive revelation and blessed their lives. For example, how did their study of these chapters influence the choices they made this week?</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>MATTHEW 16:13–17</heading>
<heading>A testimony of Jesus Christ comes by revelation.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Have any of your class members had to explain to someone how they know the gospel is true? In Matthew 16:13–17, what did the Savior teach about how we receive a testimony? You could share how Alma gained his testimony (see Alma 5:45–46) or what the Lord taught Oliver Cowdery about revelation (see Doctrine and Covenants 6:14–15, 22–23; 8:2–3). What do you think Peter or Alma or Oliver Cowdery might have said if someone asked them how they know the gospel is true?</li>
<li>There may be people in your class who are praying for personal revelation but do not know how to recognize it when it comes. At HearHim.ChurchofJesusChrist.org, you can find videos in which Church leaders share how they recognize the Lord's voice. You might watch one or more of these videos with the class and talk about what the videos teach about receiving revelation. What other teachings or scriptures can your class think of that would help someone recognize personal revelation? (For example, see 1 Kings 19:11–12; Galatians 5:22–23; Enos 1:1–8; Doctrine and Covenants 6:22–24; 8:2–3; 9:7–9.)</li>
</ul>
<heading>MATTHEW 16:13–19; 17:1–9</heading>
<heading>Priesthood keys are essential for our salvation.</heading>
<ul>
<li>To start a discussion about priesthood keys, you could write references like these on the board: Matthew 16:19; Doctrine and Covenants 107:18–20; 128:8–11; 132:18–19, 59; Joseph Smith–History 1:72; and "Keys of the Priesthood" in Guide to the Scriptures (scriptures.ChurchofJesusChrist.org). Then invite class members to read one or more of the passages and share something they learn from them about priesthood keys. Why do we need priesthood keys?</li>
<li>To help class members strengthen their testimonies of the restoration of priesthood keys in the latter days, you could ask half of the class to study Matthew 17:1–9 and the other half to study Doctrine and Covenants 110. They could then share with each other what they learned and note similarities between the two accounts. The video "Priesthood Keys: The Restoration of Priesthood Keys" (ChurchofJesusChrist.org) could also be helpful.</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>Priesthood keys are the authority to direct the use of the priesthood.</graphics-caption>
<heading>MARK 9:14–30</heading>
<heading>When seeking greater faith, we start with the faith we have.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Elder Jeffrey R. Holland used the account of a father seeking healing for his son to teach how we should approach the Lord when we feel that our faith is insufficient (see "Lord, I Believe," Ensign or Liahona, May 2013, 93–95). After reading Mark 9:14–30 as a class, you could discuss together Elder Holland's three observations (see "Additional Resources").</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>Three observations to help us gain more faith.</heading>
<p>After retelling the account found in Mark 9:14–29, Elder Jeffrey R. Holland taught:
"Observation number one regarding this account is that when facing the challenge of faith, the father asserts his strength first and only then acknowledges his limitation. His initial declaration is affirmative and without hesitation: «Lord, I believe.» I would say to all who wish for more faith, remember this man! In moments of fear or doubt or troubling times, hold the ground you have already won, even if that ground is limited. . . .
"The second observation is a variation of the first. When problems come and questions arise, do not start your quest for faith by saying how much you do not have, leading as it were with your 'unbelief.'. . . I am not asking you to pretend to faith you do not have. I<i>am</i>asking you to be true to the faith you<i>do</i>have. . . .
"Last observation: When doubt or difficulty come, do not be afraid to ask for help. If we want it as humbly and honestly as this father did, we can get it" ("Lord, I Believe," Ensign or Liahona, May 2013, 93–94).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Ask questions that invite testimony.</b>Asking questions that encourage class members to bear their testimonies can be an effective way to invite the Spirit. For example, when discussing Matthew 16:13–17, you could ask, "What have you learned about the Savior that has strengthened your testimony of Him as the Savior?" (See Teaching in the Savior's Way, 32.)</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<graphics-caption>The Good Samaritan, by Dan Burr</graphics-caption>
<heading>APRIL 17–23</heading>
<heading>Matthew 18; Luke 10</heading>
<heading>"WHAT SHALL I DO TO INHERIT ETERNAL LIFE?"</heading>
<p>Read Matthew 18 and Luke 10, and record your spiritual impressions. As you receive impressions, you might ask, as Elder Richard G. Scott suggested, "Is there more I should know?" ("To Acquire Spiritual Guidance," Ensign or Liahona, Nov. 2009, 8).</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>These chapters contain many examples of gospel that are different from what the world teachings teaches us. Perhaps class members could share some examples they found in their reading this week. How does the Lord bless us when we apply His teachings?</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>MATTHEW 18:21–35</heading>
<heading>We must forgive others if we are to receive forgiveness from the Lord.</heading>
<ul>
<li>How could you use the parable of the unmerciful servant to inspire class members to be more forgiving? Perhaps you could write questions like the following on the board and invite class members to ponder them as one person retells the parable:<i>Who does the king represent? Who does the unmerciful servant represent? Who does the fellow servant represent? What do the debts represent?</i>Invite class members to share what messages the parable has for them personally. (See also "Additional Resources.")</li>
<li>You could invite the class to create an adaptation of the parable of the unmerciful servant that teaches the same lessons about forgiveness using modern situations and details. (Consider having them work on this in groups.) Discuss how the parable answered Peter's question about how many times he should forgive.</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>Jesus spoke of money and debt to teach about forgiveness.</graphics-caption>
<heading>LUKE 10:25–37</heading>
<heading>To obtain eternal life, we must love God and our neighbors.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Here's an idea that might give class members a fresh view of the parable of the good Samaritan: Invite them to pretend that they are investigating a case of assault and robbery on the road between Jericho and Jerusalem. Ask a few class members to come to class prepared to represent the different people in the parable and talk about their involvement in the case. For example, what might be some reasons the priest and Levite didn't stop to help the injured man? Why did the Samaritan stop? What thoughts could the innkeeper add? How might the injured man have felt about each of the others? Make sure the discussion inspires class members to be like the good Samaritan and the innkeeper and avoid being like the priest and Levite.</li>
<li>How does the parable of the good Samaritan answer the questions asked of Jesus in Luke 10:25–29? Invite class members to talk about times when they felt like the "certain man" (verse 30) who needed help desperately. How did help come? How can we as ward members work together to help others, like the good Samaritan and the innkeeper did?</li>
</ul>
<heading>LUKE 10:38–42</heading>
<heading>We choose "that good part" by making daily choices that lead to eternal life.</heading>
<ul>
<li>After reading Luke 10:38–42 as a class, you could ask class members how they might have reacted to the Savior's counsel if they had been in Martha's place. How might this experience have affected their future choices? How can we know what things in our own lives deserve more time and attention? Class members could search President Dallin H. Oaks's message "Good, Better, Best" (Ensign or Liahona, Nov. 2007, 104–8) to find counsel that can help them.</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>The debts in the parable of the unmerciful servant.</heading>
<p>Commenting on the debts owed in the parable of the unmerciful servant, Elder Jeffrey R. Holland said:
"There is some difference of opinion among scholars regarding the monetary values mentioned here — and forgive the U.S. monetary reference — but to make the math easy, if the smaller, unforgiven 100–pence debt were, say, $100 in current times, then the 10,000–talent debt so freely forgiven would have approached $1 billion — or more!
"As a personal debt, that is an astronomical number totally beyond comprehension. (Nobody can shop that much!) Well, for the purposes of this parable, it is<i>supposed</i>to be incomprehensible; it is<i>supposed</i>to be beyond our ability to grasp, to say nothing of beyond our ability to repay. That is because this isn't a story about two servants arguing in the New Testament. It is a story about us, fallen human family — mortal debtors, transgressors, and prisoners all. Every one of us is a debtor, and the verdict was imprisonment for every one of us. And there we would all have remained were it not for the grace of a King who sets us free because He loves us and is «moved with compassion toward us» [Doctrine and Covenants 121:4]" ("Be Ye Therefore Perfect Eventually," Ensign or Liahona, Nov. 2017, 41).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Follow the Savior's example.</b>As you read accounts of the Savior teaching in the New Testament, look for lessons in His example that can help you become a better teacher. For instance, in Luke 10:25–37, what did Jesus do to teach the lawyer about how to obtain eternal life?</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<graphics-caption>Neither Do I Condemn Thee, by Eva Koleva Timothy</graphics-caption>
<heading>APRIL 24–30</heading>
<heading>John 7–10</heading>
<heading>"I AM THE GOOD SHEPHERD"</heading>
<p>You and your class members will gain insights while reading John 7–10 this week. Remember that the ideas in this outline should supplement rather than replace the inspiration you receive by studying the scriptures.</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>Remind class members about the importance of making their homes the center of gospel learning. Ask them to share what the Holy Ghost taught them as they studied John 7–10 at home, individually or with their families.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>JOHN 7–10</heading>
<heading>Jesus Christ is the Savior of the world.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Throughout John 7–10, the Savior made several declarations that can help class members better understand His mission and draw closer to Him. Consider inviting class members to read the following scripture passages and share what they teach about the Savior's divine mission. How does Christ fulfill these roles in our lives?
<ul>
<li>John 7:37–39: The source of "living water"</li>
<li>John 8:12; 9:4–5: "The light of the world"</li>
<li>John 9:8–10, 35–38: "The Son of God"</li>
<li>John 10:7–9: "The door"</li>
<li>John 10:11–14: "The good shepherd"</li>

</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>Light of the World, by Howard Lyon</graphics-caption>
<heading>JOHN 7:14–17</heading>
<heading>As we live the teachings of Jesus Christ, we will come to know they are true.</heading>
<ul>
<li>In some ways, gaining a testimony is like learning a skill — both require practice and experience. To illustrate this, you could invite class members who have a particular skill, such as juggling or playing a musical instrument, to explain how they developed their skill. Why isn't it enough to read about the skill or watch someone else perform it? As a class, discuss how the effort involved in practicing a skill is similar to the spiritual pattern the Savior described in John 7:14–17. How is it different?</li>
<li>Perhaps class members could share experiences in which living a gospel truth helped them gain a testimony of it. Give class members time to think of a gospel principle they would like to gain a stronger testimony of, and then encourage them to set specific goals to live that principle more fully.</li>
</ul>
<heading>JOHN 8:1–11</heading>
<heading>The Savior's mercy is extended to all who repent.</heading>
<ul>
<li>To those who feel condemned because of their sins, the story of the Savior offering mercy and repentance to the woman taken in adultery could be a source of encouragement. Or, if class members feel tempted to condemn others because of their sins, the story could serve as a warning. You could invite class members to read John 8:1–11, looking for answers to questions like the following: What does this story teach about the Savior's mercy? How might receiving His mercy when we sin help us when we feel tempted to judge others? (see Alma 29:9–10).</li>
<li>To help class members find personal relevance in John 8:1–11, consider dividing the class into three groups — one to focus on the words and actions of the Pharisees, one to focus on the words and actions of the Savior, and one to focus on the words and actions of the woman. They could do this while reading the account or while watching the video "Go and Sin No More" (ChurchofJesusChrist.org). Invite each group to make a list of the spiritual truths they learn from reading each part of the account.</li>
<li>Sometimes we aren't aware of ways in which we judge others. Here's an activity to help class members overcome this tendency: Ask the class to help you create a list of ways we judge people (on their appearance, their behavior, their background, and so on). Give class members pieces of paper cut in the shape of a stone, and ask them to select a way of judging others that they feel they are guilty of and write it on a paper stone. What do we learn from the Savior's words to the Pharisees in John 8:1–11? Invite the class to write on the other side of their paper stones something that will remind them not to judge (perhaps a phrase from John 8).</li>
</ul>
<heading>JOHN 8:18–19, 26–29</heading>
<heading>As we come to know Jesus Christ, we come to know the Father.</heading>
<ul>
<li>What do the Savior's words in John 8:18–19, 26–29 teach about the connection between Him and His Father? After reading and discussing these verses, class members could list on the board some things Jesus did, said, or taught. What do we learn about God the Father from these things?</li>
</ul>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Live worthy of the Spirit's guidance.</b>When you live the gospel, you are worthy of the companionship of the Spirit. As you seek His guidance, He will give you thoughts and impressions about how to meet the needs of those you teach. (See Teaching in the Savior's Way, 5.)</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<graphics-caption>The Prodigal Son, by Liz Lemon Swindle</graphics-caption>
<heading>MAY 1–7</heading>
<heading>Luke 12–17; John 11</heading>
<heading>"REJOICE WITH ME; FOR I HAVE FOUND MY SHEEP WHICH WAS LOST"</heading>
<p>Begin your preparation by prayerfully studying Luke 12–17 and John 11. What "lost sheep" in your class come to mind? Use<i>Come, Follow Me—For Individuals and Families</i>and this outline as you seek the Lord's guidance on how to best meet class members' needs, even if they aren't attending class.</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>Application is an important part of learning, so invite class members to share how they chose to live something they learned from the scriptures this week.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>LUKE 14:15–24</heading>
<heading>No excuse is sufficient for rejecting the gospel.</heading>
<ul>
<li>To help class members study the parable of the great supper, you might invite them to an imaginary party that you will host. Let them share some reasons why they might or might not attend. Read Luke 14:15–24 together, and discuss the excuses the people in the parable made when they were invited to a feast that represented the blessings of the gospel. What excuses do people make today for failing to accept the Savior's invitations to receive Heavenly Father's blessings? Perhaps class members could share blessings they have received when they have made the sacrifices necessary to live certain gospel principles.</li>
</ul>
<heading>LUKE 15</heading>
<heading>We can seek out those who are lost and rejoice with the Father when they return.</heading>
<ul>
<li>How will you give class members the opportunity to share what they have learned about the three parables in Luke 15? Consider assigning each class member one of the parables to review. They could look for and share answers to questions like these: What words in the parable reveal how Heavenly Father feels about those who are lost? What do the parables suggest about how we should reach out to all of God's children? Class members could share how the Savior has found them when they have felt lost.</li>
<li>Singing "Dear to the Heart of the Shepherd" (Hymns, no. 221) together might be a meaningful addition to the teachings of these parables.</li>
<li>As review the parable of the prodigal son together, class members may benefit from focusing on the words, actions, and beliefs of in the parable. What do we learn from each person? Perhaps class members could write an alternate ending to the parable in which each person the older son's attitude toward his brother is different. What does the father's counsel in the parable teach us about how we should feel about those who are lost and those who return to the gospel? (See also Elder Jeffrey R. Holland's statement in "Additional Resources.") Or you could ask class members to imagine that they are the father in this parable. What additional counsel would they give the older son to help him rejoice in the progress or success of others?</li>
</ul>
<heading>LUKE 17:11–19</heading>
<heading>Gratitude for my blessings will bring me closer to God.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Invite class members to share what they learned about gratitude from their study of Luke 17:11–19 and the video "President Russell M. Nelson on the Healing Power of Gratitude" (ChurchofJesusChrist.org). How was the thankful leper blessed for expressing his gratitude? How are we blessed when we express gratitude? Class members could suggest ways we can show our gratitude to God and others.</li>
</ul>
<heading>JOHN 11:1–46</heading>
<heading>Jesus Christ is the Resurrection and the Life.</heading>
<ul>
<li>One way to examine John 11:1–46 is to ask class members to take turns reading the verses and invite them to stop when they find evidence of faith in Jesus Christ. You could also ask class members to consider the perspectives of the people involved including the Savior, the Apostles, Martha, Mary, and Lazarus. What do we learn from each of them? Perhaps class members could share experiences when their faith in Jesus Christ was strengthened during a trial.</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>Learning from the other prodigal.</heading>
<p>Elder Jeffrey R. Holland made this observation about the prodigal son's older brother: "This son is not so much angry that the other has come home as he is angry that his parents are so happy about it. . . . He has yet to come to the compassion and mercy, the charitable breadth of vision to see that<i>this is not a rival returning.</i>It is his brother. As his father pled with him to see, it is one who was dead and now is alive. It is one who was lost and now is found" ("The Other Prodigal," Ensign, May 2002, 63).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Reach out to the one.</b>Like the shepherd in the Savior's parable (see Luke 15:4), "you can reach out to those who are missing from your class. Your opportunities to teach and lift class members and help them come unto Christ extend beyond the classroom and beyond those who attend your formal lessons" (Teaching in the Savior's Way, 8).</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<heading>MAY 8–14</heading>
<heading>Matthew 19–20; Mark 10; Luke 18</heading>
<heading>"WHAT LACK I YET?"</heading>
<p>As you prepare to teach, prayerfully consider how you can help class members share what they learned or felt during their own study.</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>It might be helpful to occasionally discuss class members' overall experiences with home-centered gospel learning. What successful experiences can they share? What obstacles or challenges are they facing? What advice can they give each other?</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>MATTHEW 19:3–9</heading>
<heading>Marriage between a man and a woman is essential to God's eternal plan.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Increasingly, the world's views on marriage diverge from eternal truth. To help your class learn about God's views on marriage, you might invite them to read Matthew 19:3–9 and list on the board the truths they find regarding marriage. They could also list additional truths they find in the following: Genesis 1:27–28; 1 Corinthians 11:11; Doctrine and Covenants 42:22; 49:15–17; 131:1–4; 132:19; and Moses 3:18, 21–24. How are these truths reinforced in "The Family: A Proclamation to the World"? (ChurchofJesusChrist.org).</li>
</ul>
<heading>MATTHEW 20:1–16</heading>
<heading>Everyone can receive the blessing of eternal life, no matter when they receive the gospel.</heading>
<ul>
<li>What would help members of your class apply the principles in the parable of the laborers in the vineyard? You might invite a few class members to prepare a dramatization of the parable to present to the class. After the presentation, the people portraying the laborers could share how they felt about the payment they received and why. What does this parable suggest about the kingdom of heaven? What additional insights do we gain about this parable from Elder Jeffrey R. Holland's message "The Laborers in the Vineyard"? (Ensign or Liahona, May 2012, 31–33).</li>
</ul>
<heading>MATTHEW 19:16–22; MARK 10:17–27</heading>
<heading>The Savior will guide us closer to Him as we ask for His help.</heading>
<ul>
<li>How can you help class members identify and apply principles in the story of the rich young man? One approach could be to ask them to read Mark 10:17–27 and consider whether they have ever felt like the rich young man. What has helped us follow the Savior's counsel even when doing so was difficult? Class members may be willing to share experiences in which they asked "What lack I yet?" (Matthew 19:20) and received a personalized prompting to improve. To help class members who might become discouraged by focusing on what they lack, you could share the statement in "Additional Resources."</li>
<li>Class members may have read a conference message related to these verses as suggested in<i>Come, Follow Me—For Individuals and Families.</i>Invite them to share insights they gained.</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>The Repentant Publican and the Self-Righteous Pharisee in the Temple, by Frank Adams</graphics-caption>
<heading>LUKE 18:9–14</heading>
<heading>We should trust God's mercy, not our own righteousness.</heading>
<ul>
<li>The Savior's parable comparing a Pharisee's prayer with a publican's can help you highlight the attitude that the Lord asks of those who seek to follow Him. To help class members apply this parable to our day, you could invite them to rewrite the Pharisee's prayer in a way that uses modern details but expresses the same attitudes. They could do the same with the publican's prayer and then share what they wrote. How do verses 15–17 and 18–24 relate to what the Savior taught in this parable? You might also share the following statement regarding these verses by Elder Dale G. Renlund: "The message for us is clear: a repenting sinner draws closer to God than does the self-righteous person who condemns that sinner" ("Our Good Shepherd," Ensign or Liahona, May 2017, 31).</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>Let us not be content or discouraged.</heading>
<p>Elder D. Todd Christofferson taught:
"If we sincerely ask, «What lack I yet?» [God] will not leave us to guess, but in love He will answer for the sake of our happiness. And He will give us hope.
"It is a consuming endeavor, and it would be terribly daunting if in our striving for holiness we were alone. The glorious truth is we are not alone. We have the love of God, the grace of Christ, the comfort and guidance of the Holy Spirit, and the fellowship and encouragement of fellow Saints in the body of Christ. Let us not be content with where we are, but neither let us be discouraged" ("The Living Bread Which Came Down from Heaven," Ensign or Liahona, Nov. 2017, 39).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>God needs your unique talents and abilities.</b>"You can bless God's children by drawing on the love you have for others, the gifts God has given you, and your life experiences. As you serve faithfully and seek God's help, He will magnify you, and you will grow in your capacity to teach the gospel in the Savior's way" (Teaching in the Savior's Way, 5).</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<graphics-caption>Zacchaeus in the Sycamore Tree, by James Tissot</graphics-caption>
<heading>MAY 15–21</heading>
<heading>Matthew 21–23; Mark 11; Luke 19–20; John 12</heading>
<heading>"BEHOLD, THY KING COMETH"</heading>
<p>As you read Matthew 21–23; Mark 11; Luke 19–20; and John 12, look for principles that will help meet the needs of the people you teach. The Holy Ghost will inspire you to know how to help class members discover those principles.</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>Several days before class, invite a few class members to come to class prepared to share an experience they had while studying this week's assigned chapters. Ask them to tell about the blessings that come to them as they study the scriptures during the week.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>LUKE 19:1–10</heading>
<heading>The Savior knows us personally.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Your class members have likely felt overlooked or forgotten at times in their lives. The account of Zacchaeus can help them understand that Heavenly Father and Jesus Christ know them and care about them. To help class members liken this account to their lives, invite them to imagine themselves as Zacchaeus. What do you think he learned about the Savior from his experience? What can we learn from Zacchaeus's efforts about seeking the Savior?</li>
</ul>
<heading>MATTHEW 21:1–11; MARK 11:1–11; LUKE 19:29–44; JOHN 12:12–16</heading>
<heading>Jesus Christ is our King.</heading>
<ul>
<li>A simple activity could introduce a discussion about the Savior's triumphal entry into Jerusalem: Several class members could draw on the board things associated with a king, such as a crown or a throne, while the others guess what they are drawing. Then other class members could draw a colt and tree branches. What do these things have to do with a king? You could then show the picture of the Savior's triumphal entry into Jerusalem from this week's outline in<i>Come, Follow Me—For Individuals and Families</i>and invite class members to read Mark 11:1–11. How did these people recognize Jesus as their King? How do we worship Jesus Christ as our King through our words and actions?</li>
</ul>
<heading>MATTHEW 22:34–40</heading>
<heading>The two great commandments are to love God and love others as ourselves.</heading>
<ul>
<li>How can you help class members understand that "on these two commandments" — loving God and loving our neighbor — "hang all the law and the prophets"? (Matthew 22:40). After reading Matthew 22:34–40 together, you could write<i>Love God</i>and<i>Love your neighbor</i>on the board. Give each class member a slip of paper with a commandment written on it. Invite a few of them to read their commandment and talk about how their commandment helps us obey one or both of discuss these two great commandments. After they their their commandment, they could put paper on the board. Why is it important to remember that all commandments relate to the two great commandments? (see "Additional Resources").</li>
</ul>
<heading>MATTHEW 23:13–33</heading>
<heading>We will be protected as we avoid following blind guides.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Would your class members benefit from discussing the term "blind guides," which the Savior used to describe the spiritually blind Pharisees and scribes? (Matthew 23:16). You might think of a way to demonstrate what it would be like for someone to follow a person who couldn't see. Or the class could list on the board the characteristics of a blind guide, as described in Matthew 23:13–33. To add to the list, consider looking at additional scriptures that teach about spiritual blindness, such as 2 Corinthians 4:3–4; 2 Nephi 9:28–32; and Jacob 4:14. How can we recognize and avoid blind guides?</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>The Savior denounced the Pharisees as hypocrites and blind guides</graphics-caption>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>Loving God and loving our neighbors is the foundation of all we do.</heading>
<p>Referring to the two great commandments found in Matthew 22:37–39, President M. Russell Ballard taught:
"Obedience to those two commandments provides a way to experience more peace and joy. When we love and serve the Lord and love and serve our neighbors, we will naturally feel more happiness that comes to us in no better way.
"Loving God and loving our neighbors is the doctrinal foundation of ministering; home-centered, Church-supported learning; Sabbath-day spiritual worship; and the work of salvation on both sides of the veil supported in the Relief Societies and the elders quorums. All of these things are based on the divine commandments to love God and to love our neighbors. Can there be anything more basic, more fundamental, and more simple than that?" ("The True, Pure, and Simple Gospel of Jesus Christ," Ensign or Liahona, May 2019, 29).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>You don't need to cover everything.</b>"There is much to discuss in each lesson, but it is not necessary to cover everything in one class period in order to touch someone's heart — often one or two key points are enough. As you ponder learners' needs, the Spirit will help you identify which principles, stories, or scriptures will be especially meaningful to them" (Teaching in the Savior's Way, 7).</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<graphics-caption>The Second Coming, by Harry Anderson</graphics-caption>
<heading>MAY 22–28</heading>
<heading>Joseph Smith–Matthew 1; Matthew 24–25; Mark 12–13; Luke 21</heading>
<heading>"THE SON OF MAN SHALL COME"</heading>
<p>Remember to begin your preparation to teach by prayerfully reading Joseph Smith–Matthew 1; Matthew 24–25; Mark 12–13; and Luke 21. Seek inspiration on your own, and then review this outline for additional ideas.</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>Make a list on the board of the Savior's parables found in this week's reading, such as the fig tree, the good man and the thief, the faithful and evil servants, the ten virgins, the talents, and the sheep and the goats. Ask class members to share truths they learned from these parables that can help them prepare for the Second Coming of the Lord. What are they doing to apply these truths to their lives?</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>Joseph Smith–Matthew 1:21–37</heading>
<heading>Prophecies about the Savior's Second Coming can help us face the future with faith.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Signs of the Savior's Second Coming may be difficult for some class members to understand. It might help them to work in groups and identify signs they find in Joseph Smith–Matthew 1:21–37. It might also help them better understand the importance of these signs if they compare them to road signs. Why are road signs important? How are the signs of the Second Coming like road signs? How are they different? You might even give each group pieces of paper in the shape of road signs and invite them to write on each paper a sign that will precede the Second Coming. Let them share what they found, and invite the class to discuss evidence of these signs in the world today.</li>
</ul>
<heading>Joseph Smith–Matthew 1:26–27, 38–55; MATTHEW 25:1–13</heading>
<heading>We must always be ready for the Savior's Second Coming.</heading>
<ul>
<li>The parables in Joseph Smith–Matthew 1:26–27, 38–55 and Matthew 25:1–13 can help class members recognize the importance of being prepared for the Second Coming. Invite class members to search these verses and share what they feel the Savior is inviting us to do. Elder David A. Bednar gave one interpretation of the parable of the ten virgins that could help (see "Additional Resources"). Why must each of us experience conversion for ourselves? How do we do this? What does Doctrine and Covenants 45:56–57 add to our understanding of this parable?</li>
<li>As you learn about the Savior's return, you might read or sing together hymns about the Second Coming (see "Jesus Christ — Second Coming" in the topical index at the back of the hymnbook).</li>
</ul>
<heading>MATTHEW 25:14–46</heading>
<heading>At the Final Judgment, we will give the Lord an account of our lives.</heading>
<ul>
<li>The parable of the talents and the parable of the sheep and goats can inspire us to think about the account of our lives we will give to the Lord at the Final Judgment. You might read the parables together and invite each class member to share one question the Savior might ask about our lives when we are judged. Provide time for class members to plan ways they will act on impressions they have received during the discussion.</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>Christ used sheep and goats to teach about the Final Judgment (see Matthew 25:31–33).</graphics-caption>
<ul>
<li>To inspire a discussion about Matthew 25:34–40, you could invite class members to share examples of people who demonstrate the compassion described in these verses. Give them time to ponder who might need their service. What are some practical ways we can feed the hungry, clothe the naked, and visit the sick?</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>The oil of conversion.</heading>
<p>Elder David A. Bednar suggested this possible interpretation of the parable of the ten virgins:
"Consider the oil to be the oil of conversion [see Matthew 25:4–9]. . . .
"Were the five wise virgins selfish and unwilling to share, or were they indicating correctly that the oil of conversion cannot be borrowed? Can the spiritual strength that results from consistent obedience to the commandments be given to another person? Can the knowledge obtained through diligent study and pondering of the scriptures be conveyed to one who is in need? Can the peace the gospel brings to a faithful Latter-day Saint be transferred to an individual experiencing adversity or great challenge? The clear answer to each of these questions is no.
"As the wise virgins emphasized properly, each of us must «buy for ourselves.» These inspired women were not describing a business transaction; rather, they were emphasizing our individual responsibility to keep our lamp of testimony burning and to obtain an ample supply of the oil of conversion. This precious oil is acquired one drop at a time — «line upon line [and] precept upon precept» (2 Nephi 28:30), patiently and persistently" ("Converted unto the Lord," Ensign or Liahona, Nov. 2012, 109).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Ensure that you are teaching true doctrine.</b>"Continually ask yourself, «How will what I am teaching help my class members build faith in Christ, repent, make and keep covenants with God, and receive the Holy Ghost?»" (Teaching in the Savior's Way, 20).</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<graphics-caption>In Remembrance of Me, by Walter Rane</graphics-caption>
<heading>MAY 29–JUNE 4</heading>
<heading>Matthew 26; Mark 14; John 13</heading>
<heading>"IN REMEMBRANCE"</heading>
<p>Read Matthew 26; Mark 14; and John 13, and ponder the thoughts and impressions that come to your mind. What messages would bless members of your class?</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>Invite class members to share something they learned this week that helped them find more meaning in the sacrament. What did they do and how did it affect their experience partaking of the sacrament?</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>MATTHEW 26:20–22</heading>
<heading>We must examine our own lives to determine how the Lord's words apply to us.</heading>
<ul>
<li>We hear many gospel lessons in our lives, but sometimes it's tempting to assume those lessons apply mostly to other people. A discussion about Matthew 26:20–22 can help us overcome this tendency. What lessons can we learn from how the disciples applied the Savior's words to themselves? If any class members read President Dieter F. Uchtdorf's reference to this account in his message "Lord, Is It I?," they could share insights they gained (Ensign or Liahona, Nov. 2014, 56–59).</li>
</ul>
<heading>MATTHEW 26:26–29</heading>
<heading>The sacrament is an opportunity to remember the Savior.</heading>
<ul>
<li>How would class members explain the sacred ordinance of the sacrament to someone who isn't familiar with it? Perhaps you can create a list together of questions that someone might have about the sacrament, such as "Why did the Savior give us the sacrament? Why are bread and water such powerful symbols of Jesus Christ? What do we promise as we partake of the sacrament? What promises do we receive?" Class members could look for answers in the following resources: Matthew 26:26–29; Doctrine and Covenants 20:75–79; and Gospel Topics, "Sacrament" (topics.ChurchofJesusChrist.org). You might also share the insights from Elder D. Todd Christofferson in "Additional Resources."</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>The sacrament helps us remember Jesus Christ.</graphics-caption>
<ul>
<li>Class members may benefit from hearing each other's ideas about how to remember the Savior during the sacrament and throughout the week (see Luke 22:19–20; Doctrine and Covenants 6:36–37). Perhaps you could invite them to share what helps them and their families remember the Savior and keep their covenants. They could also share what they do to make the sacrament a sacred experience.</li>
</ul>
<heading>JOHN 13:1–17</heading>
<heading>The Savior is our example of humbly serving others.</heading>
<ul>
<li>To help your class members ponder the significance of Jesus washing His disciples' feet, you could invite a class member to play the role of Peter and be interviewed by the rest of the class.Class members could search John 13:1–17 and think of meaningful questions they could ask Peter to learn about his experience. What do we learn from this account that might affect how we serve others?</li>
</ul>
<heading>JOHN 13:34–35</heading>
<heading>Our love for others is a sign that we are true disciples of Jesus Christ.</heading>
<ul>
<li>How might you inspire class members to be more loving? Perhaps you could ask them what traits they notice when they meet someone who is a follower of Christ. You could invite them to search John 13:34–35 to learn how the Savior's true disciples can be identified. What can we do to make love the defining characteristic How might you inspire class members to be more loving? Perhaps you could ask them what traits they notice when they meet someone who is a follower of Christ. You could invite them to search John 13:34–35 to learn how the Savior's true disciples can be identified. What can we do to make love the defining characteristic of our discipleship? Perhaps you could discuss how loving others is a way of testifying of Jesus Christ. How can we do this in our families, on social media, and in other settings?</li>
<li>As a class, you have learned a lot about the Savior's life this year, including many examples of how He showed His love for others. One way to help class members ponder the commandment in John 13:34 could be to write<i>As I Have Loved You</i>on the board and to ask class members to list examples they recall from the New Testament that illustrate Jesus's love. Then you could write<i>Love One Another</i>on the board and ask class members to list ways we can follow His example of love. Class members might find ideas in one of the videos listed in "Additional Resources."</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>"Internalize the qualities and character of Christ."</heading>
<p>Elder D. Todd Christofferson taught, "Figuratively eating [the Savior's] flesh and drinking His blood [means] to internalize the qualities and character of Christ, putting off the natural man and becoming Saints through the atonement of Christ the Lord' [Mosiah 3:19]. As we partake of the sacramental bread and water each week, we would do well to consider how fully and completely we must incorporate His character and the pattern of His sinless life into our life and being" ("The Living Bread Which Came Down from Heaven," Ensign or Liahona, Nov. 2017, 37).</p>
<heading>Videos about love on ChurchofJesusChrist.org.</heading>
<ul>
<li>"Love One Another"</li>
<li>"Families Sacrifice, Give, and Love"</li>
<li>"Preparation of Thomas S. Monson: He Learned Compassion in His Youth"</li>
</ul>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Look through God's eyes.</b>Strive to see your class members as God sees them, and the Spirit will show you their divine worth and potential. As you do this, you will be guided in your efforts to help them (see Teaching in the Savior's Way, 6).</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<graphics-caption>The Last Supper, by William Henry Margetson</graphics-caption>
<heading>JUNE 5–11</heading>
<heading>John 14–17</heading>
<heading>"CONTINUE YE IN MY LOVE"</heading>
<p>As you prayerfully study John 14–17, ponder how you can best show love to those you teach. The Holy Ghost will bring ideas to your mind as you study the scriptures,<i>Come, Follow Me—For Individuals and Families</i>, and this outline.</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>Write the numbers 14 through 17 on the board, representing the chapters in John that class members read this week. Invite a few class members to write, next to each chapter number, the reference to a verse that the Holy Ghost helped them better understand or that they would like to discuss as class.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>JOHN 14:16–27; 15:26; 16:7–15</heading>
<heading>The Holy Ghost helps us fulfill our purposes as disciples of Jesus Christ.</heading>
<ul>
<li>To help class members learn about the different roles of the Holy Ghost, consider inviting them to read one or more of the following passages: John 14:16–27; 15:26; and 16:7–15. They could write on the board what they learn about the Holy Ghost from these passages. They could also look for insights about the Holy Ghost in the scriptures and messages listed in "Additional Resources." How has the Holy Ghost fulfilled these roles in our lives? You might also think of objects or visual aids you could bring to class to help class members understand some of these roles.</li>
<li>Consider inviting a few class members ahead of time to study one of the general conference addresses suggested in "Additional Resources" (or another conference address they know of) about the Holy Ghost. Allow them to share briefly what they learned with the class. What do these messages add to what we have learned about the Holy Ghost from John 14–16?</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>The Last Supper, by Clark Kelley Price</graphics-caption>
<heading>JOHN 15:1–12</heading>
<heading>As we abide in Christ, we will bring forth good fruit and have joy.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Consider bringing a small plant (or a picture of one) to class and using it to help class members visualize the Savior's teaching about the vine and branches. After reading John 15:1–12 as a class, you could discuss what it means to "abide in [Christ]" (John 15:4). A few class members could share how they have found John 15:5 to be true. (See also the statement from Elder Jeffrey R. Holland in "Additional Resources.")</li>
</ul>
<heading>JOHN 17</heading>
<heading>Heavenly Father and Jesus Christ are perfectly united.</heading>
<ul>
<li>You probably can't teach all of the important truths found in John 17 in one class discussion, but here's a way to help the class explore several of them. List on the board concepts from John 17, such as these:
<ul>
<li>Our relationship with Jesus Christ</li>
<li>Jesus Christ's relationship with His Father</li>
<li>Our relationship with the rest of the world</li>
<li>Our relationship with each other as His disciples</li>
</ul>
Invite each class member to choose one of these concepts and to read John 17, searching for versese that are related to it. Ask several class members to share what they learn.
How does our relationship with God affect our relationships with each other? How do our relationships with each other affect our relationship with God?</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>The Holy Ghost.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Acts 2:37–38; Galatians 5:22–23; 1 Nephi 10:17–19; 2 Nephi 32:3–5; Mosiah 3:19; 3 Nephi 27:20; Moroni 8:26; 10:4–5; Doctrine and Covenants 8:2–3; 42:17</li>
<li>Henry B. Eyring, "His Spirit to Be with You," Ensign or Liahona, May 2018, 86–89</li>
<li>David A. Bednar, "Receive the Holy Ghost," Ensign or Liahona, Nov. 2010, 94–97</li>
<li>Michelle D. Craig, "Spiritual Capacity," Ensign or Liahona, Nov. 2019, 19–21</li>
</ul>
<heading>Abiding in Christ.</heading>
<p>Noting that the word<i>abide</i>has connotations of permanence and commitment, Elder Jeffrey R. Holland taught:
"The sense this [word] then is 'stay — but stay<i>forever</i>. . . . Come, but come to remain. Come with conviction and endurance. . . .
"Jesus said, «Without me ye can do nothing» [John 15:5]. I testify that that is God's truth. Christ is everything to us and we are to «abide» in Him permanently, unyieldingly, steadfastly, forever. For the fruit of the gospel to blossom and bless our lives, we must be firmly attached to Him, the Savior of us all, and to this His Church, which bears His holy name. He is the vine that is our true source of strength and the only source of eternal life. In Him we not only will endure but also will prevail and triumph in this holy cause that will never fail us" ("Abide in Me," Ensign or Liahona, May 2004, 32).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Invite the Spirit.</b>"We can be instruments in God's hands to help His children learn by the Spirit. To do this, we invite the influence of the Spirit into our lives and encourage those we teach to do the same. . . . Sacred music, the scriptures, words of latter-day prophets, expressions of love and testimony, and moments of quiet contemplation can all invite the presence of the Spirit" (Teaching in the Savior's Way, 10).</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<graphics-caption>Gethsemane Grove, by Derek Hegsted</graphics-caption>
<heading>JUNE 12–18</heading>
<heading>Luke 22; John 18</heading>
<heading>"NOT MY WILL, BUT THINE, BE DONE"</heading>
<p>Consider what you will do to invite the Spirit into your class as you discuss the sacred events in these chapters. Prayerfully seek ways to help class members deepen their love for the Savior and their faith in Him.</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>Invite several class members to share what they felt as they read this week and what verses helped them feel this way.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>LUKE 22:39–46</heading>
<heading>We become more Christlike when we choose to submit our will to the Father's.</heading>
<ul>
<li>The Savior's example of submitting to the Father's will can help your class members when they need to do the same. To start a discussion, you could invite class members to share experiences when they submitted themselves to something they knew God wanted them to do. Ask them to share how they knew what God wanted them to do and how they were blessed for submitting to His will. Invite the class to read Luke 22:39–46 and talk about why the Savior was willing to submit His will to His Father's. How can we follow the Savior's example?</li>
<li>In addition to the Savior's act of submission to God in Luke 22:42, what other examples of His submissiveness do we find in Luke 22 and John 18? How did the Savior submit to His Father's will throughout His life? What can we do to be more like Him? The statement from Elder Neal A. Maxwell in "Additional Resources" might help inspire class members to consider how they can submit their will to God's.</li>
</ul>
<heading>LUKE 22:39–46</heading>
<heading>Jesus Christ performed an infinite Atonement for us.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Luke 22:39–46 describes what happened in Gethsemane. To help class members understand the personal significance of this sacred event, maybe you could write on the board questions like<i>What happened in Gethsemane?</i>and<i>Why is it important to me?</i>Class members could find answers in Luke 22:39–46; Alma 7:11–13; Doctrine and Covenants 19:16–19; and the video "The Savior Suffers in Gethsemane" (ChurchofJesusChrist.org). They could also find answers in President Tad R. Callister's message "The Atonement of Jesus Christ" (Ensign or Liahona, May 2019, 85–87).</li>
<li>In the Book of Mormon, Jacob calls the Atonement of Jesus Christ "an infinite atonement" (2 Nephi 9:7). To help class members understand what this means, you could share President Russell M. Nelson's teachings in "Additional Resources" and ask class members to list the ways that the influence of the Savior's sacrifice could be considered infinite. They could also read the following scriptures and add to their list: Hebrews 10:10; Alma 34:10–14; Doctrine and Covenants 76:24; and Moses 1:33. How can we show our appreciation for what the Savior has done for us?</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>Peter's Denial, by Carl Heinrich Bloch</graphics-caption>
<heading>LUKE 22:54–62</heading>
<heading>We can be faithful to Jesus Christ despite our fears and weaknesses.</heading>
<ul>
<li>To help class members visualize the events in Luke 22:54–62, you might show a picture, such as Peter's Denial (ChurchofJesusChrist.org), or the video "Jesus Is Tried by Caiaphas, Peter Denies Knowing Him" (ChurchofJesusChrist.org). Class members could share what they learn from Peter's experiences that inspires them to be faithful to Jesus Christ.</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>Submitting our will to the Father.</heading>
<p>Elder Neal A. Maxwell taught: "As you submit your wills to God, you are giving Him the<i>only</i>thing you<i>can</i>actually give Him that is really yours to give. Don't wait too long to find the altar or to begin to place the gift of your wills upon it!" ("Remember How Merciful the Lord Hath Been," Ensign or Liahona, May 2004, 46).</p>
<heading>The infinite Atonement.</heading>
<p>President Russell M. Nelson taught:
"[Jesus Christ's] Atonement is infinite — without an end. It was also infinite in that all humankind would be saved from never-ending death. It was infinite in terms of His immense suffering. It was infinite in time, putting an end to the preceding prototype of animal sacrifice. It was infinite in scope — it was to be done once for all. And the mercy of the Atonement extends not only to an infinite number of people, but also to an infinite number of worlds created by Him. It was infinite beyond any human scale of measurement or mortal comprehension.
"Jesus was the only one who could offer such an infinite atonement, since He was born of a mortal mother and an immortal Father. Because of that unique birthright, Jesus was an infinite Being" ("The Atonement," Ensign, Nov. 1996, 35).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Be a humble instrument of the Spirit.</b>"Your purpose as a teacher is not to make an impressive presentation but rather to help others receive the influence of the Holy Ghost, who is the true teacher" (Teaching in the Savior's Way, 10).</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<graphics-caption>Ecce Homo, by Antonio Ciseri</graphics-caption>
<heading>JUNE 19–25</heading>
<heading>MATTHEW 27; MARK 15; LUKE 23; JOHN 19</heading>
<heading>"IT IS FINISHED"</heading>
<p>Begin your preparation to teach by prayerfully reading Matthew 27; Mark 15; Luke 23; and John 19. Seek to live worthy of the Spirit so that you can bear powerful witness of the Savior and His Atonement</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>Invite each class member to select a chapter from this week's reading and spend a few minutes scanning it, looking for a word, a phrase, or a detail that teaches them something meaningful about the Savior and His mission. Give them opportunities to share what they found and explain why it is meaningful to them.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>Matthew 27; Mark 15; Luke 23; John 19</heading>
<heading>Jesus Christ's willingness to suffer shows His love for the Father and for all of us.</heading>
<ul>
<li>To help your class understand how the Savior's suffering and death on the cross demonstrated His love, try an activity like this: Give each class member a paper heart, and invite them to write on their hearts a phrase from 1 Corinthians 13:4–7 that describes charity. Then ask them to search Matthew 27; Mark 15; Luke 23; or John 19 and write on the other side of their hearts a few verses that show how the Savior demonstrated the love described in the phrase they chose. Let them share what they find. What experiences have helped us understand the Savior's love?</li>
<li>Art can help class members visualize some of the events they read about this week. Perhaps you could divide the class into groups and assign a picture to each group (see "Additional Resources" for suggested pictures). Class members could read the verses that describe the event depicted in their picture. They could then share their thoughts and feelings about these events — including how the picture helps them better understand the Savior's Atonement. You might also consider showing the videos "Jesus Is Condemned before Pilate" and "Jesus Is Scourged and Crucified" (ChurchofJesusChrist.org). Encourage class members to bear testimony of the Savior and His Atonement.</li>
</ul>
<heading>MATTHEW 27:11–60</heading>
<heading>Ancient prophets foresaw the Savior's suffering and Crucifixion.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Ancient prophets foretold many of the events in the Savior's final hours. One way to help class members see this is to give each person one or more of the scriptures in "Additional Resources" and ask them to find verses in Matthew 27 that show how the scriptures were fulfilled. You might make a chart that matches the prophecies with their fulfillments. How do these prophecies strengthen our faith in Jesus Christ?</li>
</ul>
<heading>MATTHEW 27:27–49; MARK 15:16–32; LUKE 23:11, 35–39; JOHN 19:1–5</heading>
<heading>Opposition cannot stop the work of God.</heading>
<ul>
<li>To help class members faithfully face opposition as they live true to their faith, you could invite them to read verses describing the persecution the Savior faced (see Matthew 27:27–49; Mark 15:16–32; Luke 23:11, 35–39; John 19:1–5). What do we learn from the Savior's responses that can help us face opposition? What other examples of facing opposition can help us? (See, for example, Joseph Smith–History 1:24–25.)</li>
</ul>
<heading>LUKE 23:34–43</heading>
<heading>The Savior offers us hope and forgiveness.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Even in His final moments, the Savior continued to offer hope and forgiveness. Consider ways to inspire class members to follow His example. For instance, you could ask half of the class to read Luke 23:34–38 (including verse 34, footnote c, which provides insight from the Joseph Smith Translation) and the other half to read Luke 23:39–43. Class members could share what they learn about the Savior from their assigned verses. How can we follow the Savior's example?</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>Pictures of the persecution, suffering, and death of Jesus.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Pilate Washes His Hands (ChurchofJesusChrist.org; Matthew 27:11–25)</li>
<li>Christ with a Crown of Thorns (ChurchofJesusChrist.org; Matthew 27:26–31)</li>
<li>Jesus Carries His Cross (ChurchofJesusChrist.org; John 19:13–18)</li>
<li>The Crucifixion (ChurchofJesusChrist.org and Gospel Art Book, no. 57; Luke 23:33–46; John 19:23–37)</li>
<li>Burial of Jesus (ChurchofJesusChrist.org and Gospel Art Book, no. 58; John 19:38–42</li>
</ul>
<heading>Scriptures that foretell the trials and death of Jesus Christ.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Isaiah 53:5, 7</li>
<li>1 Nephi 19:9</li>
<li>Isaiah 50:6</li>
<li>Psalm 69:21</li>
<li>Psalm 22:16</li>
<li>1 Nephi 19:10</li>
<li>Psalm 22:18</li>
<li>Isaiah 53:12</li>
<li>Psalm 22:7–8</li>
<li>Psalm 22:1</li>
<li>Isaiah 53:9</li>
</ul>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Draw strength from the Savior.</b>"In your efforts to live and teach more like the Savior, you will inevitably fall short at times. Do not become discouraged; rather, let your mistakes and weaknesses turn you to Heavenly Father and the Savior" (Teaching in the Savior's Way, 14).</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<graphics-caption>Feed My Sheep, by Kamille Corry</graphics-caption>
<heading>JUNE 26–JULY 2</heading>
<heading>Matthew 28; Mark 16; Luke 24; John 20–21</heading>
<heading>"HE IS RISEN"</heading>
<p>Before exploring the teaching ideas in this outline, read Matthew 28; Mark 16; Luke 24; and John 20–21, and ponder how these chapters might be used to strengthen the faith of those you teach.</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>To help class members share what they learned in their personal and family study, ask them to write down a truth from this week's reading assignment that they feel should be shared with "all the world" (see Mark 16:15). At the end of class, ask them if they found any additional truths they would like to share.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>MATTHEW 28; MARK 16; LUKE 24; JOHN 20</heading>
<heading>Because Jesus was resurrected, we too will be resurrected.</heading>
<ul>
<li>You might give class members a few minutes to review this week's reading assignment and "Resurrection" in the Bible Dictionary and write down truths they learned about the Resurrection. Let a few share what they wrote, and encourage class members to raise their hands when they hear someone share a truth that is similar to what they wrote down. Why are these truths important to us? How do they influence our relationships? How do they influence our choices?</li>
</ul>
<heading>LUKE 24:13–35</heading>
<heading>We can invite the Savior to "abide with us."</heading>
<ul>
<li>To help class members see connections between their experiences and the experience of the disciples on the road to Emmaus, draw a road on the board, and invite class members to write details from the account in Luke 24:13–35 on one side of the road. Then, on the other side of the road, they could write parallels they see to their own experiences as followers of Jesus Christ. For example, they could write<i>"Their eyes were holden"</i>(Luke 24:16) on one side of the road and<i>We sometimes don't recognize the Lord's influence in our lives</i>on the other side. How can we invite the Savior to abide with us?</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>Jesus taught Thomas, "Be not faithless, but believing" (John 20:27).</graphics-caption>
<heading>JOHN 20:19–29</heading>
<heading>"Blessed are they that have not seen, and yet have believed."</heading>
<ul>
<li>Your Sunday School class can be a place for class members to strengthen each other's faith in things that they cannot see. Perhaps you could start by asking someone to summarize Thomas's experience in John 20:19–29. You could also show the video "Blessed Are They That Have Not Seen, and Yet Have Believed" (ChurchofJesusChrist.org). Class members could list on the board some things God asks us to believe without seeing. Then you could ask them to share experiences that have strengthened their testimonies of these things and blessings that have come to them as they have exercised faith.</li>
</ul>
<heading>JOHN 21:1–17</heading>
<heading>The Savior invites us to feed His sheep.</heading>
<ul>
<li>What might help your class members accept the Savior's invitation to "feed [His] sheep"? You might start by inviting them to read John 21:15–17 silently, replacing Simon's name with their own name and "my lambs" and "my sheep" with the names of people they feel the Lord wants them to serve — for example, people they minister to, neighbors, or people they What might help your class members accept the Savior's invitation to "feed [His] sheep"? You might start by inviting them to read John 21:15–17 silently, replacing Simon's name with their own name and "my lambs" and "my sheep" with the names of people they feel the Lord wants them to serve — for example, people they minister to, neighbors, or people they know at work or school. After a few minutes, class members could share impressions they had. What do we learn about the Savior from His actions in John 21:4–13? What can we do to feed the Savior's lambs and sheep? The statement by Elder Gary E. Stevenson in "Additional Resources" could help answer this question.</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>How can we "feed [His] sheep"?</heading>
<p>Elder Gary E. Stevenson explained how we can fulfill the Lord's commandment to feed His sheep:
"Who is a shepherd? Every man, woman, and child in the kingdom of God is a shepherd. No calling is required. From the moment we emerge from the waters of baptism, we are commissioned to this work. We reach out in love to others because it is what our Savior commanded us to do. . . . Whenever our neighbors are in distress temporally or spiritually, we run to their aid. We bear one another's burdens that they may be light. We mourn with those who mourn. We comfort those who stand in need of comfort [see Mosiah 18:8–9]. The Lord lovingly expects this of us. And the day will come when we will be held accountable for the care we take in ministering to His flock [see Matthew 25:31–46]" ("Shepherding Souls," Ensign or Liahona, Nov. 2018, 111).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Reserve time for learners to share.</b>"When learners share what they are learning, they not only feel the Spirit and strengthen their own testimonies, but they also encourage other class members to discover truths for themselves. . . . Reserve time for student sharing in every lesson in some cases, you may find that these discussions are the lesson" (Teaching in the Savior's Way, 30).</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<graphics-caption>Day of Pentecost, by Sidney King</graphics-caption>
<heading>JULY 3–9</heading>
<heading>Acts 1–5</heading>
<heading>"YE SHALL BE WITNESSES UNTO ME"</heading>
<p>If you read Acts 1–5 and seek the guidance of the Spirit, you will receive inspiration about what truths in the chapters will help your class members more fully rely on the Holy Ghost and be faithful witnesses of the Lord Jesus Christ.</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>There are many meaningful passages and principles in Acts 1–5. One great way to discover which are the most valuable and relevant to members of your class is to let them tell you what stood out to them in their study. How will you invite this kind of sharing? It could be as simple as giving them a few minutes to find and share a verse from Acts 1–5 in which they felt the voice of the Lord speaking to them.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>ACTS 1:1–8; 2:37–39; 4:1–13, 31–33</heading>
<heading>Jesus Christ directs His Church through the Holy Ghost.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Reading about the experiences of the Apostles can help your class members see how they can receive power and guidance from the Holy Ghost in their Church callings and assignments. One way to review the experiences in Acts 1–5 would be to write on the board<i>The Holy Ghost helped the Apostles lead the Church by:</i>and then invite class members to search Acts 1:1–8; 2:37–39; and 4:1–13, 31–33, looking for ways to finish the sentence. Class members could then share experiences in which the Holy Ghost helped them in these ways. Why did the Apostles need the Holy Ghost and why do we need Him?</li>
</ul>
<heading>ACTS 1:15–26</heading>
<heading>The Apostles of Jesus Christ are called by God through revelation.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Consider inviting class members to explain how a business might go about choosing a replacement for an executive position. What qualifications might they look for? Ask class members to contrast this with how the Apostle Matthias was called (see Acts 1:15–26; see also 1 Samuel 16:1–13) and with President Gordon B. Hinckley's words in "Additional Resources" describing how Apostles are called today. How does God's method for choosing leaders affect our faith in the leaders He has called? Class members could share how they have gained a witness that today's apostles and prophets are called by Him.</li>
</ul>
<heading>ACTS 2:37–47</heading>
<heading>The Holy Ghost inspires us to act on what we learn.</heading>
<ul>
<li>As class members study the scriptures at home and together in class each week, they may often feel "pricked in their heart" (Acts 2:37). You may feel inspired to help them go a step further by asking, "What shall we do?" (Acts 2:37). Read Acts 2:37–47 together, inviting class members to search for things this group of 3,000 people did as a result of Peter's invitation. Maybe they could also share ways they have acted on inspiration from their study of the word of God. Then you might reserve time at the end of class for each person to ask themselves the question "What shall I do?" and record their impressions.</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>Despite being arrested and beaten, Peter boldly preached the gospel.</graphics-caption>
<heading>ACTS 3; 4:1–21; 5:12–42</heading>
<heading>As we are filled with the Holy Ghost, we can share the gospel with boldness.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Class members could review Acts 3; 4:1–21; 5:12 Class members could review Acts 3; 4:1–21; 5:12–42, looking for examples of Peter testifying boldly. Or they could watch one of the following videos: "Peter Preaches and Is Arrested," "Peter and John Are Judged," or "Peter and John Continue Preaching the Gospel" (ChurchofJesusChrist.org). What does it mean to speak "the word of God with boldness"? (Acts 4:31). How does the Holy Ghost help us share the gospel boldly? How is this kind of boldness different from being contentious? Class members might have experiences to share in which they, or someone they know, boldly defended or testified of the gospel.</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>The calling of a member of the Twelve.</heading>
<p>Gordon B. Hinckley shared the following insights about the process of calling a new Apostle: "The procedure is peculiar to the Lord's church. There is no seeking for office, no jockeying for position, no campaigning to promote one's virtues. Contrast the Lord's way with the way of the world. The Lord's way is quiet, it is a way of peace, it is without fanfare or monetary costs. It is without egotism or vanity or ambition. Under the Lord's plan, those who have responsibility to select officers are governed by one overriding question: 'Whom would the Lord have?"There is quiet and thoughtful deliberation. And there is much of prayer to receive the confirmation of the Holy Spirit that the choice is correct" ("God Is at the Helm," Ensign, May 1994, 53).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Invite learners to act.</b>The Holy Ghost often inspires us to act on what we are learning (see Acts 2:37). When this happened to the people Peter was teaching, he extended an invitation (see Acts 2:38). Consider how you can follow Peter's example.</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<graphics-caption>Conversion on the Way to Damascus, by Michelangelo Merisi da Caravaggio</graphics-caption>
<heading>JULY 10–16</heading>
<heading>Acts 6–9</heading>
<heading>"WHAT WILT THOU HAVE ME TO DO?"</heading>
<p>Study Acts 6–9 and record your impressions. This will help you receive revelation on how to help class members draw closer to Jesus Christ through their study of these chapters.</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>On the board, write the names of some of the people mentioned in Acts 6–9, such as<i>Stephen, Saul, Philip, Ananias, Peter,</i>and<i>Tabitha</i>or<i>Dorcas.</i>Invite a few class members to share something they learned from one of these people in their study this week.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>ACTS 7</heading>
<heading>Resisting the Holy Ghost can lead to rejecting the Savior and His servants.</heading>
<ul>
<li>You could begin a discussion about Stephen's experience by inviting class members to review Stephen's words in Acts 7:37–53. What warnings might his words have for us today? You might focus on Stephen's statement in Acts 7:51. What does it mean to "resist the Holy Ghost"? To understand these words more deeply, class members could discuss one or more of these: 2 Nephi 28:3–6; 33:1–2; Mosiah 2:36–37; Alma 10:5–6; and Alma 34:37–38. Why do we sometimes "resist the Holy Ghost"? What can we do to better recognize and follow the promptings of the Holy Ghost?</li>
</ul>
<heading>ACTS 8:9–24</heading>
<heading>Our hearts need to be "right in the sight of God."</heading>
<ul>
<li>To study the account of Simon as a class, you could write on the board the questions<i>Who was Simon? What did he want?</i>and<i>How did he try to get it?</i>Assign each class member to read Acts 8:9–24, looking for answers to these questions. What truths did Simon not yet understand? What can we learn from Simon's experience? How can we make sure our hearts are "right in the sight of God"? (verse 21).</li>
<li>During their personal study, some class members may have noted qualities that Stephen and Philip had that Simon did not (see this week's outline in Come Follow Me—For Individuals and Families).If so, you might invite them to share what they found. Class members could also share other examples from Acts 6–9 of people whose hearts were right before God, such as Philip and the man from Ethiopia (see Acts 8:26–40), Saul (see Acts 9:1–22), and Tabitha (see Acts 9:36–39).</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>Tabitha Arise, by Sandy Freckleton Gagon</graphics-caption>
<heading>ACTS 8:26–39</heading>
<heading>The Holy Ghost will help us guide others to Jesus Christ.</heading>
<ul>
<li>To help class members understand how they can guide others to Jesus Christ (see Acts 8:31), you might invite two class members to sit facing each other and read the dialogue of Philip and the man from Ethiopia in Acts 8:26–39. A third class member could read the parts that are not dialogue. What do we learn from Philip's example about teaching the gospel to others? To explore modern examples of the account in Acts 8:26–39, class members could share experiences they have had with sharing the gospel or with joining the Church. How did the Holy Ghost help them? How did To explore modern examples of the account in Acts 8:26–39, class members could share experiences they have had with sharing the gospel or with joining the Church. How did the Holy Ghost help them? How did someone act as their guide? Invite class members to ponder whom they might guide to the gospel.</li>
</ul>
<heading>ACTS 9</heading>
<heading>When we submit to the Lord's will, we can become instruments in His hands.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Class members can learn powerful truths about their own conversion by studying Saul's experience, including the truth that everyone can repent and change if they are willing. You might ask class members to compare Saul's experience with the experiences of Alma (see Mosiah 17:1–4; 18; 26:15–21) and of the Anti-Nephi-Lehies (see Alma 24:7–12). What did the Lord do to help these people become converted? How did they demonstrate their willingness to change? What messages do we find for our own lives from these accounts?</li>
<li>To prompt discussion about Saul's experience, you might invite a few class members to come prepared to share what they learn from each of the sections in President Dieter F. Uchtdorf's message "Waiting on the Road to Damascus" (Ensign or Liahona, May 2011, 70–77). How do we sometimes wait on our own road to Damascus? According to President Uchtdorf, what can help us better hear God's voice? You might also consider watching the video "The Road to Damascus" (ChurchofJesusChrist.org). Perhaps class members could share their experiences with seeking and following God's will.</li>
</ul>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Testify of Jesus Christ.</b>As a teacher, you can help class members build their faith in the Savior, just as Philip did for the Ethiopian man by teaching him from Isaiah (see Acts 8:26–37). To do this, you must have your own faith-building experiences in the scriptures. The witness you share can be a powerful force in helping class members strengthen their testimonies of Jesus Christ.</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<heading>JULY 17–23</heading>
<heading>Acts 10–15</heading>
<heading>"THE WORD OF GOD GREW AND MULTIPLIED"</heading>
<p>Prayerfully studying Acts 10–15 before reading this outline will help you receive impressions from the Lord. The ideas below are only suggestions.</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>Invite class members to share with someone sitting nearby something the Spirit taught them as they read Acts 10–15. Invite a few to share their insights with the whole class.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>ACTS 10; 11:1–18; 15:1–25</heading>
<heading>Heavenly Father teaches us line upon line through revelation.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Some class members might have misconceptions about the process of receiving revelation. It may help them to discuss how revelation came to Peter and how they can move forward, "doubting nothing" (Acts 10:20), when revelation seems incomplete or unclear. Consider drawing a line on the board and writing at one end of the line<i>The gospel is to be preached to the Gentiles.</i>As a class, review Acts 10 and 11:1–18, and then add points on the line that show how the Lord revealed to Peter step by step that the time had come to preach the gospel to the Gentiles. For instance, you might start with a point labeled "Cornelius saw a vision" (Acts 10:1–6) or even start with the Savior's command to His disciples to "teach all nations" in Matthew 28:19. What can we learn about revelation from Peter's experience? What do Nephi's teachings about revelation in 2 Nephi 28:30 and the teachings from Elder David A. Bednar in "Additional Resources" add to our understanding?</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>Personal revelation often comes over time through persistent effort.</graphics-caption>
<ul>
<li>You might study instances in the scriptures in which the Lord taught people line upon line. In addition to Peter's experience in Acts 10, class members could review the experiences of Nephi (1 Nephi 18:1–3); Alma (Alma 7:8; 16:20); and Mormon (3 Nephi 28:17, 36–40). What other examples can class members think of in which people received spiritual guidance "here a little and there a little"? (2 Nephi 28:30). Why might the Lord sometimes choose to reveal things in this way rather than giving us answers all at once? (see Doctrine and Covenants 50:40; 98:12).</li>
<li>Sometimes members have questions or concerns about changes in the policies and programs in the Church. It might help them to discuss how the revelation to begin preaching the gospel to the Gentiles (see Acts 10) replaced the Lord's earlier instructions to His disciples (see Matthew 10:1, 5–6). You could show the video "The Jerusalem Conference" (ChurchofJesusChrist.org). How might class members respond to someone in Peter's day who disagreed with Peter's direction because it contradicted earlier practices? How can the revelation in Acts 10 help us heed the Lord's continuing revelation through His prophet?</li>
</ul>
<heading>ACTS 10:9–48</heading>
<heading>"God is no respecter of persons."</heading>
<ul>
<li>Would your class members benefit from a discussion about what it means to be "no respecter of persons"? You might start by inviting the class to read scriptures that teach that God is not a respecter of persons, such as Romans 2:1–11; 1 Nephi 17:34–40; 2 Nephi 26:32–33; Alma 5:33; Moroni 8:12; and Doctrine and Covenants 1:34–35. Ask class members to write possible definitions of "no respecter of persons," based on what they read, and then share what they wrote. How do the events and principles in Acts 10:34–48 show that God is no respecter of persons? How can the righteous be "accepted" and "favored" by God even though He is not a respecter of persons? (see Acts 10:34–35; 1 Nephi 17:35).</li>
<li>You may need to help class members understand that being "no respecter of persons" does not mean that God blesses everyone equally regardless of our actions. He wants all of His children to accept His gospel, but the fulness of the blessings of the gospel are reserved for those who make and keep covenants with Him.</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>Receiving revelation line upon line.</heading>
<p>Elder David A. Bednar taught: "Many of us typically assume we will receive<i>an</i>answer or<i>a</i>prompting to our earnest prayers and pleadings. And we also frequently expect that such an answer or a prompting will come immediately and<i>all at once.</i>Thus, we tend to believe the Lord will give us a<b>big answer quickly and all at one time.</b>However, the pattern repeatedly described in the scriptures suggests we receive «line upon line, precept upon precept,» or in other words,<b>many small answers over a period of time.</b>Recognizing and understanding this pattern is an important key to obtaining inspiration and help from the Holy Ghost" ("Line upon Line, Precept upon Precept," New Era, Sept. 2010, 3–4).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Start with the scriptures.</b>Before turning to supplementary resources, diligently study ancient and modern scriptures. Prayerfully studying God's word will allow the Spirit to help you draw upon what you have studied as you teach. (See Teaching in the Savior's Way, 12.)</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<heading>JULY 24–30</heading>
<heading>Acts 16–21</heading>
<heading>"THE LORD HAD CALLED US FOR TO PREACH THE GOSPEL"</heading>
<p>Before looking at this outline, prayerfully read Acts 16–21 with your class members in mind. The following ideas can supplement the inspiration you receive from the Spirit.</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>Consider inviting class members to share a passage from Acts 16–21 that reminded them of an experience they had sharing the gospel.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>ACTS 16–21</heading>
<heading>As members of the Savior's Church, we testify of Him and share His gospel.</heading>
<ul>
<li>One prominent message in Acts 16–21 is the importance of the Holy Ghost in sharing the gospel. For one example, class members could read about how the Holy Ghost helped Paul and Silas in Acts 16:6–15. Why do we need the Holy Ghost when we share the gospel? (see 2 Nephi 33:1; Doctrine and Covenants 33:8–10; 42:14; 100:5–8). Perhaps class members could share experiences when the Holy Ghost guided their efforts to share the gospel.</li>
<li>How can Paul's experiences help class members have courage when they are prompted to share their testimonies? Consider asking each class member to review one of the following accounts: Acts 16:16–34; 17:16–34; 18:1–11. Ask them to share evidence they find of Paul's courage and boldness. What truths did Paul teach (and understand) that gave him confidence in his message? Why are we sometimes hesitant to share the gospel, and how does the Savior help us? Encourage class members to think of one way they can follow Paul's example and share their testimony of Christ more often (the video "I'll Go Where You Want Me to Go" [ChurchofJesusChrist.org] can help).</li>
</ul>
<heading>ACTS 17:16–34</heading>
<heading>We are the offspring of God.</heading>
<ul>
<li>On Mars' Hill, Paul taught about Heavenly Father to a group of people who knew little about God's true nature. To explore these teachings, class members could read Acts 17:24–31 and write on the board the truths they find about Heavenly Father, our relationship with Him, and our relationships with each other. They could then share experiences in which they have felt the truth of Paul's statement that God is "not far from every one of us" (verse 27).</li>
<li>As you examine these verses together, consider discussing the truth taught in verse 29: "We are the offspring of God." You could write on the board<i>Because we are children of God,</i>. . . and<i>If we did not know we are children of God,</i>. . . Invite class members to suggest ways to complete these sentences. For example, what does the fact that we are children of God teach us about ourselves and about the way we should treat each other? How would our lives be different if we did not know about our true relationship with God? What does the statement by President Dallin H. Oaks in "Additional Resources" add to this discussion?</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>Each of us is a child of God.</graphics-caption>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>We are all children of God.</heading>
<p>"The Family: A Proclamation to the World" shares eternal truths about our relationship to God: "All human beings — male and female — are created in the image of God. Each is a beloved spirit son or daughter of heavenly parents, and, as such, each has a divine nature and destiny" (ChurchofJesusChrist.org).</p>
<p>President Dallin H. Oaks spoke of the importance of seeing ourselves first and foremost as spiritual children of God:
"Be careful how you characterize yourself. Don't characterize or define yourself by some temporary quality. The only<i>single</i>quality that should characterize us is that we are a son or daughter of God. That fact transcends all other characteristics, including race, occupation, physical characteristics, honors, or even religious affiliation. . . .
"We have our agency, and we can choose any characteristic to define us. But we need to know that when we choose to define ourselves or to present ourselves by some characteristic that is temporary or trivial in eternal terms, we de-emphasize what is most important about us, and we overemphasize what is relatively unimportant. This can lead us down the wrong path and hinder our eternal progress" ("Be Wise" [Brigham Young University — Idaho devotional, Nov. 7, 2006], byui.edu).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Invite youth to be part of your lesson.</b>If you teach youth, remember that they often are able to understand the things their peers are going through. When a young person bears testimony or teaches doctrine, other youth may be touched in a way that you cannot replicate. Give youth opportunities to teach each other. (See Teaching in the Savior's Way, 28.)</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<heading>JULY 31–AUGUST 6</heading>
<heading>Acts 22–28</heading>
<heading>"A MINISTER AND A WITNESS"</heading>
<p>Read Acts 22–28 with a prayer in your heart that the Holy Ghost will inspire you to know what to focus on that will help your class members. Record any ideas that come to mind; these may be the beginning of your teaching plan.</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>Ask class members to write down a scripture reference from Acts 22–28 that impressed them this week. Gather their answers and read a few of the verses together. Invite several class members to share why these verses are meaningful to them.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>ACTS 22:1–21; 26:1–29</heading>
<heading>A testimony is a declaration of truth based on personal knowledge or belief.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Paul's testimony to Festus and King Agrippa can be an opportunity to discuss what it means to bear testimony. You could ask class members to review Acts 22:1–21 or 26:1–29. What do we learn from Paul's example about bearing testimony? What additional principles about bearing testimony do we learn from the statement by President M. Russell Ballard in "Additional Resources"? Singing or playing the hymn "Testimony" (Hymns, no. 137) could invite the Spirit into your discussion.</li>
<li>Even though Paul wasn't seeking the spiritual witness he received on the road to Damascus, he spent the rest of his life working to maintain and defend his testimony (see Acts 22:10, 14–16; 26:19). Paul's example could help your class understand that a testimony requires work and sacrifice. To start a discussion about this, perhaps a class member could describe his or her effort to become a skilled musician, artist, or athlete. How is developing such a skill similar to gaining and strengthening a testimony? What efforts must we make to gain and strengthen a testimony? (see also Alma 5:46).</li>
</ul>
<heading>ACTS 26:9–23</heading>
<heading>We have a responsibility to minister to others.</heading>
<ul>
<li>The Lord called Paul to be "a minister" (Acts 26:16), but what does this word mean? To help class members explore how they can minister to others, with or without a formal assignment, you could write on the board a question like<i>What does it mean to minister?</i>Invite class members to look for answers in the following resources: Matthew 20:25–28; Acts 26:16–18; 3 Nephi 18:29–32; Jean B. Bingham, "Ministering as the Savior Does," Ensign or Liahona, May 2018, 104–7. As they share what they find, encourage them to discuss ways we can all minister to others, including in our Church callings. You could also show the video "The Miracle of the Roof" (ChurchofJesusChrist.org).</li>
</ul>
<heading>ACTS 27</heading>
<heading>If we heed the Lord's prophets, He will guide us and protect us from evil.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Invite class members to talk about the centurion's response when Paul prophesied that the ship would suffer "much damage" and lives would be lost (see Acts 27:10–11). Why might the centurion have responded that way? Perhaps class members could share what they would have said to the centurion to help him have faith in Paul's prophecy. What other lessons can we learn from Acts 27 about following the Lord's servants? Some class members may have had experiences when they followed the direction of prophets even when it differed from the opinions of people around them. Invite a few class members to share their experiences.</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>Bearing testimony.</heading>
<p>President M. Russell Ballard spoke about Paul's testimony before King Agrippa and taught what it means for us to bear testimony:
"Our testimony meetings need to be more centered on the Savior, the doctrines of the gospel, the blessings of the Restoration, and the teachings of the scriptures. We need to replace stories, travelogues, and lectures with pure testimonies. Those who are entrusted to speak and teach in our meetings need to do so with doctrinal power that will be both heard and felt, lifting the spirits and edifying our people. . . .
". . . . While it is always good to express love and gratitude, such expressions do not constitute the kind of testimony that will ignite a fire of belief in the lives of others. To bear testimony is «to bear witness by the power of the Holy Ghost; to make a solemn declaration of truth based on personal knowledge or belief» [Guide to the Scriptures, «Testify,» scriptures.ChurchofJesusChrist.org]. Clear declaration of truth makes a difference in people's lives. That is what changes hearts. That is what the Holy Ghost can confirm in the hearts of God's children" ("Pure Testimony," Ensign or Liahona, Nov. 2004, 41).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Prepare in advance.</b>"As you ponder how the gospel principles you are teaching will bless your class members, ideas and impressions will come throughout your daily life — as you travel to work, do household chores, or interact with family and friends. Don't think of spiritual preparation as something you make time for but as something you are always doing" (Teaching in the Savior's Way, 12).</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<heading>AUGUST 7–13</heading>
<heading>Romans 1–6</heading>
<heading>"THE POWER OF GOD UNTO SALVATION"</heading>
<p>Prayerfully read Romans 1–6 with your class members in mind. This will help you be sensitive to the promptings of the Spirit as you prepare to teach.</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>Consider giving class members a few minutes to search Romans 1–6 for a verse that the Holy Ghost helped them better understand. Then they could share the verse they chose with someone sitting nearby.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>ROMANS 1:16–17</heading>
<heading>"I am not ashamed of the gospel of Christ."</heading>
<ul>
<li>Many people have had experiences in which they were ridiculed for their beliefs. To help class members when they have such experiences, you could invite them to read Romans 1:16–17 and think of instances from the book of Acts where Paul showed he was not ashamed of the gospel. Perhaps class members could also share reasons they feel unashamed of the gospel of Jesus Christ. Or they could share experiences in which they or others showed that they were not ashamed of the gospel.</li>
</ul>
<heading>ROMANS 2:28–29</heading>
<heading>True discipleship is found in our inward commitment, not just in our actions.</heading>
<heading>"Where sin abounded, grace did much more abound."</heading>
<ul>
<li>How do we evaluate our own discipleship? Paul's counsel to the Romans can help us remember to focus more on "the heart [and] the spirit" (Romans 2:29) than on outward actions. To help your class understand Paul's counsel, you could write the text from Romans 2:28–29 on the board. Replace the word Jew with Latter-day Saint and the word circumcision with the covenant. What does this change add to our understanding of Paul's teachings? You could also discuss examples of things we do as Church members that are more meaningful and powerful when done "of the heart, in the spirit" (Romans 2:29).</li>
</ul>
<heading>ROMANS 3–6</heading>
<ul>
<li>How can you help class members understand Paul's teachings about faith, works, and grace? Consider sharing the following two scenarios to help them understand that we should not see our good works as a way to prove our worthiness, nor should we see Christ's grace as a reason to excuse our mistakes and sins. Class members could search for truths in Romans 3:20–31; 5:1–2; 6:1–2, 21–23 that could help Gloria and Justin. What other truths in "Additional Resources" could help class members understand the importance of both righteous works and the grace of Christ?</li>
<li><p><b>Scenario 1</b></p>
<p>A friend named Gloria feels overwhelmed in her efforts to be a faithful disciple. She works hard to do everything she feels she should do, but she often worries that her efforts fall short. "Am I good enough?" she wonders. "Will the Lord accept me?"</p></li>
<li><p><b>Scenario 2</b></p>
<p>A friend named Justin doesn't worry too much about making righteous choices. He believes in Jesus Christ, he attends his church meetings, and he is a loving father and a good neighbor. However, he has chosen not to live the standards that would qualify him for a temple recommend. When family and friends try to encourage him to prepare for the temple, he responds, "I'm a good person. I have faith in Christ. He already paid the price for my sins, and I don't think He's going to keep me out of the celestial kingdom over such minor issues."</p></li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>Faith, grace, and works.</heading>
<heading>Scenario 1</heading>
<ul>
<li>Ether 12:27</li>
<li>Moroni 10:32–33</li>
<li>J. Devn Cornish, "Am I Good Enough? Will I Make It?," Ensign or Liahona, Nov. 2016, 32–34</li>
</ul>
<p>President Dieter F. Uchtdorf taught: "Salvation cannot be bought with the currency of obedience; it is purchased by the blood of the Son of God. Grace is a gift of God, and our desire to be obedient to each of God's commandments is the reaching out of our mortal hand to receive this sacred gift from our Heavenly Father" ("The Gift of Grace," Ensign or Liahona, May 2015, 109–10). "</p>
<heading>Scenario 2</heading>
<ul>
<li>James 2:17–26</li>
<li>Helaman 12:23–24</li>
<li>D. Todd Christofferson, "Abide in My Love," Ensign or Liahona, Nov. 2016, 48–51</li>
</ul>
<p>President Uchtdorf taught: "If grace is a gift of God, why then is obedience to God's commandments so important? Why bother with God's commandments — or repentance, for that matter?. . . Our obedience to God's commandments comes as a natural outgrowth of our endless love and gratitude for the goodness of God. This form of genuine love and gratitude will miraculously merge our works with God's grace"("The Gift of Grace," 109).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Your call is inspired.</b>As a teacher, you have been called by the Lord to bless His children. The Lord wants you to succeed, so as you live worthy of His help, He will give you the revelation you seek. (See Teaching in the Savior's Way, 5.)</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<heading>AUGUST 14–20</heading>
<heading>Romans 7–16</heading>
<heading>"OVERCOME EVIL WITH GOOD"</heading>
<p>Read Romans 7–16, and record impressions you receive about how to help class members learn from the scriptures. As you ponder your impressions, they can lead to meaningful learning activities.</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>Consider reading Romans 10:17 and 15:4 and asking class members to share scriptures from Romans 7–16 that build their faith in Jesus Christ or give them hope.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>ROMANS 8:14–18</heading>
<heading>We can become "joint-heirs with Christ."</heading>
<ul>
<li>As Latter-day Saints, we believe that phrases such as "heirs of God" and "joint-heirs with Christ" mean that with Jesus Christ's help, we can become like Heavenly Father and receive all He has (Romans 8:17; see also Doctrine and Covenants 132:20–21). To help class members see how this doctrine is taught throughout the scriptures, you could invite them to form pairs or small groups and study some of the scriptures listed in "Additional Resources." Then class members could share what they have learned and discuss why this doctrine is so important.</li>
<li>The analogy given by President Dallin H. Oaks in "Additional Resources" could help class members discuss how we can prepare to become "heirs of God" (Romans 8:17). What are some of the "laws and principles" President Oaks referred to? What difference does it make in our lives to know that we can become "heirs of God, and joint-heirs with Christ"? (Romans 8:17).</li>
</ul>
<heading>ROMANS 8:18, 28, 31–39</heading>
<heading>"Who shall separate us from the love of Christ?"</heading>
<ul>
<li>Discussing 8 together could provide an opportunity to help class members feel the Savior's love. Consider displaying a picture of Jesus Christ (see this week's outline in Come, Follow Me—For Individuals and Families) while you read Romans 8:18, 28, 31–39 as a class. You could invite class members to share any thoughts or feelings they have after reading these verses. Some might be willing to share how they have gained testimonies of the truths they find in these verses.</li>
</ul>
<heading>ROMANS 13:8–10</heading>
<heading>All of God's commandments are fulfilled in the commandment to love.</heading>
<ul>
<li>To help class members see how all commandments are "briefly comprehended in" the commandment to "love thy neighbour" (Romans 13:9), invite them to make a list on the board of all the commandments they can think of. Read together Romans 13:8–10 and Matthew 22:36–40, and discuss as a class the relationship between loving God and our neighbor and obeying each of the commandments listed on the board. How does this truth change the way we think about commandments and obedience? For example, what does this truth suggest about the purpose of commandments?</li>
</ul>
<heading>ROMANS 14</heading>
<heading>"Let us not. . . judge one another."</heading>
<ul>
<li>To give some context to Romans 14, you might point out that some of the Roman Saints disputed with each other about cultural practices, like eating habits and holiday observances. What similar situations do we face today? Perhaps class members could scan Romans 14 and give a one-sentence summary of Paul's counsel. What advice can we share with each other about how to avoid being judgmental? Perhaps class members can find ideas in President Dieter F. Uchtdorf's message "The Merciful Obtain Mercy," Ensign or Liahona, May 2012, 70–77.</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>Receiving "all that [the] Father hath" (Doctrine and Covenants 84:38).</heading>
<ul>
<li>Luke 12:42–44</li>
<li>Romans 8:14–18, 32</li>
<li>2 Corinthians 3:18</li>
<li>Galatians 4:1–7</li>
<li>Revelation 3:21</li>
<li>Revelation 21:7</li>
<li>3 Nephi 28:10</li>
<li>Doctrine and Covenants 50:26–28</li>
<li>Doctrine and Covenants 76:92–95</li>
<li>Doctrine and Covenants 84:38</li>
<li>Doctrine and Covenants 88:107</li>
<li>Doctrine and Covenants 132:19–20</li>
<li>"Becoming Like God" (Gospel Topics, topics.ChurchofJesusChrist.org)</li>
</ul>
<p>President Dallin H. Oaks related the following parable:
"A wealthy father knew that if he were to bestow his wealth upon child who had not yet developed the needed wisdom and stature, the inheritance would probably be wasted. The father said to his child: 
"All that I have I desire to give you — not only my wealth, but also my position and standing among men. That which I have I can easily give you, but that which I am you must obtain for yourself. You will qualify for your inheritance by learning what I have learned and by living as I have lived. I will give you the laws and principles by which I have acquired my wisdom and stature. Follow my example, mastering as I have mastered, and you will become as I am, and all that I have will be yours'" ("The Challenge to Become," Ensign, Nov. 2000, 32).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Find resources to support the principles.</b>In addition to the teaching ideas in this outline, you could modify activities from this week's outline in Come, Follow Me—For Individuals and Families to use in your class. (See also Teaching in the Savior's Way, 17–18.)</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<graphics-caption>Corinth, Southern Greece, the Forum and Civic Center, painting by Balage Balogh</graphics-caption>
<graphics-caption>https/www.Archaeologylllustrated.com</graphics-caption>
<heading>AUGUST 21–27</heading>
<heading>1 Corinthians 1–7</heading>
<heading>"BE PERFECTLY JOINED TOGETHER"</heading>
<p>Elder Jeffrey R. Holland taught that most people "come [to church] seeking a spiritual experience" ("A Teacher Come from God," Ensign, May 1998, 26). As you read 1 Corinthians 1–7, prayerfully consider what you can do to help create spiritual experiences in your class.</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>Consider inviting class members to write down how they have acted on what they are learning from the scriptures. Ask a few class members to share what they wrote.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>1 CORINTHIANS 1:10–17; 3</heading>
<heading>The members of Christ's Church strive to be united.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Discussing the first few chapters of 1 Corinthians may be an opportunity to build greater unity among ward members. You could start by asking class members to talk about a club, group, team, or other organization they belonged to that had a great sense of unity. Why did this group feel so united? You could then explore some of Paul's teachings on unity in 1 Corinthians 1:10–13; 3:1–11. What do these verses, along with our experiences, teach about what helps create unity and what threatens it? What sacrifices do we have to make in order to achieve unity? What blessings come to those who are united? See also Sister Sharon Eubank's analogy in "Additional Resources."</li>
<li>Paul uses the image of a building to encourage unity in 1 Corinthians 3:9–17. How could this analogy help your class better understand unity? For example, after reading these verses together, you could give each class member a block and let them work together to build something. In what sense are we "God's building"? (1 Corinthians 3:9). How is God building us individually? What are we building together as fellow Saints? What can we do as a unified ward that we wouldn't be able to do as individuals?</li>
</ul>
<heading>1 CORINTHIANS 1:17–31; 2; 3:18–20</heading>
<heading>To accomplish God's work, we need the wisdom of God.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Here's an idea to help your class rely on God: Divide class members into groups and ask them to scan 1 Corinthians 1:17–31; 2; or 3:18–20 searching for words like wise and foolish. Then they could share in their groups what these verses teach about being wise in the Lord's work. What are things about the gospel that might seem foolish to some people? How do these things demonstrate the wisdom of God? Perhaps class members could also share experiences in which they trusted in God's wisdom, rather than their own, to accomplish His work.</li>
</ul>
<heading>1 CORINTHIANS 6:9–20</heading>
<heading>Our physical bodies are sacred.</heading>
<ul>
<li>To begin a discussion about these verses, you might write on the board questions like the following:<i>How does the Lord want us to view our bodies? How is this different from the way Satan wants us to think of our bodies? What does it mean that our bodies are temples of the Holy Ghost?</i>Invite class members to find answers to these questions in 1 Corinthians 6:9–20 (see also Doctrine and Covenants 88:15; Moses 6:8–9).</li>
<li>Your discussion about the sanctity of our bodies could include a conversation about the law of chastity. Perhaps you could ask your class members what they learn from Paul — as well as from other Church resources — that could help them explain to others why chastity is important. Some of these resources may include those listed in "Additional Resources."</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>"Differences can be turned to advantage."</heading>
<p>Sister Sharon Eubank described how competitive rowing teams achieve unity:
"Rowers must rein in their fierce independence and at the same time hold true to their individual capabilities. Races are not won by clones. Good crews are good blends — someone to lead the charge, someone to hold something in reserve, someone to fight the fight, someone to make peace. No rower is more valuable than another, all are assets to the boat, but if they are to row well together, each must adjust to the needs and capabilities of the others — the shorter-armed person reaching a little farther, the longer-armed person pulling in just a bit.
"Differences can be turned to advantage instead of disadvantage" ("By Union of Feeling We Obtain Power with God," Ensign or Liahona, Nov. 2020, 56; see Daniel James Brown, The Boys in the Boat: Nine Americans and Their Epic Quest for Gold at the 1936 Berlin Olympics [2013], 161, 179).</p>
<heading>The blessings of sexual purity.</heading>
<p>Jeffrey R. Holland, "Personal Purity," Ensign, Nov. 1998, 76.</p>
<p>David A. Bednar, "We Believe in Being Chaste," Ensign or Liahona, May 2013, 42.</p>
<p>"Chastity: What Are the Limits?," "I Choose to Be Pure" (videos), ChurchofJesusChrist.org</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Bear testimony of Jesus Christ.</b>Paul "came not with excellency of speech or of wisdom, declaring . . . the testimony of God" (1 Corinthians 2:1). Your simple testimony of the Savior can have a profound influence.</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<heading>AUGUST 28–SEPTEMBER 3</heading>
<heading>1 Corinthians 8–13</heading>
<heading>"YE ARE THE BODY OF CHRIST"</heading>
<p>Elder Richard G. Scott taught that we "can leave the most precious, personal direction of the Spirit unheard" if we do not record and respond to "the first promptings that come to [us]" ("To Acquire Spiritual Guidance," Ensign or Liahona, Nov. 2009, 8).</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>In 1 Corinthians 8–13, Paul taught gospel truths using metaphors such as a runner in a race, the human body, and "a tinkling cymbal" (see 1 Corinthians 9:24–25; 12:13–26; 13:1). You might ask class members what they learned from these comparisons. How do the comparisons help us understand gospel truths?</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>1 CORINTHIANS 10:1–13</heading>
<heading>God provides a way to escape temptation.</heading>
<ul>
<li>How can you help class members discover powerful truths in 1 Corinthians 10:13? One idea is to divide the verse into brief phrases, give each one to a different class member, and ask the class members to restate the phrases in their own words. For example, what is another way to say "God is faithful" or "tempted above that ye are able"? You could then reread the verse, using some of the class members' statements. Class members may be able to share experiences in which they found the promises in this verse to be true. What additional insights can we gain into these verses from Alma 13:27–28?</li>
<li>Rather than dwelling on anyone's specific temptations, you might want to focus the discussion of 1 Corinthians 10:13 on temptations that are, in Paul's words, "common to man." Class members could start by identifying temptations Paul warns against in verses 1–12. They might also suggest modern examples of common temptations, such as temptations to be dishonest, gossip, or judge others. How might a person, with God's help, "escape" these temptations?</li>
</ul>
<heading>1 CORINTHIANS 10:16–17; 11:23–30</heading>
<heading>The sacrament unifies us as members of Christ's Church.</heading>
<ul>
<li>These verses could inspire a discussion about how the sacrament can unify your ward in your efforts to become more like the Savior. You might begin by reading 1 Corinthians 10:16–17 and exploring what the word<i>communion</i>could mean in this context (someone could look for possible definitions in a dictionary). How can partaking of the sacrament together help us feel more united? How does Paul's counsel to "let a man examine himself" relate to this goal? (1 Corinthians 11:28).</li>
</ul>
<heading>1 CORINTHIANS 12</heading>
<heading>Spiritual gifts are given to benefit all of Heavenly Father's children.</heading>
<ul>
<li>To help class members see examples of how developing their spiritual gifts helps edify the Church, consider inviting them to think of spiritual gifts people in the scriptures had. For ideas, you could assign them to search one of the scripture references in "Additional Resources" and name the spiritual gifts they think that person had. They could also talk about spiritual gifts they see in each other. How are these people's spiritual gifts a blessing to all of us? How can we use our spiritual gifts to bless others and edify the body of Christ, or the Church? (see 1 Corinthians 12:12–31; see also 1 Corinthians 14:12).</li>
<li>To help class members understand how to develop spiritual gifts, invite them to read 1 Corinthians 12:27–31; Moroni 7:48; 10:23, 30; Doctrine and Covenants 46:8. What do these scriptures teach us about how to obtain spiritual gifts? How does developing spiritual gifts make us more like Christ? Invite class members to select a gift they would like to obtain and to seek the Lord's help in acquiring that gift.</li>
</ul>
<heading>1 CORINTHIANS 13</heading>
<heading>Charity is the greatest spiritual gift.</heading>
<ul>
<li>You might ask class members to silently ponder 1 Corinthians 13 and think of someone they know who is a good example of one or more aspects of charity that Paul mentions. Some class members could describe the person they thought of and an experience in which this person exemplified charity. You might even list parts of Paul's description on the board and invite class members to share ideas about what it means that a person with charity "suffereth long" or "is not easily provoked" (1 Corinthians 13:4–5). How did the Savior exemplify these attributes of charity? What additional truths does Moroni 7:46–48 teach about charity?</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>Scriptural examples of spiritual gifts.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Genesis 40–41</li>
<li>Ruth 1</li>
<li>Kings 3:5–15</li>
<li>Matthew 1:18–24; 2:13–15, 19–22</li>
<li>Luke 1:26–38</li>
<li>John 11:20–27</li>
<li>Acts 3:1–8; 5:12–16</li>
<li>Mormon 1:1–5</li>
<li>Ether 2:14–25; 3:1–20</li>
<li>Doctrine and Covenants 6:5, 10–12</li>
<li>Moses 6:22–27, 31–43; 7:2–4, 13, 17–21</li>
</ul>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Live the principles you teach.</b>Living the principles you are teaching will help you bear witness of them more powerfully. Paul taught, "Even so hath the Lord ordained that they which preach the gospel should live of the gospel" (1 Corinthians 9:14).</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<heading>SEPTEMBER 4–10</heading>
<heading>Corinthians 14–16</heading>
<heading>"GOD IS NOT THE AUTHOR OF CONFUSION, BUT OF PEACE"</heading>
<p>Before reviewing this outline, read 1 Corinthians 14–16. Record your initial impressions about what truths will help your class members, and continually seek additional guidance from the Spirit as you prepare to teach.</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>Provide a few minutes for class members to review 1 Corinthians 14–16 and find a verse they feel is especially meaningful. Invite them to find someone in the class with whom they can share their verse and explain why they chose it.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>1 CORINTHIANS 14</heading>
<heading>When we gather together, we should seek to edify one another.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Consider using Paul's teachings in 1 Corinthians 14 to remind class members that we can all edify or support and uplift each other at church. A simple way to review this chapter might be to write a question on the board, such as<i>What should be our goal when we gather together?</i>Invite class members to search for possible answers in 1 Corinthians 14. Other ideas could be found in Moroni 6:4–5 and Doctrine and Covenants 50:17–23. As class members share what they find, consider asking them how they feel your class is doing at accomplishing these goals. They could also share experiences in which they felt edified by something a class member shared.</li>
</ul>
<heading>1 CORINTHIANS 15</heading>
<heading>Because Jesus Christ was resurrected, we will all be resurrected.</heading>
<ul>
<li>How can you use Paul's testimony in 1 Corinthians 15 to strengthen your class members' testimonies of the Resurrection? One way could be to divide the class into two groups and ask one group to look in 1 Corinthians 15 for the consequences we would face if Jesus Christ had not been resurrected. The other group could look for the blessings we receive because of His Resurrection. Each group could then write on the board what they learned. What could they add to their lists after reading the statement by Elder D. Todd Christofferson in "Additional Resources"? To help class members feel the Spirit during this discussion, consider displaying a picture of the resurrected Savior (see this week's outline in Come, Follow Me—For Individuals and Families) or playing or singing a hymn about the Resurrection.</li>
<li>Because Paul was responding to people who did not believe in resurrection, your class might benefit from role-playing a similar situation. For example, how might they strengthen a loved one's faith in the Resurrection? What do we find in 1 Corinthians 15 that would help us explain the need for and the evidence of the Resurrection of Jesus Christ? What other scriptures could we use? (See, for example, Luke 24:1–12, 36–46; Alma 11:42–45.)</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>Paul taught about the Resurrection by referring to "celestial bodies" like the sun (1 Corinthians 15:40).</graphics-caption>
<ul>
<li>1 Corinthians 15 is one of the few places in the scriptures where baptisms for the dead are mentioned (see verse 29; see also Doctrine and Covenants 128:18). Perhaps class members could share the joy they have experienced while performing baptisms or other ordinances for their ancestors. Why might Paul have referred to baptisms for the dead as evidence of the Resurrection? If it would help to discuss why baptisms for the dead are necessary, see the Gospel Topics article "Baptisms for the Dead" (topics.ChurchofJesusChrist.org). The video "Glad Tidings: The History of Baptisms for the Dead" (ChurchofJesusChrist.org) explains how this principle was restored in our day.</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>Significance of the Resurrection.</heading>
<p>Elder D. Todd Christofferson taught:
"Consider for a moment the significance of the Resurrection in resolving once and for all the true identity of Jesus of Nazareth and the great philosophical contests and questions of life. If Jesus was in fact literally resurrected, it necessarily follows that He is a divine being. No mere mortal has the power in himself to come to life again after dying. Because He was resurrected, Jesus cannot have been only a carpenter, a teacher, a rabbi, or a prophet. Because He was resurrected, Jesus had to have been a God, even the Only Begotten Son of the Father.
"Therefore, what He taught is true; God cannot lie.
"Therefore, He was the Creator of the earth, as He said.
"Therefore, heaven and hell are real, as He taught.
"Therefore, there is a world of spirits, which He visited after His death.
"Therefore, He will come again, as the angels said, and «reign personally upon the earth.»
"Therefore, there is a resurrection and a final judgment for all" ("The Resurrection of Jesus Christ," Ensign or Liahona, May 2014, 113).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Get to know those you teach.</b>No two people are exactly alike; each person you teach has a unique background, perspective, and set of talents. Pray to know how you can use these to engage your learners. As you better understand those you teach, you can create meaningful and memorable teaching moments for them (see Teaching in the Savior's Way, 7).</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<heading>SEPTEMBER 11–17</heading>
<heading>2 Corinthians 1–7</heading>
<heading>"BE YE RECONCILED TO GOD"</heading>
<p>As you read 2 Corinthians 1–7 this week, think about specific class members — those who come to class and those who don't. How could the principles in these chapters bless them?</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>Class members can benefit from hearing ideas from each other about how to make their scripture study more effective. Provide a few minutes for this from time to time.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>2 CORINTHIANS 1:3–7; 4:6–10, 17–18; 7:4–7</heading>
<heading>Our trials can be a blessing.</heading>
<ul>
<li>The experiences Paul described and the counsel in 2 Corinthians can help class members think about the blessings that can come from their trials. To start a discussion, you might ask a class member to come prepared to talk about how a trial blessed his or her life or what he or she learned from someone else who endured a trial. Then you I could give class members a few minutes to review 2 Corinthians 1:3–7; 4:6–10, 17–18; and 7:4–7, looking for what Paul taught about the purposes and blessings of trials. Ask class members to share what they find. You might suggest that they read aloud the verse in which they found a particular teaching and then share an experience or testimony related to that teaching.</li>
<li>To add to your discussion, consider singing together class members' favorite hymns that testify of the comfort and blessings Heavenly Father and the Savior offer us in times of trial — such as "How Firm a Foundation" (Hymns, no. 85). After singing together, you might invite class members to look for a phrase in 2 Corinthians 1 and 4 that they feel fits the message of the hymn.</li>
</ul>
<heading>2 CORINTHIANS 2:5–11</heading>
<heading>Forgiveness is a blessing we both give and receive.</heading>
<ul>
<li>We've all had experiences when someone has "caused grief" for us or our family (verse 5). Perhaps class members could search 2 Corinthians 2:5–11, looking for counsel from Paul about how we should treat someone who has offended us. Consider inviting class members to review Matthew 5:43–48 and Luke 15:11–32 to learn more about how we should treat those who have offended us. How do we harm ourselves and others when we choose not to forgive?</li>
</ul>
<heading>2 CORINTHIANS 5:14–21</heading>
<heading>Through the Atonement of Jesus Christ, we can be reconciled to God.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Many people come to church with a desire to feel closer to God, and a discussion of 2 Corinthians 5:14–21 can help them. To begin, class members could explore the meaning of the word<i>reconcile,</i>perhaps beginning by looking up the word in a dictionary. What insights does this provide about being reconciled with God? What additional insights do we gain from the entry "Atonement" in the Bible Dictionary? How do these insights help us understand 2 Corinthians 5:14–21? You may want to invite class members to share their feelings about the Savior, whose Atonement makes it possible for us to be reunited with God.</li>
</ul>
<heading>2 CORINTHIANS 7:8–11</heading>
<heading>Godly sorrow leads to repentance.</heading>
<ul>
<li>2 Corinthians 7:8–11 gives a helpful explanation of godly sorrow and its role in repentance. What do we learn about godly sorrow from 2 Corinthians 7:8–11 and President Dieter F. Uchtdorf's words in "Additional Resources"? Why is godly sorrow essential to repentance?</li>
<li>You might feel impressed to encourage a broader discussion about repentance. If so, you could try something like this: Write on the board<i>Repentance is __.</i>Ask class members to find ways to complete this phrase, using things they learn from 2 Corinthians 7:8–11, as well as from the scriptures and other resources found in the Gospel Topics article "Repentance" (topics.ChurchofJesusChrist.org). How might we use these teachings to help someone understand how to sincerely repent?</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>Godly sorrow inspires change and hope.</heading>
<p>President Dieter F. Uchtdorf explained:
"<i>Godly sorrow</i>inspires change and hope through the Atonement of Jesus Christ.<i>Worldly sorrow</i>pulls us down, extinguishes hope, and persuades us to give in to further temptation.
"<i>Godly sorrow</i>leads to conversion and a change of heart. It causes us to hate sin and love goodness. It encourages us to stand up and walk in the light of Christ's love. True repentance is about transformation, not torture or torment" ("You Can Do It Now!," Ensign or Liahona, Nov. 2013, 56).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Include those who are struggling.</b>Sometimes struggling class members just need to be included to feel loved. Consider giving them an assignment to participate in an upcoming lesson.Don't give up if they don't respond to your efforts at first. (See Teaching in the Savior's Way, 8–9.)</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<heading>SEPTEMBER 18–24</heading>
<heading>2 Corinthians 8–13</heading>
<heading>"GOD LOVETH A CHEERFUL GIVER"</heading>
<p>As you read 2 Corinthians 8–13, think about the people you teach, and plan activities that would help them discover the principles in these chapters. Then review this outline for additional ideas.</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>Here is one way to invite class members to share what they learned from 2 Corinthians 8–13: ask a few of them to write on the board a favorite phrase from their reading and share why these phrases are meaningful to them.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>2 CORINTHIANS 8:1–15; 9:6–15</heading>
<heading>Saints cheerfully share what they have to bless the poor and needy.</heading>
<ul>
<li>God has commanded His Saints to help take care of those in need, and passages in 2 Corinthians 8–9 can inspire your class members in their efforts. To help them find these passages, you could write on the board questions like<i>Why do we give?</i>and<i>How should we give?</i>Half of the class could search for answers in 2 Corinthians 8:1–15, and the other half could search in 2 Corinthians 9:6–15. (You might explain that in chapter 8, verses 1–5, Paul spoke of the Macedonian Saints as examples of generous giving.) How might the principles taught by Paul help us better care for the poor and needy?</li>
</ul>
<heading>2 CORINTHIANS 11:1–4</heading>
<heading>We should focus on "the simplicity that is in Christ."</heading>
<ul>
<li>Sometimes Church members feel overwhelmed with the demands of life — including what they might see as the demands of being a Latter-day Saint. Paul's counsel about "the simplicity that is in Christ" (2 Corinthians 11:3) can help. Perhaps you could read together 2 Corinthians 11:3 and discuss what the phrase "simplicity that is in Christ" might mean. You could also ask class members to imagine that they were invited to write a description of the gospel of Jesus Christ for a newspaper, with a limit of 100 words. Give them time to write their descriptions, and let them share with each other what they wrote. If they need help, they might refer to John 3:16–17; 3 Nephi 27:13–21; President Dieter F. Uchtdorf's statement in "Additional Resources." Class members could share ideas about how to "simplify [our] approach to discipleship."</li>
</ul>
<heading>2 CORINTHIANS 12:5–10</heading>
<heading>The Savior's grace is sufficient to help us find strength in our weakness.</heading>
<ul>
<li>What would you say to a friend who has prayed for relief from an infirmity but feels that this prayer is not being answered? Consider inviting class members to ponder this question as they silently read 2 Corinthians 12:5–10. Then they could share insights from these verses that might help in this situation. They could also share experiences when, through Jesus Christ's grace, or His divine power and help, they found strength in weakness. How did that experience influence their lives? Why is it important to trust the Lord's timing?</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>We can simplify our approach to living the gospel.</heading>
<p>President Dieter F. Uchtdorf taught:
"Brothers and sisters, living the gospel doesn't need to be complicated.
"It is really straightforward. It could be described like this: 
<ul>
<li>Hearing the word of God with earnest intent leads us to believe in God and to trust His promises.</li>
<li>The more we trust God, the more our hearts are filled with love for Him and for each other.</li>
<li>Because of our love for God, we desire to follow Him and bring our actions in alignment with His word.</li>
<li>Because we love God, we want to serve Him; we want to bless the lives of others and help the poor and the needy.</li>
<li>The more we walk in this path of discipleship, the more we desire to learn the word of God.</li>
</ul>
"And so it goes, each step leading to the next and filling us with ever-increasing faith, hope, and charity.
"It is beautifully simple, and it works beautifully.
"Brothers and sisters, if you ever think that the I gospel isn't working so well for invite you to you, step back, look at your life from a higher plane, and simplify your approach to discipleship. Focus on the basic doctrines, principles, and applications of the gospel. I promise that God will guide and bless you on your path to a fulfilling life, and the gospel will definitely work better for you" ("It Works Wonderfully!," Ensign or Liahona, Nov. 2015, 22).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Work together with family members.</b>"The people who have the most powerful influence on an individual — for good or ill — are usually those in his or her home. Because the home is the center of gospel living and learning, your efforts to strengthen a class member will be most effective when you work together with . . . family members" (Teaching in the Savior's Way, 8).</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<graphics-caption>The resurrected Savior visited Paul in prison (see Acts 23:11). Jesus Christ can free us from the "yoke of bondage" (Galatians 5:1).</graphics-caption>
<heading>SEPTEMBER 25–OCTOBER 1</heading>
<heading>Galatians</heading>
<heading>"WALK IN THE SPIRIT"</heading>
<p>As you prayerfully read and ponder Galatians, the Lord will teach you what you need to share with your class. Recording your impressions shows gratitude to God for His help.</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>Scripture study often leads to meaningful gospel discussions with family or friends. Did this happen for members of your class this week? Invite them to share their experiences.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>GALATIANS 1:6–7; 3:1–5; 4:8–21; 5:1, 13–14</heading>
<heading>The gospel of Jesus Christ offers liberty.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Studying any book of scripture is easier when we know why it was written. For this reason, it might be good to begin your discussion about Galatians with a question like "What do you think Paul's purpose was in writing this epistle?" or "What problem was Paul trying to solve?" Invite class members to look for clues in Galatians 1:6–7; 3:1–5; 4:8–21. How is Paul's message relevant to us today?</li>
<li>Some Galatian Saints thought they needed to continue living the law of Moses. To Paul, this was like living with a "yoke of bondage" compared to the "liberty" that Jesus Christ offers us (Galatians 5:1). To help members of your class explore Paul's teachings about freedom and bondage, you could ask them to name attitudes and actions that limit our spiritual growth and progress (such as cultural practices, bad habits, false beliefs, or focusing on outward actions rather than inward conversion). According to Galatians 5:1, 13–14, how do we find freedom from these attitudes and actions? How have we experienced the liberty found through Jesus Christ? How could we respond to someone who feels that living the gospel limits personal freedom?</li>
</ul>
<heading>GALATIANS 5:16–26</heading>
<heading>If we "walk in the Spirit," we will receive the "fruit of the Spirit."</heading>
<ul>
<li>Many people struggle to recognize the influence of the Spirit. Galatians 5 can help. Maybe you could ask class members to search Galatians 5:22–25 to find the words Paul used to describe the fruit of the Spirit. Why is fruit a good metaphor for the way the Spirit influences us? Perhaps class members could share how this fruit has been evident in their lives or the lives of people they know. Some other resources to explore include Matthew 7:16–18; John 14:26–27; Moroni 7:13–17; Doctrine and Covenants 11:12–13; and President Gordon B. Hinckley's words in "Additional Resources."</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>We can receive the "fruit of the Spirit" as we seek it.</graphics-caption>
<heading>GALATIANS 6:7–10</heading>
<heading>When we sow "to the Spirit," we will reap blessings in due time.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Studying Galatians 6:7–10 could help class members think more deeply about the long-term consequences of their choices. To help them, you could bring seeds of various kinds, along with plants, fruits, or vegetables that grow from each of these seeds (or you could bring pictures of these things). Class members could work together to match each seed with the thing it produces. Then they could read verses 7–10 and talk about what it means to sow "to [the] flesh" and "to the Spirit." (The message from Elder Ulisses Soares in "Additional Resources" might help.) What do we reap when we sow to the flesh? What do we reap when we sow to the Spirit? (see Galatians 5:22–23).</li>
<li>Some class members may feel "weary in well doing" (Galatians 6:9) — perhaps because they aren't sure their efforts are bearing fruit. A discussion of Galatians 6:7–10 might be helpful. To introduce these verses, you could invite someone in the class to talk briefly about a time when he or she needed patience when trying to grow something. What could this person's experience, along with Galatians 6:7–10, teach us about our efforts to "walk in the Spirit"? (Galatians 5:25).</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>The fruit of the Spirit.</heading>
<ul>
<li>President Gordon B. Hinckley taught: "You recognize the promptings of the Spirit by the fruits of the Spirit — that which enlighteneth, that which buildeth up, that which is positive and affirmative and uplifting and leads us to better thoughts and better words and better deeds is of the Spirit of God" (Teachings of Presidents of the Church: Gordon B. Hinckley [2016], 121).</li>
</ul>
<heading>Sowing in the Spirit.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Elder Ulisses Soares explained: "To sow in the Spirit means that all our thoughts, words, and actions must elevate us to the level of the divinity of our heavenly parents. However, the scriptures refer to the flesh as the physical or carnal nature of the natural man, which allows people to be influenced by passion, desires, appetites, and drives of the flesh instead of looking for inspiration from the Holy Ghost" ("Abide in the Lord's Territory!," Ensign or Liahona, May 2012, 39).</li>
</ul>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Help learners lift each other.</b>"Each individual in your class is a rich source of testimony, insights, and experiences with living the gospel. Invite them to share with and lift each other" (Teaching in the Savior's Way, 5).</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<heading>OCTOBER 2–8</heading>
<heading>Ephesians</heading>
<heading>"FOR THE PERFECTING OF THE SAINTS"</heading>
<p>Thoughts and impressions about what and how to teach will come as you prayerfully study Ephesians, recent general conference addresses, this outline, and<i>Come, Follow Me—For Individuals and Families.</i></p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>Consider inviting class members to write on the board a one-sentence summary of something they learned in their study this week. Randomly select a few summaries, and invite the class members who wrote them to share their thoughts.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>EPHESIANS 2:19–22; 4:4–8, 11–16</heading>
<heading>Prophets and apostles — and all of us — strengthen and unify the Church.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Could you and your class build something together to illustrate how the Church is "built upon the foundation of the apostles and prophets" and how the Savior is "the chief corner stone"? (Ephesians 2:20). Perhaps class members could label blocks or paper cups and assemble them into a tower or pyramid, with Jesus Christ and the apostles and prophets forming the base. Then you could demonstrate what would happen if Christ or the apostles and prophets were removed. Why is the chief cornerstone a good metaphor for Jesus Christ and His role in the Church? (For a description of a chief cornerstone, see "Additional Resources.") Class members could search Ephesians 2:19–22; 4:11–16 for blessings we receive because of apostles, prophets, and other Church leaders. What can we do to build our lives on their teachings?</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>Jesus Christ is the cornerstone of the Church.</graphics-caption>
<ul>
<li>If members of your class listened to general conference since the last time you met, invite them to share how the things taught during conference helped fulfill the purposes stated in Ephesians 4:11–16.</li>
<li>Perhaps you could give class members a moment to list some of the "vocations" or responsibilities we have as members of Christ's Church (see Ephesians 4:1) — for example, a ministering brother or sister, a righteous parent, a disciple of Christ, and so on. Then they could exchange lists with another class member, read Ephesians 4:4–8, 11–16, and share how fulfilling the responsibilities on their lists helps to edify the body of Christ. How can we work together to become unified under "one Lord, one faith, one baptism"?</li>
</ul>
<heading>EPHESIANS 5:25–6:4</heading>
<heading>Following the Savior's example can strengthen our family relationships.</heading>
<ul>
<li>To help class members apply Paul's counsel about family relationships, you might write questions like the following on the board:<i>How can we follow the Savior's example in the way we treat our family members? (see Ephesians 5:25). What does it mean to you to "honour thy father and mother"? (Ephesians 6:1–3). How do we raise children in "the nurture and admonition of the Lord"? (Ephesians 6:4).</i>Class members could discuss these questions, in groups or as a class, as they read the associated scriptures. You might invite class members to share examples they have seen of people living in the ways that Paul describes.</li>
</ul>
<heading>EPHESIANS 6:10–18</heading>
<heading>The armor of God will help protect us from evil.</heading>
<ul>
<li>What would help inspire class members to strive to put on the whole armor of God each day? You could prepare an activity in which class members match pieces of armor with the principles or virtues they represent, as described in Ephesians 6:14–17. How can each piece of armor help protect us from wickedness? (For some help, see "Additional Resources.") How do we put on this armor? What can we do to identify and strengthen any weaknesses in our armor?</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>What is a chief cornerstone?</heading>
<p>The chief cornerstone is the first stone placed in a foundation. It serves as a reference point for the measurement and placement of the other stones, which must be aligned with the chief cornerstone. Because it bears the weight of the rest of the building, the chief cornerstone must be solid, stable, and reliable (see "The Cornerstone," Ensign, Jan. 2016, 74–75).</p>
<heading>The armor of God.</heading>
<ul>
<li><b>Loins girt about with truth:</b>This piece of armor is like a belt tied around the waist. The word girt can also mean fortified, strengthened, or reinforced.</li>
<li><b>Breastplate of righteousness:</b>A breastplate protects the heart and other vital organs.</li>
<li><b>Feet shod with the preparation of the gospel of peace:</b>This refers to protective covering for a soldier's feet.</li>
<li><b>Shield of faith:</b>A shield can protect almost any part of the body from a variety of attacks.</li>
<li><b>Helmet of salvation:</b>A helmet protects the head.</li>
<li><b>Sword of the Spirit:</b>A sword allows us to take action against the enemy.</li>
</ul>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Strive for Christlike love.</b>Your interactions with those you teach should be motivated by love. You and your learners will be blessed as you pray to develop Christlike love and seek ways to show it (see Teaching in the Savior's Way, 6; Moroni 7:48).</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<heading>OCTOBER 9–15</heading>
<heading>Philippians; Colossians</heading>
<heading>"I CAN DO ALL THINGS THROUGH CHRIST WHICH STRENGTHENETH ME"</heading>
<p>Begin by reading Philippians and Colossians, and prayerfully ponder the doctrine the Lord wants you to teach. Let the Spirit guide you as you consider the questions and resources you could use to teach this doctrine.</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>Invite class members to share one word or phrase that summarizes what they learned from Philippians and Colossians and to then explain why they chose that word or phrase. Encourage them to share scripture verses as part of their explanation.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>PHILIPPIANS 2:1–5, 14–18; 4:1–9; COLOSSIANS 3:1–17</heading>
<heading>We become "new" as we live the gospel of Jesus Christ.</heading>
<ul>
<li>You may want to help your class members visualize what it means to "put off the old man" and "put on the new man" through Jesus Christ (Colossians 3:9–10). To do this, you might display before and after pictures of something old that has been transformed into something new (such as a piece of furniture, a home, or a bike). Class members could discuss how we become "new" through our faith in Jesus Christ and our willingness to live His gospel. As part of this discussion, you could ask half of the class to study Philippians 2:1–5, 14–18; 4:1–9 and the other half to study Colossians 3:1–17, identifying characteristics of the "old man" and the "new man." You could also invite a few class members to share how having faith in Jesus Christ and living His gospel have helped them become new people.</li>
</ul>
<heading>PHILIPPIANS 4:1–13</heading>
<heading>We can find joy in Christ, regardless of our circumstances.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Even though our circumstances are different from Paul's, we can all learn from his willingness to be content and to rejoice in all the circumstances of his life. To begin a discussion on this topic, you could review some of the trials Paul experienced (see, for example, 2 Corinthians 11:23–28). You could then ask class members to review Philippians 4:1–13 to find counsel Paul gave that can help us rejoice, even in times of trial.</li>
<li>Perhaps class members could share experiences when they felt "the peace of God, which passeth all understanding" (Philippians 4:7) or when they felt strengthened "through Christ" (verse 13) to accomplish something they could not have done otherwise.</li>
<li>If you would like to explore this topic further, you might ask a class member to share some inspiring accounts or statements from President Russell M. Nelson's talk "Joy and Spiritual Survival" (Ensign or Liahona, Nov. 2016, 81–84). Or the class could watch the video "Trial of Adversity" (ChurchofJesusChrist.org). How did the people in President Nelson's talk or the woman in the video find joy, despite their difficult circumstances?</li>
<li>Because evil is increasing in today's world, your class members will benefit from Paul's counsel to "think on" things that are pure, lovely, of good report, virtuous, or praiseworthy (Philippians 4:8). Perhaps you could assign each class member (or small groups of class members) one of the qualities listed in Philippians 4:8 or Articles of Faith 1:13. They could each use the Topical Guide to find scriptures about their assigned quality and share with the class what they find. They could also share examples of that quality in people's lives. How do we "seek after these things"?</li>
</ul>
<heading>COLOSSIANS 1:12–23; 2:2–8</heading>
<heading>When we are "rooted" in Jesus Christ, we are strengthened against worldly influences.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Paul's testimony of the Savior found in Colossians 1:12–23; 2:2–8 provides a good opportunity for class members to ponder and strengthen their own faith. Class members could search these verses to find things that strengthen their faith in Jesus Christ. What does it mean to be "rooted and built up in [Jesus Christ]"? (Colossians 2:7). The picture of a tree in this week's outline in<i>Come, Follow Me—For Individuals and Families</i>and the video "Spiritual Whirlwinds" (ChurchofJesusChrist.org) can help class members discuss this verse. What can strengthen or weaken the roots of a tree? How does being "rooted and built up in [Jesus Christ]" strengthen us against worldly influences? (see Colossians 2:7–8; see also Helaman 5:12; Ether 12:4).</li>
<li>You might invite class members to list things that Colossians 1:12–23; 2:3–8 teaches we can do to avoid the "vain deceit" that can "spoil" our faith in Christ (Colossians 2:8). How can we support each other in our efforts to follow the Savior and avoid Satan's deceptions?</li>
</ul>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Use music.</b>Sacred music invites the influence of the Holy Ghost. It can create a reverent atmosphere and inspire commitment and action. Consider how "teaching and admonishing one another in psalms and hymns" can be part of your class (Colossians 3:16; see also Teaching in the Savior's Way, 22).</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<heading>OCTOBER 16–22</heading>
<heading>1 and 2 Thessalonians</heading>
<heading>"PERFECT THAT WHICH IS LACKING IN YOUR FAITH"</heading>
<p>Alma taught, "Trust no one to be your teacher nor your minister, except he be a man of God, walking in his ways and keeping his commandments" (Mosiah 23:14). What does this scripture suggest about how you should prepare yourself to teach?</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>Give class members a few minutes to quickly look over 1 and 2 Thessalonians and find a verse that impresses them. Invite them to share their verses with someone else in the class, and then ask a few of the pairs to share what they learned from each other.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>1 THESSALONIANS 1:5–8; 2:1–13</heading>
<heading>Servants of the Lord should preach with sincerity and love.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Paul began his Epistle to the Thessalonians by reminding the Saints of the manner in which he and others had shared the gospel with them. This may be a good opportunity for your class members to evaluate how they are doing at teaching and learning from one another. You could invite class members to read 1 Thessalonians 1:5–8; 2:1–13 and identify principles related to sharing the gospel effectively. They could then write questions based on these verses that will help them evaluate their efforts to teach the gospel to others. For instance, one question might be "Am I an example of the things I know?" (see 1 Thessalonians 1:7). How can following the principles in this passage help us better minister to those we teach?</li>
</ul>
<heading>1 Thessalonians 3:9–13; 4:1–12</heading>
<heading>As we follow Jesus Christ, He can make us holy.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Paul taught the Thessalonian Saints that "God hath not called us unto uncleanness, but unto holiness" (1 Thessalonians 4:7). To begin a discussion about holiness, your class or an individual could sing "More Holiness Give Me" (Hymns, no. 131). Ask class members to discuss the characteristics of holiness mentioned in the hymn that stand out to them. Write on the board<i>More holiness give me, more. . . ,</i>and invite class members to look for words or phrases from 1 Thessalonians 3:9–13; 4:1–12 to complete the sentence. How can we develop these characteristics?</li>
<li>The invitation to be holy might seem daunting. It might help if class members understand that developing holiness is a gradual process that requires us to "increase more and more" over time (1 Thessalonians 4:10). To illustrate this process, you could invite a class member to talk about a talent or accomplishment that took consistent effort over time, such as making a quilt or playing a musical instrument. How is this similar to the process of becoming holy? Invite class members to review 1 Thessalonians 3:9–13; 4:1–12 and share insights about the effort it takes to become holy in the ways Paul describes. What has helped us progress toward holiness?</li>
</ul>
<heading>1 THESSALONIANS 4:11–12; 2 THESSALONIANS 3:7–13</heading>
<heading>We should work to provide for ourselves and those in need.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Questions like the following could inspire a discussion about Paul's counsel regarding work: What are the consequences of idleness? What are the blessings of work? What do you think Paul meant by the words "quiet" and "quietness"? (1 Thessalonians 4:11; 2 Thessalonians 3:12). You might want to write questions like these on the board for class members to ponder and discuss as they read 1 Thessalonians 4:11–12 and 2 Thessalonians 3:7–13. What other scriptures help us understand the importance of work and the perils of idleness? (see the suggestions in "Additional Resources").</li>
</ul>
<heading>2 THESSALONIANS 2</heading>
<heading>An apostasy was to precede the Second Coming of Jesus Christ.</heading>
<ul>
<li>It might be helpful to discuss some of the metaphors prophets have used to describe the Apostasy, such as a falling away (see 2 Thessalonians 2:3), a famine (see Amos 8:11–12), grievous wolves entering a flock (see Acts 20:28–30), and itching ears (see 2 Timothy 4:3–4). Consider dividing class members into pairs and asking them to read one or more of these scriptures (or others that you choose) and describe what the verses teach about the Great Apostasy. What did prophets teach about the Apostasy and the effect it would have?</li>
<li>Though the Church won't experience another "falling away" (2 Thessalonians 2:3) as it did anciently, we can still fall away individually. What does 2 Thessalonians 2 suggest about how this falling away can happen (see verses 9–10) and how we can avoid it? (see verses 15–17).</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>Scriptures about work and idleness.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Genesis 3:19</li>
<li>Matthew 21:28–32</li>
<li>Mosiah 2:10–16</li>
<li>Doctorine and Covenants 42:42; 58:27; 60:13; 75:29</li>
</ul>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Use a variety of methods.</b>It can be easy to get comfortable with one particular style of teaching, but different teaching methods reach different class members. Look for ways to vary your teaching approach, such as using videos, artwork, or music or giving class members opportunities to teach (see Teaching in the Savior's Way, 22).</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<heading>OCTOBER 23–29</heading>
<heading>1 and 2 Timothy; Titus; Philemon</heading>
<heading>"BE THOU AN EXAMPLE OF THE BELIEVERS"</heading>
<p>Read 1 and 2 Timothy; Titus; and Philemon with your class members in mind. The thoughts and impressions that come will help you direct class members to relevant scripture passages and bring the Spirit into your classroom.</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>It can be helpful for class members to hear each other talk about their successes and challenges with studying the scriptures, both individually and as families. Consider starting the class by inviting class members to talk about what is going well in their scripture study.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>1 AND 2 TIMOTHY; TITUS</heading>
<heading>Understanding true doctrine will help us avoid being deceived.</heading>
<ul>
<li>The members of your class are living in a time when it can be difficult to determine what is true and what is false. Timothy and Titus also lived in such a time, so perhaps Paul's counsel to them could be valuable today. Here are some passages containing Paul's counsel: 1 Timothy 1:1–7; 4:1–2, 6; 6:3–5, 20–21; 2 Timothy 3:13–17; 4:2–4; Titus 1:7–9; 2:1, 7–8. You could assign each class member to read one of these passages and share what he or she learns about the importance of true doctrine (see also Alma 31:5). How does the Savior's doctrine help us avoid deception? Class members could also share experiences in which the power of true doctrine blessed them.</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>"Let no man despise thy youth; but be thou an example of the believers" (1 Timothy 4:12).</graphics-caption>
<heading>1 TIMOTHY 4:10–16</heading>
<heading>"Be thou an example of the believers."</heading>
<ul>
<li>It's possible that members of your class don't realize the power of the good example they are setting. Consider inviting them to talk about how people they know, including fellow class members, have been examples of disciples of Christ. It might help the discussion if you list on the board the words in verse 12 that describe how we should be an example —<i>word, conversation</i>(which can also mean conduct or behavior),<i>charity, spirit, faith,</i>and<i>purity.</i>Class members could discuss how we can be examples of the believers in each of these ways.</li>
</ul>
<heading>2 TIMOTHY 1</heading>
<heading>"God hath not given us the spirit of fear; but of power, and of love, and of a sound mind."</heading>
<ul>
<li>This week's outline in<i>Come, Follow Me—For Individuals and Families</i>suggests looking in 2 Timothy for counsel Paul gave to encourage Timothy in his ministry. Ask class members to share any insights they found. Or you could give them a few minutes in class to find and share some of Paul's counsel (chapter 1 has some good examples). They could also share an experience when God helped them overcome their fears and gave them "the spirit of . . . power, and of love, and of a sound mind" (2 Timothy 1:7).</li>
</ul>
<heading>2 TIMOTHY 3</heading>
<heading>Studying the scriptures can help us overcome the perils of the last days.</heading>
<ul>
<li>After warning Timothy about "perilous times" to come, Paul testified of the power and importance of the scriptures (see 2 Timothy 3:1, 14–17). To begin a discussion about how the scriptures can strengthen us in difficult times, you could invite class members to review Paul's description of the perils of the last days, found in 2 Timothy 3:1–7. Then they could search for and share scriptures that have helped them guard against perils like these (some examples are listed in "Additional Resources"). How has studying the scriptures protected us from troubles in today's world?</li>
<li>Studying Paul's counsel about the power of the scriptures could be an opportunity for class members to encourage each other in their efforts to study the word of God. Perhaps class members could read 2 Timothy 3:14–17 and identify the blessings and protections that come from studying the scriptures. Then they could share experiences when they received these blessings because of their scripture study. You could also give class members a few moments to ponder what they can do to have more meaningful experiences with the scriptures, both individually and as families.</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>Scriptural truths that protect us against the perils of the last days (see 2 Timothy 3:2).</heading>
<table><thead>
<tr>
<th><b>Perils of the Last Days</b></th>
<th><b>Truths That Protect Us</b></th>
</tr></thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Lovers of their own selves</td>
<td>John 15:12–13</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Covetous</td>
<td>Doctrine and Covenants 88:123</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Boasters</td>
<td>Mosiah 2:24–25</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Proud</td>
<td>Alma 5:27–28</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Blasphemers</td>
<td>Doctrine and Covenants 63:64</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Disobedient to parents</td>
<td>Ephesians 6:1–3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Unthankful</td>
<td>Doctrine and Covenants 78:19</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Unholy</td>
<td>Deuteronomy 7:6</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Spiritual growth occurs at home.</b>You are with your class members for only a short time twice a month. Many of them are having meaningful spiritual experiences outside of class, and these experiences could strengthen other members of the class. Ask questions that encourage class members to share what they are learning as they study the gospel at home. (See Teaching in the Savior's Way, 18.)</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<graphics-caption>Balm of Gilead, by Annie Henrie</graphics-caption>
<heading>OCTOBER 30–NOVEMBER 5</heading>
<heading>Hebrews 1–6</heading>
<heading>JESUS CHRIST, "THE AUTHOR OF ETERNAL SALVATION"</heading>
<p>Consider sharing with members of your class some of the impressions you receive from the Holy Ghost about Hebrews 1–6. Doing so may inspire them to seek their own impressions as they study the scriptures.</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>Some class members who do not share often in class may simply need a specific invitation and a little time to prepare. You could contact a few of them a day or two in advance and ask them to come prepared to share a verse from Hebrews 1–6 that is meaningful to them.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>HEBREWS 1–5</heading>
<heading>Jesus Christ is "the author of eternal salvation."</heading>
<ul>
<li>How can you encourage class members to share meaningful scriptures about Jesus Christ that they found in their personal and family study this week? Consider creating five columns on the board, one for each of the first five chapters in Hebrews. Invite class members to write in the appropriate column phrases from these chapters that taught them about Jesus Christ and the verse number where each phrase is found. How does knowing these things about the Savior affect our faith in Him and willingness to follow Him?</li>
</ul>
<heading>HEBREWS 2:9–18; 4:12–16; 5:7–8</heading>
<heading>Jesus Christ suffered all things so that He can understand and help us when we suffer.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Hebrews 2:9–18; 4:12–16; 5:7–8 can help people who observe the suffering in the world and wonder if God notices or even cares. Perhaps class members could search these verses to find truths that would help with such questions. What do these verses teach about how the Savior responds to humanity's suffering? It may also be helpful to invite class members to share examples from the scriptures where Jesus Christ supported and comforted people in their sufferings (see "Additional Resources") or show the video "Mountains to Climb" (ChurchofJesusChrist.org). Class members could discuss what they learn about how the Savior can help us when we face difficult challenges.</li>
</ul>
<heading>HEBREWS 3:7–4:2</heading>
<heading>God's blessings are available to those who "harden not [their] hearts."</heading>
<ul>
<li>Hebrews 3 and 4 contain a plea to the Saints not to harden their hearts and thereby reject the blessings God wanted to give them. As you and your class read Hebrews 3:7–4:2, discuss ways the experiences of the ancient Israelites could apply to us today, just as they applied to the Hebrews in the early Church (see the study material about these verses in this week's outline in Come, Follow Me—For Individuals and Families). What can we do to keep our hearts soft and responsive to the will of the Lord? (see Proverbs 3:5–6; Alma 5:14–15; Ether 4:15). Class members could share how they or others they know have been blessed because they have had soft and contrite hearts.</li>
</ul>
<heading>HEBREWS 5:1–5</heading>
<heading>Those who serve in God's kingdom must be called of God.</heading>
<ul>
<li>The message in Hebrews 5 about priesthood holders being called of God can apply to all who are set apart by priesthood authority to serve in Church callings. To help your class learn what it means to "be called of God as was Aaron," consider inviting them to review the account of Aaron receiving his calling in Exodus 4:10–16, 27–31; 28:1. What insights from this account help us understand Hebrews 5:1–5? Class members could share how they have received confirmation that someone was called of God to fulfill a specific calling including, perhaps, themselves. How did that confirmation help them better sustain the person in his or her calling?</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>"No man taketh this honour unto himself, but he that is called of God, as was Aaron" (Hebrews 5:4). Moses Calls Aaron to the Ministry, by Harry Anderson</graphics-caption>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>Scriptural examples of people comforted by Jesus Christ.</heading>
<ul>
<li>John 8:1–11: The Lord comforted the woman taken in adultery.</li>
<li>John 11:1–46: The Lord comforted Mary and Martha after the death of their brother, Lazarus.</li>
<li>Enos 1:4–6: The Lord forgave Enos's sins and removed his guilt.</li>
<li>Mosiah 21:5–15: The Lord softened the hearts of the Lamanites so that they eased the burdens of the people of Limhi.</li>
<li>Mosiah 24:14–15: The Lord strengthened Alma's people so they could bear their burdens.</li>
<li>Ether 12:23–29: The Lord's words comforted Moroni.</li>
<li>3 Nephi 17:6–7: The Savior healed the Nephites of their infirmities.</li>
<li>Doctrine and Covenants 121:7–10: The Lord comforted Joseph Smith (see also Doctrine and Covenants 123:17).</li>
</ul>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Create a spiritual environment.</b>When you foster a peaceful, loving environment in your classroom, the Spirit can more easily touch the hearts of those you teach. What can you do to invite the influence of the Spirit into your classroom? Could you rearrange the seats or use pictures or music to invite the Spirit? (See Teaching in the Savior's Way, 15.)</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<graphics-caption>Melchizedek Blesses Abram, by Walter Rane. Gift of the artist</graphics-caption>
<heading>NOVEMBER 6–12</heading>
<heading>Hebrews 7–13</heading>
<heading>"AN HIGH PRIEST OF GOOD THINGS TO COME"</heading>
<p>As you read Hebrews 7–13, ponder what the Lord's message was for the Hebrew Saints. Also look for His messages to you and the people you teach.</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>Before class, invite a few class members to come prepared to share verses from Hebrews 7–13 that help them "draw near [to God] with a true heart in full assurance of faith" (Hebrews 10:22).</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>HEBREWS 7–10</heading>
<heading>Ancient and modern ordinances point to Jesus Christ.</heading>
<ul>
<li>This week's outline in<i>Come, Follow Me—For Individuals and Families</i>suggests searching Hebrews 7 for passages that teach about the Melchizedek Priesthood and testify of Jesus Christ. Invite class members to share what they found. Or you could give them time in class to review chapter 7 and find verses that teach of this priesthood and testify of the Savior. How was Melchizedek like Jesus Christ? (see the titles of Melchizedek in verses 1–2). How do Melchizedek Priesthood ordinances help us come unto Christ? Perhaps class members could look for possible answers in Gospel Topics, "Melchizedek Priesthood" (topics.ChurchofJesusChrist.org).</li>
<li>Even though we don't offer animal sacrifices, we do participate in ordinances today that, in a similar way, point our souls to Christ and provide "authorized channels through which the blessings and powers of heaven can flow into our individual lives" (David A. Bednar, "Always Retain a Remission of Your Sins," Ensign or Liahona, May 2016, 60). Perhaps you could explore together how the ancient ordinances described in Hebrews 8–10 symbolized the atoning sacrifice of the Savior. For example, what does the blood of bulls and goats represent? (see Hebrews 9:13–14). Whom does the high priest represent? (see Hebrews 9:24–26). The video "Sacrifice and Sacrament" (ChurchofJesusChrist.org) could help. How have modern ordinances blessed us and helped point us to Jesus Christ? What can we do to make these ordinances more meaningful and focused on the Savior?</li>
</ul>
<heading>HEBREWS 10:34–38; 11</heading>
<heading>Faith requires trusting in God's promises.</heading>
<ul>
<li>To help class members understand Paul's teachings about faith, you could begin by asking them to think about how they would describe faith in one sentence. Then, read and discuss as a class the definition Paul gave in Hebrews 11:1. You could then assign each person to choose one of the people mentioned in Hebrews 11 to study. Class members could use the footnotes or the Guide to the Scriptures (scriptures.ChurchofJesusChrist.org) to review the person's experiences in the Old Testament and then share with the class what they found. How did these people show that they felt an "assurance of things hoped for"? (Joseph Smith Translation, Hebrews 11:1 [in Hebrews 11:1, footnote b]). Class members may be able to share other examples of faithful people. When have we exercised faith in promises that had not yet been fulfilled?</li>
<li>The counsel to the Hebrew Saints who were tempted to "draw back" from their faith can be valuable to class members who may be struggling with their testimonies. It could also help those who are trying to help loved ones in a crisis of faith. To discover this counsel, class members could read Hebrews 10:34–38 and Elder Jeffrey R. Holland's statement in "Additional Resources." Why are we sometimes tempted to cast away our confidence (see Hebrews 10:35) in the Lord and His gospel? What can we do to build and maintain faith and confidence to "receive [God's] promise"? (Hebrews 10:36). The videos "Good Things to Come" and "An High Priest of Good Things to Come" (ChurchofJesusChrist.org) could supplement this discussion.</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>"Cast not away therefore your confidence."</heading>
<p>Referring to Hebrews 10:32–39, Elder Jeffrey R. Holland taught:
"Sure it is tough — before you join the Church, while you are trying to join, and after you have joined. That is the way it has always been, Paul says, but don't draw back. Don't panic and retreat. Don't lose your confidence. Don't forget how you once felt. Don't distrust the experience you had. . . .
"With any major decision there are cautions and considerations to make, but once there has been illumination, beware the temptation to retreat from a good thing. If it was right when you prayed about it and trusted it and lived for it, it is right now. Don't give up when the pressure mounts. . . . Face your doubts. Master your fears. «Cast not away therefore your confidence.» Stay the course and see the beauty of life unfold for you" ("Cast Not Away Therefore Your Confidence," Ensign, Mar. 2000, 8–9).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Go to the scriptures first.</b>The scriptures should be the primary source for your study and preparation. The words of modern prophets can complement the standard works (see Teaching in the Savior's Way, 17).</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<heading>NOVEMBER 13–19</heading>
<heading>James</heading>
<heading>"BE YE DOERS OF THE WORD, AND NOT HEARERS ONLY"</heading>
<p>Before reading this outline, read the Epistle of James and pay attention to promptings you receive. What principles do you find that would bless and edify your class members?</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>Invite class members to share verses from James that inspire them to be "doers of the word" (James 1:22). If it's not too personal, they could also share what they feel they need to act on, individually or as families.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>JAMES 1:5–6</heading>
<heading>When we ask in faith, God gives liberally.</heading>
<ul>
<li>The principles taught in James 1:5–6 led Joseph Smith to a life-changing spiritual experience, and they can bless each of us in some way. Perhaps you could write questions like the following on the board and ask class members to ponder them silently:<i>What influence has James 1:5–6 had in your life? What has Joseph Smith's experience with these verses taught you about seeking wisdom about your own questions?</i>(see Joseph Smith–History 1:10–17).<i>What experiences have taught you that "the testimony of James [is] true"?</i>(Joseph Smith–History 1:26). Invite class members to share thoughts they have after pondering these questions.</li>
<li>Perhaps class members could put James 1:5–6 into their own words. How does this help them understand these verses better? You may want to discuss together what some of the words from these verses mean.</li>
</ul>
<heading>JAMES 1:2–4; 5:7–11</heading>
<heading>If we endure patiently, the Lord will lead us to perfection.</heading>
<ul>
<li>To start a discussion on James's teachings about patience in these verses, you might invite class members to share experiences when they had to be patient and what they learned from that experience. Then they could search James 1:2–4; 5:7–11 for principles that relate to their experiences. They might also find applicable principles in the video "Continue in Patience" (ChurchofJesusChrist.org) or President Dieter F. Uchtdorf's message "Continue in Patience" (Ensign or Liahona, May 2010, 56–59). Class members could share what they have learned about patience as they have come to know Heavenly Father and the Savior. What has helped us develop patience?</li>
</ul>
<heading>JAMES 1:3–8, 21–25; 2:14–26</heading>
<heading>"Faith without works is dead."</heading>
<ul>
<li>One way to discuss James's teachings about faith and works could be to divide your class into two groups — one to explore why faith requires action and the other to explore why our actions require faith. To do this, they could read Matthew 7:21–23; James 1:6–8, 21–25; 2:14–26; and Joseph Smith History 1:19. Then each group could share what they found and discuss why both faith and works are necessary.</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>"Abraham believed God, and it was imputed unto him for righteousness" (James 2:23). Abraham on the Plains of Mamre, by Grant Romney Clawson</graphics-caption>
<ul>
<li>To help class members ponder more deeply the memorable phrase "Faith without works is dead" (James 2:26), you could write the following sentence on the board:<i>Faith without works is like __ without __.</i>Invite class members to think of creative ways to complete the sentence, and let them write their ideas on the board. What can we do to continually act on our faith in Jesus Christ?</li>
</ul>
<heading>JAMES 2:1–9</heading>
<heading>As disciples of Jesus Christ, we love all people, regardless of their circumstances.</heading>
<ul>
<li>To help inspire class members to show Christlike love to everyone regardless of others' situation or outward appearance, you could ask class members to take turns reading verses from James 1:9–11; 2:1–9; 5:1–6. Discuss questions like the following: What does it mean to "have respect to persons"? (James 2:9). Why do we sometimes treat those who have money, fame, or power differently than those who don't? How can we avoid treating others differently based on what their circumstances are? In what way are faithful followers of the Savior really the richest of all? (see James 2:5).</li>
</ul>
<heading>JAMES 3</heading>
<heading>The words we use have the power to hurt or bless others.</heading>
<ul>
<li>The powerful images James used can remind and motivate us to use words — both spoken and written to uplift others. Consider inviting class members to scan James 3, looking for comparisons James used to describe how words can hurt or bless others; some class members might enjoy drawing pictures of what they find. How do these comparisons illustrate James's instructions in this chapter? For example, how can our words be like a fire? Perhaps class members could share experiences that demonstrate the power that language can have. You might invite class members to ponder how they can apply James's counsel.</li>
</ul>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Encourage a respectful environment.</b>"Help your class members understand that each of them affects the spirit of the class. Encourage them to help you establish an open, loving, and respectful environment so that everyone feels safe sharing their experiences, questions, and testimonies" (Teaching in the Savior's Way, 15).</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<graphics-caption>Christ Preaching in the Spirit World, by Robert T. Barrett</graphics-caption>
<heading>NOVEMBER 20–26</heading>
<heading>1 and 2 Peter</heading>
<heading>"REJOICE WITH JOY UNSPEAKABLE AND FULL OF GLORY"</heading>
<p>Remember that your purpose is to teach people, not just present a lesson. As you read the Epistles of Peter, think of individual class members. What principles will help them build their faith?</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>Write the headings<i>1 Peter</i>and<i>2 Peter</i>on the board. Give class members time to review these epistles, and invite them to write under these headings words or phrases that they found meaningful. Then use the lists to invite people to share their insights.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>1 PETER 1:3–9; 2:19–24; 3:14–17; 4:12–19</heading>
<heading>I can find joy during times of trial and suffering.</heading>
<ul>
<li>One way to review Peter's counsel in 1 Peter 1:3–9; 2:19–24; 3:14–17; and 4:12–19 is to invite class members to think about someone they know who is experiencing a trial. Give them time in class to write a letter to that person, including truths from these verses that would encourage that person (see also Doctrine and Covenants 121:1–8; 123:17). Then class members could talk about the truths they chose.</li>
</ul>
<heading>1 PETER 1:13–20; 2:1–12</heading>
<heading>We are called to be "the people of God."</heading>
<ul>
<li>Peter's teachings in 1 Peter 1:13–20 and 2:1–12 can be an inspiring reminder of how the Lord sees us — His people — and what He expects of us. Perhaps you could invite class members to search these verses looking for descriptions of what it means to be "the people of God" (1 Peter 2:10) and then discuss what they find. You might explain that the word "peculiar" in 1 Peter 2:9 means "purchased" or "preserved" (see footnote f). What does this teach us about the way God feels about us and how He wants us to live?</li>
</ul>
<heading>1 PETER 3:18–20; 4:6</heading>
<heading>The gospel is preached to the dead so they can be judged justly.</heading>
<ul>
<li>The First Epistle of Peter contains one of the few references in the Bible to Jesus Christ's visit to the spirit world after His death — an event that modern revelation helps us understand more fully. To help class members deepen their understanding of the spirit world, you could invite them to read the following scriptures and write what they learn on the board: John 5:25; 1 Peter 3:18–20; 4:6; Alma 40:7–14, 21; Doctrine and Covenants 138:11–32 (see also "Additional Resources.") Why is it important to know about the Savior's visit to the spirit world? How does this knowledge affect the way we feel about God and His plan of salvation?</li>
</ul>
<heading>2 PETER 1:1–11</heading>
<heading>Through the power of Jesus Christ, we can develop our divine natures.</heading>
<ul>
<li>To encourage those you teach in their efforts to become more like Jesus Christ, you could invite them to identify the Christlike qualities described in 2 Peter 1:1–11. Consider writing these qualities on the board and asking class members to define them. Class members could then discuss how developing one quality leads to the development of the other qualities. Provide time for them to ponder which quality they would like to develop more fully.</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>Each Christlike quality we develop helps us weave a spiritual tapestry of discipleship.</graphics-caption>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>The work of redeeming the dead testifies of Christ's mission.</heading>
<p>Elder D. Todd Christofferson taught:
"What is the destiny of the countless billions who have lived and died with no knowledge of Jesus? With the Restoration of the gospel of Jesus Christ has come the understanding of how the unbaptized dead are redeemed and how God can be «a perfect, just God, and a merciful God also» [Alma 42:15].
"While yet in life, Jesus prophesied that He would also preach to the dead [see John 5:25]. Peter tells us this happened in the interval between the Savior's Crucifixion and Resurrection [see 1 Peter 3:18–19]. President Joseph F. Smith witnessed in vision that the Savior visited the spirit world [see Doctrine and Covenants 138:30, 33]. . . .
"Our anxiety to redeem the dead, and the time and resources we put behind that commitment, are, above all, an expression of our witness concerning Jesus Christ. It constitutes as powerful a statement as we can make concerning His divine character and mission. It testifies, first, of Christ's Resurrection; second, of the infinite reach of His Atonement; third, that He is the sole source of salvation; fourth, that He has established the conditions for salvation; and, fifth, that He will come again" ("The Redemption of the Dead and the Testimony of Jesus," Ensign, Nov. 2000, 9–10).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Teach the "why."</b>"Sometimes learners — especially youth — wonder how gospel principles relate to them or why they should obey certain commandments. However, if they understand Heavenly Father's eternal plan for the happiness of His children, the reasons for gospel principles and commandments become clearer and the motivation to obey increases" (Teaching in the Savior's Way, 20).</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<graphics-caption>Perfect Love, by Del Parson</graphics-caption>
<heading>NOVEMBER 27–DECEMBER 3</heading>
<heading>1–3 John; Jude</heading>
<heading>"GOD IS LOVE"</heading>
<p>What themes and principles stand out to you as you read 1–3 John and Jude? How can you use them to help your class members?</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>Invite several class members to share themes or specific truths that stood out to them as they studied the Epistles of John and Jude. What messages from these epistles were most relevant to them and their families?</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>1 JOHN 1:5–10; 2:3–11; 3:1–3; 4:7–21; 5:1–3</heading>
<heading>Heavenly Father and Jesus Christ are perfect examples of light and love.</heading>
<ul>
<li>How can you help those you teach recognize God's light and love in their lives? You might begin by writing the words light and love on the board. Ask class members to share other words that come to mind when they think of these two words. Each class member could then study one of the following scripture passages, looking for something the verses teach about light or love: 1 John 1:5–10; 2:3–11; 3:1–3; 4:7–12; 4:16–21; 5:1–3. Ask a few of them to share with the class what they found. You could also invite class members to share experiences when they have felt God's light and love.</li>
<li>You could invite class members to look at a ceiling light or the light coming through a window and share what they know about physical light. How is physical light like spiritual light? Class members could study the following to find additional insights into how God and His Son provide light in our lives: Psalm 27:1; John 1:4–5; 1 John 1:5–7; 3 Nephi 11:11; Doctrine and Covenants 88:6–13; and a hymn about light, such as "The Lord Is My Light" (Hymns, no. 89). Class members could also share experiences with seeking and receiving spiritual light in their lives.</li>
</ul>
<heading>1 JOHN 2:18–28; 4:3; 2 JOHN 1:7–11; 3 JOHN 1:9–11; JUDE</heading>
<heading>We must "[abide] in the doctrine of Christ."</heading>
<ul>
<li>The teachings of John and Jude about apostasy can help class members consider how to keep their faith in Jesus Christ strong. Consider inviting half of the class to search for descriptions of false teachings or apostasy in 1 John 2:18–23, 26–28; 4:3; 2 John 1:7–11; 3 John 1:9–11 and the other half to search for such descriptions in Jude. Or they could look for answers to questions like these: How do John and Jude define an anti-Christ? (see also Guide to the Scriptures, "Antichrist," scriptures.ChurchofJesusChrist.org). Is there anything in these verses that seems especially applicable to challenges we face today? What does it mean to "[abide] in the doctrine of Christ"? (2 John 1:9).</li>
<li>Jude uses interesting imagery to describe false teachers, or those who "speak evil of those things which they know not" (Jude 1:10). You might invite a few class members to draw on the board some of the images described in Jude 1:12–13 while other class members guess which phrase the person is drawing. How do these images represent false teachers and anti-Christs? For example, how do corrupt practices create "spots in [our] feasts of charity"? What can we do to fortify ourselves against "mockers"? (see Jude 1:18–21). Why might Jude have suggested that we "have compassion" (Jude 1:22) on those who mock the gospel?</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>"I have no greater joy than to hear that my children walk in truth"</graphics-caption>
<heading>3 JOHN 1:1–4</heading>
<heading>Joy comes as we help others "walk in truth."</heading>
<ul>
<li>There are probably people in your class who can relate to what John was feeling when he said that he had "no greater joy" than hearing that Gaius (one of his "children") was walking in truth.</li>
<li>Class members might benefit from hearing each other's experiences. Maybe you could start by reading together 3 John 1:1–4 and the scriptures in "Additional Resources." What do these scriptures teach us about the source of true joy?</li>
<li>Class members could talk about how they have felt as parents, missionaries, Church leaders, or teachers when they knew that the people they taught were walking in truth. You might contact a few class members before class and ask them to bring pictures of people they helped bring unto Christ and tell about their experiences.</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>Scriptures about helping others walk in truth.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Deuteronomy 6:6–7</li>
<li>Proverbs 22:6</li>
<li>John 4:36</li>
<li>1 Thessalonians 3:9</li>
<li>Mosiah 4:14–15</li>
<li>Alma 17:1–2, 26:11–37</li>
<li>Doctrine and Covenants 18:10–16; 50:22</li>
</ul>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Pray for your class members.</b>Just as the Savior prayed for Peter (see Luke 22:32), you should pray by name for those you teach, seeking to understand their specific needs. As you do so, Heavenly Father will "prepare their hearts" (Alma 16:16) and help you know what to teach in order to meet their needs (see Teaching in the Savior's Way, 6).</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<heading>DECEMBER 4–10</heading>
<heading>Revelation 1–5</heading>
<heading>"GLORY, AND POWER, BE UNTO. . . THE LAMB FOR EVER"</heading>
<p>Receiving spiritual impressions helps you recognize that the Holy Ghost wants to teach you. Recording and following those impressions demonstrates that you value them and desire to receive more.</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>As you begin a discussion, it may be helpful to invite class members to share some of the messages they found in the book of Revelation during their personal or family study. For example, what did they learn about Heavenly Father's plan to save His children? What did they learn about the Savior and His role in this plan? Encourage class members to keep looking for important messages about Jesus Christ and the plan of salvation as they continue reading Revelation at home. Give them an opportunity during future lessons to share what they find.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>REVELATION 1</heading>
<heading>Jesus Christ is the Living Son of the Living God.</heading>
<ul>
<li>The imagery and symbolism in Revelation 1 vividly testify that Jesus Christ lives and that He guides His Church. Perhaps class members could write on the board several phrases from Revelation 1 that include imagery or symbolism and share what each phrase teaches them about Jesus Christ. For example, what do we learn from these symbols about how Christ leads His Church today? How does John's description of the Savior compare to the one in Doctrine and Covenants 110:1–4?</li>
</ul>
<heading>REVELATION 2–3</heading>
<heading>Jesus Christ knows us personally and will help us overcome our challenges.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Reading the Lord's messages to the various branches of the Church in Revelation 2–3 could help reassure class members that the Savior is aware of them. Maybe you could invite them to scan these chapters to find evidence that Jesus Christ knew each branch's trials and strengths. They could also share experiences in which they felt that the Savior was aware of their unique circumstances. What counsel did the Lord give the Saints that can also help us overcome our struggles?</li>
<li>In these same chapters the Lord made inspiring promises to those who overcome. You could invite class members to work in pairs to search Revelation 2–3 to find the Lord's promises. Perhaps they could also draw pictures to represent some of these promises, then share with the class what they find. How do these promises inspire us to continue striving to overcome our own trials and weaknesses?</li>
</ul>
<heading>REVELATION 5</heading>
<heading>Only Jesus Christ could make Heavenly Father's plan possible.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Would an object lesson help your class understand the symbolism in Revelation 5 about the Savior opening the sealed book? You might bring a treat in a locked container to share with the class. Before class, secretly give one person the key to the lock. Describe to the class what is inside the container, and allow several class members to try opening the box before the person with the key opens it. Then the class could compare this object lesson to Revelation 5. Questions like these might help: How is the salvation of Heavenly Father's children like the locked container or the sealed book? Why was Jesus Christ the only one who could open the seals? (see the quotation in "Additional Resources").</li>
<li>Like the jubilant people mentioned in Revelation 5, today we can also raise our voices to praise the Savior as the One who is worthy to offer us salvation. Perhaps class members could sing together a favorite hymn of praise about the Savior, such as "Glory to God on High" (Hymns, no. 67). Class members could identify truths the hymn teaches about Jesus Christ. What similarities do we see between the messages of our hymns of praise and the declarations in Revelation 5:9–14?</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>Only Jesus Christ could atone for us.</heading>
<p>Describing events in the premortal life, Elder Jeffrey R. Holland taught:
"Christ volunteered to honor the moral agency of all humankind even as He atoned for their sins. In the process, He would return to the Father all glory for such redemptive love.
"This infinite Atonement of Christ was possible because (1) He was the only sinless man ever to live on this earth and therefore was not subject to the spiritual death resulting from sin, (2) He was the Only Begotten of the Father and therefore possessed the attributes of godhood that gave Him power over physical death, and (3) He was apparently the only one sufficiently humble and willing in the premortal council to be foreordained to that service" ("The Atonement of Jesus Christ," Ensign or Liahona, Mar. 2008, 35).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Use the scriptures and the words of latter-day prophets.</b>"The Lord has commanded us to «teach one another the doctrine of the kingdom» [Doctrine and Covenants 88:77] and to use the scriptures to «teach the principles of [His] gospel» [Doctrine and Covenants 42:12]. The scriptures and words of latter-day prophets and apostles are the source of the truths we teach" (Teaching in the Savior's Way, 21).</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<graphics-caption>Composite art by Eric Johnson: The Grand Council, by Robert T. Barrett; star duster courtesy of European Space Agency</graphics-caption>
<heading>DECEMBER 11–17</heading>
<heading>Revelation 6–14</heading>
<heading>"THEY OVERCAME. . . BY THE BLOOD OF THE LAMB"</heading>
<p>Joseph Smith said that the book of Revelation "is one of the plainest books God ever caused to be written" (in Journal, December 1842–June 1844; Book 2, 10 March 1843–14 July 1843, 98, JosephSmithPapers.org). How can you help class members find plain truths in these chapters?</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>To help class members review some of the insights they had as they studied Revelation 6–14, write the numbers 6 through 14 on the board. Class members could write next to a number any insights they found in the corresponding chapter that are relevant to someone living in the latter days.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>Jesus Christ opens the seals of the book.</heading>
<heading>REVELATION 6</heading>
<ul>
<li>To help class members visualize the book with seven seals (see Revelation 5:1), you could explain that ancient scrolls were often sealed with a bit of clay or wax. A ring or stamp would be pressed into the clay or wax before it hardened, signifying the authority of the person who sealed the scroll and discouraging unauthorized people from opening it. Class members could then share any thoughts or impressions they had while reading about this book in Revelation 6; Doctrine and Covenants 77:6–7; and this week's outline in<i>Come, Follow Me—For Individuals and Families.</i>Why do you think it is important to know this book's symbolic meaning? Why do you think it is important to know that the Savior is the one to open each of the seals of the book? (see Revelation 5:1–9).</li>
</ul>
<heading>REVELATION 7–11</heading>
<heading>"The kingdoms of this world are become the kingdoms of our Lord."</heading>
<ul>
<li>Revelation 7–11 can be difficult to understand. One blessing of a Sunday School class is that class members can help each other understand the scriptures. You could make a list of questions class members have about these chapters and invite them to share insights with each other. Encourage all class members — those who may feel more knowledgeable and those who may feel they don't know as much to share their insights about these chapters.</li>
<li>You might start a discussion by asking class members what recurring themes they found in Revelation 7–11. They could share verses where these themes are found and explain why the themes are significant. If they need help, you could suggest that they read Revelation 11:15–17. What themes do they find in these verses, and how is this theme expressed in other verses in Revelation 7–11? Even though these chapters describe wars and plagues, what do we find that gives us hope and confidence in Jesus Christ?</li>
</ul>
<heading>REVELATION 12–14</heading>
<heading>We overcome Satan "by the blood of the Lamb, and by the word of [our] testimony."</heading>
<ul>
<li>Learning about the War in Heaven can help us better understand life on earth. Class members could read Joseph Smith Translation, Revelation 12:7–11 (in the Bible appendix) and identify how we overcome Satan and his hosts. What other insights do we gain from the entries on the War in Heaven in the Bible Dictionary or Gospel Topics? (topics.ChurchofJesusChrist.org). What do we learn that can help us overcome the adversary?</li>
<li>The war between good and evil is described in Revelation 13–14. What does chapter 13 teach us about how the dragon fights this war? According to chapter 14, how does the Lamb fight it? It could be interesting to make a list of the ways that each side fights this war according to these two chapters. What similarities and differences do we see?</li>
<li>What does it mean that the Lamb was "slain from the foundation of the world"? (Revelation 13:8; see also Revelation 5:6). Consider helping your class members find answers to this question by reading Mosiah 3:13 and Moses 7:47 as a class. What does it mean to overcome Satan "by the blood of the Lamb"? (Revelation 12:11).</li>
</ul>
<heading>REVELATION 14:6–7</heading>
<heading>"I saw another angel. . . having the everlasting gospel."</heading>
<ul>
<li>This week's outline in<i>Come, Follow Me—For Individuals and Families</i>suggests learning about various angels who restored "the everlasting gospel to. them that dwell on the earth"(Revelation 14:6). Invite class members to share what they learned. What does Doctrine and Covenants 133:36–40 teach us about Revelation 14:6–7? How do we participate in the work of the angel mentioned in Revelation 14:6–7? You could also show the video "The Work of These Last Days" (Churchof Jesus Christ.org)</li>
</ul>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>It's OK to say "I don't know."</b>"While it is natural to want to answer every question, in some situations it is appropriate to simply say, «I don't know. Let's study that question on our own this week, and we can discuss it next time»" (Teaching in the Savior's Way, 24). Then ask class members to search the scriptures and other Church resources for answers.</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<graphics-caption>Little Lamb, by Jenedy Paige</graphics-caption>
<heading>DECEMBER 18–24</heading>
<heading>Christmas</heading>
<heading>"GOOD TIDINGS OF GREAT JOY"</heading>
<p>Gospel discussions are spiritually powerful when they are centered on Jesus Christ. As you study the birth and mission of Jesus Christ this week, seek inspiration from the Holy Ghost to know how you can best center your class discussion on the Savior.</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>Invite class members to share what they are doing or have done in the past as individuals or families to celebrate the Savior's birth in ways that bring them closer to Him.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>MATTHEW 1:18–25; LUKE 1:26–38; 2:1–20</heading>
<heading>Jesus Christ condescended to be born on earth.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Christmas is a good time to ponder and celebrate the condescension of Christ — His willingness to leave "his Father's courts on high, with man to live, for man to die" ("Again We Meet around the Board," Hymns, no. 186). To inspire a discussion on this topic, you could ask class members what they learned in their personal or family study this week about who Jesus Christ was before He was born (see John 17:5; Mosiah 7:27; Doctrine and Covenants 76:12–14, 20–24; Moses 4:2). Then you could display the image in this week's outline in<i>Come, Follow Me—For Individuals and Families</i>as class members read about the Savior's birth (see Matthew 1:18–25; Luke 1:26–38; 2:1–20). Encourage them to share their thoughts and feelings as they compare the Savior's premortal glory with His humble birth.</li>
<li>A question like the one the angel asked Nephi in 1 Nephi 11:16 could be a good way to start a class discussion, though you might word it differently. Maybe you could write on the board<i>What is the condescension of God?</i>and ask class members to ponder this question as they read 1 Nephi 11:17–33. Ask them to share any thoughts about the Savior that these verses inspire. What pictures could you show the class that depict scenes from the Savior's life described by Nephi? Class members could also consider the condescension of the Savior as they watch a video about His birth, such as "A Gift to the World," "The Nativity," or "He Is the Gift" (Churchof Jesus Christ.org).</li>
<li>Music is a wonderful way to invite the Spirit to your class. Consider inviting someone to perform a Christmas song or reading or singing a few hymns together as a class (see Hymns, nos. 201–14). Class members could look for phrases in these hymns and the scriptures listed with the hymns that increase their gratitude for the Savior and His willingness to come to earth.</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>Gethsemane, by J. Kirk Richards</graphics-caption>
<heading>LUKE 4:16–21; JOHN 3:16</heading>
<heading>Jesus Christ fulfilled His mission, which made it possible for us to inherit eternal life.</heading>
<ul>
<li>To help class members discuss the reasons Jesus Christ was born, you could invite them to find and share scriptures that summarize His mission (see this week's outline in Come, Follow Me—For Individuals and Families for some examples). Perhaps class members could look for and read verses in pairs or small groups. What do they learn about Christ's mission from the verses they found? What do we learn about His mission from some of the titles He is given in the scriptures? (see Bible Dictionary, "Christ, names of").</li>
<li>Class members could learn about the Savior's mission by reading "The Living Christ: The Testimony of the Apostles" (Churchof Jesus Christ.org) and sharing statements they find that explain why He came to earth. Give class members time to reflect on their testimonies of Jesus Christ and His mission. Could they share personal experiences or stories from the Savior's life that have increased their faith in or love for Him? How has studying the New Testament this year contributed to a more meaningful Christmas season? To review some of the New Testament accounts class members have learned about this year, you might show the videos "For God So Loved the World" or "To This End Was I Born" (Churchof Jesus Christ.org).</li>
</ul>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Reserve time for learners to share.</b>"When learners share what they are learning, they not only feel the Spirit and strengthen their Reserve time for learners to share. "When learners share what they are learning, they not only feel the Spirit and strengthen their own testimonies, but they also encourage other class members to discover truths for themselves. . . . Reserve time for student sharing in every lesson in some cases, you may find that these discussions are the lesson" (Teaching in the Savior's Way, 30).</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<graphics-caption>The City Eternal, by Keith Larson</graphics-caption>
<heading>DECEMBER 25–31</heading>
<heading>Revelation 15–22</heading>
<heading>"HE THAT OVERCOMETH SHALL INHERIT ALL THINGS"</heading>
<p>What does the battle between good and evil described in Revelation teach you about the importance of following Christ here on earth? After pondering this principle, consider the needs of your class members. What truths from Revelation can help them make righteous choices?</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>As class members come to the end of their New Testament study, encourage them to share their thoughts about the New Testament. Invite them to share how their scripture study has helped them better know Jesus Christ and become more like Him.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>REVELATION 17–18</heading>
<heading>We must separate ourselves from the wickedness of the world.</heading>
<ul>
<li>It's not particularly pleasant to read about the wickedness and fall of Babylon in Revelation 17–18, but it is instructive because Babylon can be a symbol of the wicked world we live in today. Maybe you could divide these chapters among class members and ask them to look for answers to questions like these: Why are people drawn to Babylon, or worldliness? Why is Babylon dangerous? What will happen to Babylon? What warnings did John give to help us avoid Babylon's fate?</li>
<li>After reading Revelation 18:4, class members could discuss how they can "come out of" Babylon and "be not partakers of her sins." They could share scriptures or messages from Church leaders that have helped them resist the temptations of Babylon, or the world. Consider watching the video "Dare to Stand Alone" (Churchof Jesus Christ.org) or reading Elder Quentin L. Cook's statement in "Additional Resources." Class members could share ideas about how to apply the two principles Elder Cook mentioned. In what sense do we "come out" of Babylon? (see, for instance, Isaiah 52:11; Doctrine and Covenants 25:10). What can we do to encourage others to do the same?</li>
</ul>
<heading>REVELATION 19–20</heading>
<heading>We can prepare for the Lord's Second Coming and the Day of Judgment.</heading>
<ul>
<li>The Second Coming of Jesus Christ is frequently called "the great and the terrible day of the Lord" (Joel 2:31), and based on Revelation 19–20, that seems like a good description. Consider writing on the board some of the events described in Revelation 19:5–20:15. Invite class members to find the verses that describe these events. Why are these events called great and terrible? What do we learn from these verses about the Savior and those who follow Him? What can we do now to be among those who will rejoice at the time of His coming?</li>
<li>To inspire a discussion about the book of life and the final judgment, you could invite class members to create a simple book by folding a piece of paper into fourths. They could then read Revelation 20:12–15; 2 Nephi 9:14; 29:11 and ponder what they would want to have written about them in the book of life. Invite them to write those things in their books, and invite a few class members to share something they wrote. What choices can we make now so that these things will be written in the book of life? To help class members not feel discouraged about their own spiritual progress, consider sharing counsel from Elder Jeffrey R. Holland's message "Be Ye Therefore Perfect — Eventually" (Ensign or Liahona, Nov. 2017, 40–42).</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>The Last Judgement, by John Scott</graphics-caption>
<heading>REVELATION 21:1–22:5</heading>
<heading>If we are faithful, we will be blessed with celestial glory.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Though the latter days are prophesied to be filled with wickedness and peril, the reward John saw for the faithful far exceeds the tribulation that precedes it. To help class members explore this beautiful conclusion to Revelation, you could invite them to review Revelation 21:1–22:5, looking for phrases that inspire them to strive for celestial glory. What promises are made to the faithful? How does this description help us when we face our current challenges and trials?</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>Choosing righteousness over Babylon's wickedness.</heading>
<p>Elder Quentin L. Cook taught:
"We cannot avoid the world. A cloistered existence is not the answer. In a positive sense, our contribution to the world is part of our challenge and is essential if we are to develop our talents. . . .
". . . .Members of the Church need to be involved in the world in a positive way. How then do we balance the need to positively contribute to the world and to not succumb to the sins of the world? [See Doctrine and Covenants 25:10; 59:9.] Two principles will make a significant difference.
"1. Let people know you are a committed Latter-day Saint. . . .
"2. Be confident about and live your beliefs" ("Lessons from the Old Testament: In the World but Not of the World," Ensign, Feb. 2006, 54–55).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Respect others' agency.</b>"People are more likely to make meaningful changes in their lives when those changes come from their own exercise of agency. When you extend invitations to act, be sure to respect the agency of those you teach" (Teaching in the Savior's Way, 35).</p>
</chapter>
</text>
