<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<text manual-title="Doctrine and Covenants 2021 Come, Follow Me—For Sunday School"
		audience="adult-teacher"
		copyright="2020"
		usage-years="2021"
		standard-work="d-and-c"
		edition="original"
		era="come-follow-me">
<chapter type="cover">
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 2021</heading>
<heading>Come, Follow Me—For Sunday School</heading>
<heading>Living, Learning, and Teaching the Gospel of Jesus Christ</heading>
</chapter>
<chapter type="title-page">
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 2021</heading>
<heading>Come, Follow Me—For Sunday School</heading>
<heading>Living, Learning, and Teaching the Gospel of Jesus Christ</heading>
<p>Published by
The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints
Salt Lake City, Utah</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="copyright">
<p>© 2020 by Intellectual Reserve, Inc.
All rights reserved.
Version: 11/18
Translation of Come, Follow Me—For Sunday School: Doctrine and Covenants 2021
16589 000
Printed in the United States of America
Comments and corrections are appreciated. Please send them, including errors, to ComeFollowMe@ChurchofJesusChrist.org.</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="teacher-help">
<heading>You Are a Teacher in the Church of Jesus Christ</heading>
<p>You have been called of God to love and teach His children in the Savior's way. You were set apart to this calling by the authority of His holy priesthood. Even if you are not an experienced teacher, as you live worthily, pray daily, and study the scriptures, Heavenly Father will grant you the influence and power of the Holy Ghost to help you succeed (see 2 Nephi 33:1).</p>
<p>Those entrusted to your care are Heavenly Father's children, and He knows what they need and how best to reach them. Through the Holy Ghost, God will guide you as you prepare and while you are teaching. He will reveal to you what you should say and what you should do (see 2 Nephi 32:5).</p>
<p>The essential purpose of gospel teaching and learning is to change lives. Your purpose as a teacher is to help those you teach do all they can to become more converted to the gospel of Jesus Christ — an effort that extends far beyond class time. Invite those you teach to actively participate in learning the principles and doctrine of Jesus Christ and to act on what they learn. Encourage them to make their individual and family study outside of class the primary source of their gospel learning. As they act in faith by studying as individuals and families, they will invite the Spirit into their lives, and it is the Spirit that brings about true conversion. Everything you do as a teacher should point to this sacred objective.</p>
<p>Teach only the doctrine of the restored gospel of Jesus Christ as found in the scriptures and the words of latter-day prophets. Pure doctrine — eternal, unchanging truth taught by God and His servants — invites the Spirit and has the power to change lives.</p>
<p>The calling to teach is a sacred trust, and it is normal to feel overwhelmed at times. But remember that your Heavenly Father called you, and He will never forsake you. This is the Lord's work, and as you serve "with all your heart, might, mind and strength" (Doctrine and Covenants 4:2), He will enlarge your capacities, gifts, and talents, and your service will bless the lives of those you teach.</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="teacher-help">
<heading>Using Come, Follow Me—For Sunday School</heading>
<heading>Preparing to Teach in Sunday School</heading>
<p>Personal and family study at home should be the center of gospel learning. This is true for you and for those you teach. As you prepare to teach, start by having your own experiences in the scriptures. Your most important preparation will occur as you come unto Christ, search the scriptures, and seek the inspiration of the Holy Ghost.</p>
<p>Come, Follow Me—For Individuals and Families is an important part of both your personal study and your preparation to teach. It will help you gain a deeper understanding of the doctrinal principles found in the scriptures. It will also enable you to inspire and invite class members to use Come, Follow Me—For Individuals and Families to enhance their personal and family scripture study (for help doing this, see "Ideas for Encouraging Personal and Family Study" in this resource). As you do, remember to be sensitive to class members whose family circumstances may not support regular family scripture study and family home evening.</p>
<p>During your preparation, thoughts and impressions will come to you about the people you teach, how the principles in the scriptures will build their faith in Heavenly Father and Jesus Christ, and how you can inspire them to discover those principles as they study the scriptures for themselves.</p>
<heading>Teaching Ideas</heading>
<p>As you prepare to teach, you might gain additional inspiration by exploring the teaching outlines in this resource. Don't think of these ideas as step-by-step instructions but rather as suggestions to spark your own inspiration. You know your class members, and you will get to know them even better as you learn together in class. The Lord knows them too, and He will inspire you with the best ways to help class members build on the gospel learning they are doing at home.</p>
<p>Many other resources are available for you to use as you prepare, including ideas in Come, Follow Me—For Individuals and Families and Church magazines. For more information about these and other resources, see the section titled "Additional Resources" in this resource.</p>
<heading>Some Things to Keep in Mind</heading>
<ul>
<li>As a teacher, you have an important responsibility to support, encourage, and build on class members' personal and family gospel learning. While some class members may not be consistently studying the gospel at home, you can make a big difference in encouraging and helping them make their homes the center of gospel learning.</li>
<li>Class members' conversion to the gospel of Jesus Christ will deepen as they understand and apply true doctrine. Encourage them to record and act on the impressions they receive from the Holy Ghost.</li>
<li>Teaching is more than lecturing, but it is also more than simply leading a discussion. Part of your role is to encourage participation that edifies and is based on the scriptures. You should also share the inspired insights you received as you studied the scriptures.</li>
<li>Remember that many class members are having meaningful experiences studying the scriptures at home. You can support their gospel learning by providing them with frequent opportunities to share what they are learning at home and how it is influencing their lives.</li>
<li>Heavenly Father wants you to succeed as a teacher. He has provided many resources to help you, including teacher council meetings. In these meetings you can counsel with other teachers about challenges you face. You can also discuss and practice principles of Christlike teaching.</li>
<li>Some people learn better when they have opportunities to teach. On occasion, consider allowing class members, including youth, to teach a part of the lesson. Base this decision on the needs and abilities of class members. If you do invite a class member to teach, take the time to help him or her prepare in advance by using the ideas found in this resource and in Come, Follow Me—For Individuals and Families. Remember that as the called teacher, you are ultimately responsible for what is taught in class.</li>
<li>This resource includes teaching outlines for every week of the year. On Sundays when Sunday School is not held, families will continue reading the Doctrine and Covenants at home according to the schedule outlined in Come, Follow Me—For Individuals and Families. You may choose to skip the lessons that fall on a week when Sunday School isn't held, or you may teach from multiple lessons during a single class.</li>
</ul>
</chapter>
<chapter type="teacher-help">
<heading>Ideas for Encouraging Personal and Family Study</heading>
<p>Here are some ideas to help you encourage class members to study the word of God at home, both individually and as families. Be sensitive to the fact that not all class members can study the scriptures with their families (for example, some members live alone or in part-member families).</p>
<ul>
<li>Invite class members to share experiences they had studying the scriptures at home. For example, you could ask them to share a verse that deepened their love for Jesus Christ.</li>
<li>Ask class members to give examples of what they are doing to make personal or family scripture study more meaningful. (Some ideas can be found under "Ideas to Improve Your Personal Scripture Study" and "Ideas to Improve Your Family Scripture Study" in Come, Follow Me—For Individuals and Families.)</li>
<li>Invite class members to share how they acted on impressions they received during their personal or family scripture study.</li>
<li>Spend a few minutes showing class members some of the resources provided by the Church to help members study the gospel, such as the scripture study helps found at scriptures.ChurchofJesusChrist.org; "Scripture Stories" found at children.ChurchofJesusChrist.org; youth-focused content at youth.ChurchofJesusChrist.org; seminary and institute manuals; and videos, audio recordings, and images found at MediaLibrary.ChurchofJesusChrist.org. Many of these are also in the Gospel Library app.</li>
<li>Spend a few minutes explaining how to use the Gospel Library app to study the scriptures, including how to mark verses and record impressions.</li>
<li>Invite one or more class members to share how they have taught a specific gospel principle in their families.</li>
</ul>
</chapter>
<chapter type="teacher-help">
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<p>These resources can be found in the Gospel Library app and on ChurchofJesusChrist.org.</p>
<heading>Come, Follow Me—For Individuals and Families</heading>
<p>You can adapt any activities from this resource for use in your Sunday School class. If class members have used these activities in their personal or family scripture study, encourage them to share their experiences and insights.</p>
<heading>Revelations in Context</heading>
<p>Revelations in Context: The Stories behind the Sections of the Doctrine and Covenants is a collection of essays about the history surrounding the revelations contained in the Doctrine and Covenants. The context provided in this resource can help you better understand what the Lord's words in the Doctrine and Covenants may have meant to the early Latter-day Saints.</p>
<heading>Saints</heading>
<p>Saints is a multivolume narrative history of the Church. Volume 1, The Standard of Truth, and volume 2, No Unhallowed Hand, cover the same period of Church history as the Doctrine and Covenants. These histories can give you insights into the context surrounding the revelations you study in the Doctrine and Covenants.</p>
<heading>Church History Topics</heading>
<p>Numerous articles about the people, artifacts, geography, and events of Church history can be found at ChurchofJesusChrist.org/study/history/topics.</p>
<heading>Seminary and Institute Manuals</heading>
<p>Seminary and institute manuals provide historical background and doctrinal commentary for principles found in the scriptures. They may also inspire teaching ideas for Sunday School classes.</p>
<heading>Hymns and Children's Songbook</heading>
<p>Sacred music invites the Spirit and teaches doctrine in a memorable way. In addition to the printed versions of Hymns and Children's Songbook, you can find recordings of many hymns and children's songs at music.ChurchofJesusChrist.org and in the Sacred Music and Gospel Media apps.</p>
<heading>Church Magazines</heading>
<p>The New Era, Ensign, and Liahona magazines contain articles and other features that can supplement the principles that you are teaching from the Doctrine and Covenants.</p>
<heading>Videos and Art</heading>
<p>Artwork, videos, and other media can help those you teach visualize the doctrine and stories related to the scriptures. Visit the Gospel Media library at ChurchofJesusChrist.org to browse the Church's collection of media resources. These resources are also available in the Gospel Media app, and many images are also found in the Gospel Art Book.</p>
<heading>Gospel Topics</heading>
<p>In Gospel Topics (topics.ChurchofJesusChrist.org) you can find basic information about a variety of gospel topics, along with links to helpful resources, such as related general conference messages, articles, scriptures, and videos. You can also find Gospel Topics Essays, which offer in-depth answers to doctrinal and historical questions.</p>
<heading>True to the Faith</heading>
<p>For additional insights into gospel principles, consider looking in True to the Faith. This resource consists of an alphabetical list of gospel topics explained in simple terms.</p>
<heading>Preach My Gospel</heading>
<p>This guide for missionaries provides an overview of the basic principles of the gospel.</p>
<heading>For the Strength of Youth</heading>
<p>This resource outlines Church standards that help youth and others become faithful disciples of Jesus Christ. Consider referring to it often, especially if you are teaching youth.</p>
<heading>Teaching in the Savior's Way</heading>
<p>This resource can help you learn about and ap principles of Christlike teaching. These principles are discussed and practiced in teacher council meetings.</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="teacher-help">
<heading>A Pattern for Teaching</heading>
<p>Each outline in this resource follows a pattern of inviting sharing and teaching the doctrine.</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>As part of every class, invite class members to share insights and experiences they had during the previous week as they studied the scriptures as individuals and families and applied what they learned. Help class members see that their personal learning outside of class is important. Their individual conversion will come not only through Sunday learning but also through their daily experiences. When class members hear each other's experiences and testimonies of the gospel of Jesus Christ, they are more likely to seek similar experiences of their own.</p>
<p>Not everyone will have read the chapters for each lesson, and even some who did may not feel comfortable sharing. Make sure all class members feel they are a valued part of the class, whether or not they have something to share.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<p>You and your class members should focus on Jesus Christ and His doctrine — the eternal truths of the gospel — found in the assigned scripture passages. As you discuss doctrine from the scriptures, what verses, quotations, experiences, questions, and additional resources might you share? How might you use these resources to help class members discover and understand gospel principles? How can you help them build their faith in Heavenly Father and Jesus Christ?</p>
<graphics-caption>The First Vision of the Restoration, by Michael Bedard</graphics-caption>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<heading>DECEMBER 28–JANUARY 3</heading>
<heading>Doctrine and Covenants 1</heading>
<heading>"HEARKEN, O YE PEOPLE"</heading>
<p>As you read Doctrine and Covenants 1, think about what verses you might focus on in class and how you might help class members learn from these verses.</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>You might begin your class study of the Doctrine and Covenants by asking class members how they feel about studying this book of scripture this year. What passages from section 1 help them feel excited to read the Doctrine and Covenants? Perhaps you could ask them to search section 1 for a verse they would share if they were trying to persuade someone to read this sacred book.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 1</heading>
<heading>The Lord invites us to "search these commandments."</heading>
<ul>
<li>As you discuss the Lord's "preface" to the Doctrine and Covenants (verse 6), it might be helpful for someone in the class to explain what a preface is and the purpose it serves in a book. Then the class could discuss how section 1 serves that purpose for the Doctrine and Covenants. For example, what themes for the book does section 1 introduce? What purposes does the book have? What do we find in this section that could influence the way we read the Doctrine and Covenants this year?</li>
<li>This week's outline in<i>Come, Follow Me—For Individuals and Families</i>invites us to consider how we will act on the Lord's command to "search these commandments" (verse 37). Perhaps class members could share what they plan to do this year to make their study of the Doctrine and Covenants meaningful. What will they search for? How is searching different from just reading? What study methods have they found most helpful?</li>
</ul>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 1:1–6, 23–24, 37–39</heading>
<heading>God speaks through His servants, and His words will be fulfilled.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Many of us have family members, friends, and acquaintances who do not share our beliefs about living prophets. Perhaps class members could share truths they find in section 1 that they could use to respond to someone who questions their beliefs about prophets. You might suggest that they look particularly in verses 1–6 and 37–39. What do these verses teach about the Lord and His prophets?</li>
<li>Class members might be interested to learn that when a council called by Joseph Smith discussed publishing the Prophet's revelations, some council members opposed the idea. They were embarrassed by Joseph's weakness in writing, and they worried that publishing the revelations might cause more problems for the Saints (see Saints, 1:140–43). How does section 1 address these concerns? (see, for example, verses 6, 24, 38).</li>
<li>The lyrics of the hymn "Come, Listen to a Prophet's Voice" (Hymns, no. 21) teach some of the same principles taught in section 1. Perhaps you could sing or read the hymn together and then invite class members to find lines in the hymn and verses in section 1 that teach the same principles.</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>God speaks to us through His servants.</graphics-caption>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 1:12–30, 35–36</heading>
<heading>The Lord restored His gospel to help us face the challenges of the latter days.</heading>
<ul>
<li>What thoughts did class members have as they read the description of the last days in verses 13–16? What is happening in the world today that fulfills these prophesied descriptions? Encourage class members to share anything they found in section 1 that helped them feel peace and confidence despite the challenges of our day.</li>
<li>To help class members ponder the blessings we have because the gospel has been restored, you could write on the board<i>What do verses 17–23 teach about why the Lord restored His gospel?</i>Class members could search these verses and share their thoughts with each other. For example, how have the truths restored through Joseph Smith helped us increase our faith? (see verse 21).</li>
</ul>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 1:19–28</heading>
<heading>The Lord uses "the weak and the simple" to accomplish His work.</heading>
<ul>
<li>One important theme of Doctrine and Covenants 1 is the role of "the weak and the simple" in the Lord's great latter-day work (verse 23). Invite class members to search verses 19–28 to learn how the words "weak" and "simple" apply to us as the Lord's servants. As they share what they find, you could discuss questions like these: What characteristics does the Lord want His servants to have? What will the Lord accomplish through His servants in the latter days? How are the prophecies in these verses being fulfilled throughout the world and in our own lives?</li>
</ul>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Help learners liken the scriptures to themselves.</b>The same truths that inspired the early Saints can help us face our challenges today. As you teach the Doctrine and Covenants, help class members make connections between the Lord's messages to Joseph Smith and what the Lord might say to them personally. (See Teaching in the Savior's Way, 21.)</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<graphics-caption>Sacred Grove, by Greg K. Olsen</graphics-caption>
<heading>JANUARY 4–10</heading>
<heading>Joseph Smith—History 1:1–26</heading>
<heading>"I SAW A PILLAR OF LIGHT"</heading>
<p>Remember that your most important preparation will be studying the scriptures and living by what you learn. The Spirit can help you know what to focus on in class.</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>What insights did class members gain as they studied Joseph Smith—History 1:1–26 this week? Perhaps you could display a picture of Joseph Smith or the First Vision and invite class members to write on the board some insights from their study, along with the verses where they found them. They could also share how their testimonies of Joseph Smith and his mission grew as they learned about him this week.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>JOSEPH SMITH–HISTORY 1:5–18</heading>
<heading>If we ask in faith, God will answer us.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Members of your class may be able to relate to Joseph's desire to seek truth in a world where many conflicting ideas are taught. How is the confusion in our day similar to what he faced? To help class members see how we can find answers to our questions, you could invite them to list on the board different ways people seek truth. Then they could review Joseph Smith—History 1:5–18 and add to the list what Joseph Smith did to find answers to his questions.</li>
<li>Class members could share how they have followed Joseph Smith's example in their search for truth and how God has answered them. President Russell M. Nelson's statement in "Additional Resources" suggests some ways we might seek truth from God.</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>Prayer allows us to communicate with God.</graphics-caption>
<heading>JOSEPH SMITH–HISTORY 1:15–20</heading>
<heading>Joseph Smith saw God the Father and His Son, Jesus Christ.</heading>
<ul>
<li>The First Vision revealed several truths about God that contradicted what many in Joseph's day believed. Class members could read Joseph Smith—History 1:15–20 and identify something they learn about God. Why is it important to know these truths about God?</li>
<li>If Joseph Smith were to visit our class, what would we ask him about his experience? The video "Ask of God: Joseph Smith's First Vision" (ChurchofJesusChrist.org) could give class members additional insights about Joseph Smith's First Vision (see also "Additional Resources"). Maybe they could ponder how they would complete a sentence like this one: "Because the First Vision happened, I know that . . ." What blessings have come into our lives because of the First Vision?</li>
<li>To add to the spirit of your discussion, class members could read or sing "Joseph Smith's First Prayer" (Hymns, no. 26). What does this hymn help us understand and feel about the First Vision? Perhaps a few class members could share how they have come to know for themselves that Joseph really saw God the Father and Jesus Christ in the Sacred Grove. Or you could invite the full-time missionaries (or a recently returned missionary) to visit the class and talk about how the First Vision has influenced the lives of people they teach.</li>
</ul>
<heading>JOSEPH SMITH–HISTORY 1:21–26</heading>
<heading>We can remain true to what we know, even if others reject us.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Class members may be able to identify with some of the things Joseph Smith experienced when he began to tell other people about his vision (see Joseph Smith—History 1:21–26). Perhaps they can share passages that inspire them when others challenge their beliefs.</li>
<li>If you know of ward members who have experienced opposition because they are members of the Church, consider asking them to come to class prepared to share how they keep their faith strong. What do we learn from Joseph Smith's example in Joseph Smith—History 1:21–26?</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>Follow Joseph's example.</heading>
<p>President Russell M. Nelson taught:
"The Prophet Joseph Smith set a pattern for us to follow in resolving our questions. Drawn to the promise of James that if we lack wisdom we may ask of God [see James 1:5], the boy Joseph took his question directly to Heavenly Father. He sought personal revelation, and his seeking opened this last dispensation.
"In like manner, what will your seeking open for you? What wisdom do you lack? What do you feel an urgent need to know or understand? Follow the example of the Prophet Joseph. Find a quiet place where you can regularly go. Humble yourself before God. Pour out your heart to your Heavenly Father. Turn to Him for answers and for comfort" ("Revelation for the Church, Revelation for Our Lives," Ensign or Liahona, May 2018, 95).</p>
<heading>Joseph Smith's First Vision.</heading>
<p>To read a description of the First Vision that draws on several of Joseph Smith's accounts, see Saints, 1:14–16.</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Seek your own inspiration.</b>Don't view these outlines as instructions that you must follow as you teach. Rather, use them to spark ideas and foster inspiration as you ponder the doctrine in the scriptures and the needs of the people you teach.</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<graphics-caption>He Called Me by Name, by Michael Malm</graphics-caption>
<heading>JANUARY 11–17</heading>
<heading>Doctrine and Covenants 2; Joseph Smith—History 1:27–65</heading>
<heading>"THE HEARTS OF THE CHILDREN SHALL TURN TO THEIR FATHERS"</heading>
<p>Before you read the ideas in this outline, study Doctrine and Covenants 2 and Joseph Smith—History 1:27–65, and record your spiritual impressions.</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>To encourage class members to share insights and experiences they had as they studied these scriptures, you could ask them to share a verse that caused them to ponder more deeply than usual. What impressed them about that verse?</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>JOSEPH SMITH–HISTORY 1:27–65</heading>
<heading>Joseph Smith was called by God to do His work.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Would your class benefit from reviewing the story in Joseph Smith—History 1:27–65? You could invite a class member to summarize it, or class members could tell the story to each other in pairs or small groups. Encourage them to include as many details as they can remember. How does this story strengthen our testimonies of Joseph Smith's divine calling? What lessons do we learn from this story about how God does His work?</li>
<li>Consider displaying objects or pictures that relate to the work Joseph Smith was called to do, such as a Book of Mormon or a picture of a temple. Class members could find verses in Joseph Smith—History 1:33–42 that teach about these aspects of the Prophet's mission. How does God's work for Joseph Smith relate to the work God has for us? What do our living prophets teach us about this work?</li>
</ul>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 2</heading>
<heading>Elijah came to turn our hearts to our ancestors.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Would your class benefit from a discussion about who Elijah was and about the sealing power he restored? Class members could read about Elijah in the Bible Dictionary or Guide to the Scriptures or review a story from his life (see 1 Kings 17–18). What does this information add to our understanding of Doctrine and Covenants 2? You might also talk about what it means to seal something. Maybe some objects could help, like a can of food, a plastic storage bag with a zipper lock, or a seal that ratifies a document. How might these objects help us understand what it means to seal families together? How does this power help fulfill the purpose of the earth's creation? (see Doctrine and Covenants 138:47–48 and the statement by President Russell M. Nelson in "Additional Resources"). To help class members see how the prophecy in Doctrine and Covenants 2 was fulfilled, you could discuss Doctrine and Covenants 110:13–16.</li>
<li>Perhaps learning about the "promises made to the fathers" (Doctrine and Covenants 2:2) would help those you teach better understand the priesthood power that Elijah was sent to restore. Who are "the fathers"? (see Doctrine and Covenants 27:9–10). What promises did the Lord make to Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob? (see Genesis 17:1–8; 22:16–18; 26:1–5, 24; 28:11–15; Abraham 2:8–11). What does it mean to "plant" these promises in our hearts? How can doing this help us turn our hearts to our ancestors?</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>Palmyra New York Temple</graphics-caption>
<ul>
<li>To inspire class members to turn their hearts to their ancestors, you could invite a few members to lead a discussion on the topic. Consider including the ward temple and family history consultant. You could begin by reading Doctrine and Covenants 2:2–3 and inviting discussion leaders to share experiences in which their hearts were turned toward their ancestors. What has happened in their lives that helped them wan learn about their family history? What suggestions can they give to help other class members get involved in family history and temple service? The statement by President Dallin H. Oaks in "Additional Resources" and the videos "The Promised Blessings of Family History" and "If We Put God First" (ChurchofJesusChrist.org) can also help inspire class members. You could also refer members to FamilySearch.org for ideas.</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>The purpose of the Creation.</heading>
<p>President Russell M. Nelson taught:
"Eternal life, made possible by the Atonement, is the supreme purpose of the Creation. To phrase that statement in its negative form, if families were not sealed in holy temples, the whole earth would be utterly wasted.
"The purposes of the Creation, the Fall, and the Atonement all converge on the sacred work done in temples of The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints" ("The Atonement," Ensign, Nov. 1996, 35). See also Moses 1:39.</p>
<heading>Everyone can do something.</heading>
<p>President Dallin H. Oaks taught: "In the work of redeeming the dead there are many tasks to be performed. . . . Our effort is not to compel everyone to do everything, but to encourage everyone to do something" ("Family History: 'In Wisdom and in Order," Ensign, June 1989, 6).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Include learners who didn't study the scriptures at home.</b>Make sure that all class members feel comfortable participating and contributing to the discussion, even those who may not have read at home.</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<graphics-caption>Harvest Time in France, by James Taylor Harwood</graphics-caption>
<heading>JANUARY 18–24</heading>
<heading>Doctrine and Covenants 3–5</heading>
<heading>"MY WORK SHALL GO FORTH"</heading>
<p>Studying Doctrine and Covenants 3–5 before you review the ideas in this outline will help you receive guidance from the Holy Ghost. This week's outline in Come, Follow Me—For Individuals and Families can help you understand the history that led to the revelations recorded in these sections.</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>Give class members a few minutes to review the scriptures they read at home and find a passage that they found meaningful. Then invite them to share what they learned with another person in the class.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 3:1–15</heading>
<heading>We should trust God rather than fearing man.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Like Joseph Smith, we all have experiences when we feel pressured by other people to do something we know is wrong. What truths do we learn from Doctrine and Covenants 3:1–15 that can help us remain faithful to God in such situations?</li>
<li>Joseph Smith needed to be chastened for fearing man more than God, but he also needed to be encouraged. Invite class members to look in section 3 for how the Lord both chastened and encouraged Joseph. For example, they could list on the board phrases from verses 1–15 containing the Lord's rebukes and other phrases containing His encouragement to repent and remain faithful. What does Joseph's experience teach us about how the Savior helps us overcome our mistakes?</li>
</ul>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 4</heading>
<heading>The Lord asks us to serve Him with all our heart.</heading>
<ul>
<li>The qualities describing the Lord's servants that are listed in Doctrine and Covenants 4:5–6 are also the qualities of Jesus Christ. To help class members learn more, you could invite them to choose one of the qualities and find definitions or additional scriptures that help them better understand the quality (see, for example, the statement by Sister Elaine S. Dalton in "Additional Resources"). You could invite a few people to share what they found. They could also share why the quality they chose is a requirement for service in God's kingdom. How can we further develop these qualities? (see verse 7).</li>
<li>Doctrine and Covenants 4 was addressed to Joseph Smith Sr., who wanted to know how he could help with the Lord's work. This section can also help any of us who desire to serve the Lord. Here's one way to study this section: class members could work in small groups to write a job description for servants of God, using section 4 as a guide. How are these qualifications different from other job descriptions? Why are these qualities essential in doing God's work? The statement by Elder David A. Bednar in "Additional Resources" can help class members understand the importance of developing these qualities.</li>
</ul>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 5</heading>
<heading>A witness of the truth comes to those who are humble and believing.</heading>
<ul>
<li>If the gold plates were displayed for the world to see, would that convince everyone that the Book of Mormon is true? Why or why not? (see Doctrine and Covenants 5:7). Perhaps class members could search section 5 for insights that could help them respond to someone who asks for evidence that the Book of Mormon is true. What did the Lord teach Joseph Smith and Martin Harris that can help us gain our own witness of gospel truths?</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>Martin Harris, by Lewis A. Ramsey</graphics-caption>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>Virtue means strength.</heading>
<p>Sister Elaine S. Dalton gave this explanation of virtue: "<i>Virtue</i>is a word we don't hear often in today's society, but the Latin root word<i>virtus</i>means strength. Virtuous women and men possess a quiet dignity and inner strength. They are confident because they are worthy to receive and be guided by the Holy Ghost" ("A Return to Virtue," Ensign or Liahona, Nov. 2008, 79).</p>
<heading>Becoming a missionary.</heading>
<p>Elder David A. Bednar said: "The process of becoming a missionary does not require a young man to wear a white shirt and tie [or a young woman to wear a dress] to school every day or to follow the missionary guidelines for going to bed and getting up. . . . But you can increase in your desire to serve God [see Doctrine and Covenants 4:3], and you can begin to think as missionaries think, to read what missionaries read, to pray as missionaries pray, and to feel what missionaries feel. You can avoid the worldly influences that cause the Holy Ghost to withdraw, and you can grow in confidence in recognizing and responding to spiritual promptings" ("Becoming a Missionary," Ensign or Liahona, Nov. 2005, 45–46).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Ask questions that encourage meaningful discussion.</b>Questions that have more than one right answer invite learners to respond based on their personal thoughts, feelings, and experiences. For example, you could ask, "How do you know when God is speaking to you?" (See Teaching in the Savior's Way, 33.)</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<heading>JANUARY 25–31</heading>
<heading>Doctrine and Covenants 6–9</heading>
<heading>"THIS IS THE SPIRIT OF REVELATION"</heading>
<p>Doctrine and Covenants 6–9 teaches valuable principles about receiving revelation. Apply these principles by seeking revelation about how to help class members learn from these sections.</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>To encourage class members to share their experiences studying Doctrine and Covenants 6–9, you might invite them to discuss, as appropriate, any spiritual impressions they received during their study. What messages did the Lord have for them?</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 6; 8–9</heading>
<heading>Heavenly Father speaks to me through "the Spirit of truth."</heading>
<ul>
<li>The Lord has a lot to teach us about personal revelation in these sections, and you may not be able to cover all of it in one class. It might help to divide the class into three groups and ask each group to search section 6, 8, or 9, looking for answers to questions like these: How does the Holy Ghost speak to us? How can we recognize personal revelation? How can we prepare ourselves to receive revelation? Then someone from each group could briefly share with the class what their group discovered. You might also encourage class members to share their own experiences with recognizing personal revelation. For example, is there anything in Doctrine and Covenants 6:22–24 that reminds us of experiences we have had?</li>
<li>Talking about personal revelation may be discouraging to people in your class who pray for guidance but don't feel that they receive any. It could help them to know that Oliver Cowdery struggled with similar feelings when he wasn't able to translate as easily as he had hoped. Maybe you could invite class members to search the Lord's counsel to Oliver in section 9. What messages in this section could help someone who feels the Lord isn't answering their prayers? The statements in "Additional Resources" could also help.</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>Oliver Cowdery, by Lewis A. Ramsey</graphics-caption>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 6–7</heading>
<heading>"Even as you desire of me so it shall be."</heading>
<ul>
<li>This week's outline in<i>Come, Follow Me—For Individuals and Families</i>suggests noting instances of words like desire in sections 6–7. Perhaps class members could share what they learned from that exercise, or you could do the activity together as a class. What do our daily actions teach us about our desires? How can the Lord help us change our desires?</li>
</ul>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 6:29–37</heading>
<heading>If we look to the Lord, He can help us overcome doubt and fear.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Why do we sometimes "fear. . . to do good"? (verse 33). Maybe class members could suggest some possible reasons, along with thoughts from Doctrine and Covenants 6:29–37 that give them courage to do good.</li>
<li>To begin a discussion about how Jesus Christ helps us "doubt not, fear not" (verse 36), you could ask class members to write on pieces of paper some things people might fear. (Elder Ronald A. Rasband gave some examples in his message "Be Not Troubled" [Ensign or Liahona, Nov. 2018, 18].) Then you could read aloud a few of these papers and discuss how the Savior and His atoning power can help us when we are afraid. Doctrine and Covenants 6:29–37 has some insights (see also 1 John 4:18). What does it mean to "look unto [Christ] in every thought"?(verse 36). How does this focus on the Savior help us when we face doubt or fear?</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>Understanding how Heavenly Father answers prayers.</heading>
<p>"In my life I have learned that sometimes I do not receive an answer to a prayer because the Lord knows I am not ready. When He does answer, it is often «here a little and there a little» [2 Nephi 28:30] because that is all that I can bear or all I am willing to do" (Robert D. Hales, "Waiting upon the Lord: Thy Will Be Done," Ensign or Liahona, Nov. 2011, 73).</p>
<p>"What do you do when you I have prepared carefully, have prayed fervently, waited a reasonable time for a response, and still do not feel an answer? You may want to express thanks when that occurs, for it is an evidence of His trust. When you are living worthily and your choice is consistent with the Savior's teachings and you need to act, proceed with trust. . . . When you are living righteously and are acting with trust, God will not let you proceed too far without a warning impression if you have made the wrong decision" (Richard G. Scott, "Using the Supernal Gift of Prayer," Ensign or Liahona, May 2007, 10).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Express confidence in learners' abilities.</b>Some people in your class may not be confident in their ability to learn the gospel. Consider how you can reassure them that as they strive to learn on their own, the Holy Ghost will teach them. (See Teaching in the Savior's Way, 29.)</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<graphics-caption>Replica of the original Book of Mormon manuscript.</graphics-caption>
<heading>FEBRUARY 1–7</heading>
<heading>Doctrine and Covenants 10–11</heading>
<heading>"THAT YOU MAY COME OFF CONQUEROR"</heading>
<p>What impressions did you have as you read Doctrine and Covenants 10–11? What thoughts came to you about the needs of the people you teach?</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>To give class members an opportunity to talk about what they learned in their personal and family scripture study, you could write on the board<i>Doctrine and Covenants 10 and Doctrine and Covenants 11</i>. A few class members could write, under either heading, the number of a verse where they found an important truth. Select a few of the verses, and invite class members to share the truths they found there.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 10:1–33</heading>
<heading>Satan seeks to destroy the work of God.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Doctrine and Covenants 10 can help class members recognize and resist Satan's efforts to destroy their faith. To give some historical context for this section, you might invite a class member to share the account of Martin Harris losing 116 pages of the Book of Mormon translation (see the section heading for Doctrine and Covenants 3 and Saints, 1:50–53). Class members could then search Doctrine and Covenants 10:1–33 to find Satan's plan for the lost pages. What do we learn from these verses about the ways Satan works and why he does these things? (see also verse 63). How is he working in similar ways in our day? How does the Lord help us conquer Satan in our lives?</li>
</ul>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 10:34–52</heading>
<heading>The Lord's "wisdom is greater than the cunning of the devil."</heading>
<ul>
<li>When we feel discouraged about our sins, we can find hope in knowing how the Lord compensated for the sin that Joseph Smith and Martin Harris committed when they disobeyed the Lord and lost 116 pages of the Book of Mormon translation. Consider how you can help class members find hope in this account. For example, you could invite them to share something they learn about the Lord from Doctrine and Covenants 10:34–52 (see also Doctrine and Covenants 3:1–3). Class members could share how they have seen that the Lord's "wisdom is greater than the cunning of the devil" (Doctrine and Covenants 10:43). How does this knowledge strengthen our faith in Him?</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>Mormon Abridging the Plates, by Tom Lovell</graphics-caption>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 11</heading>
<heading>If we ask of God, we will receive.</heading>
<ul>
<li>This week's outline in<i>Come, Follow Me—For Individuals and Families</i>invites us to read Doctrine and Covenants 11 as if it were written for us. Perhaps class members would be willing to share something from the section that is particularly relevant to them. How do they plan to apply what they learned?</li>
<li>One way to encourage discussion about Doctrine and Covenants 11 is to invite class members to find a principle in the section and then write a question about it. Such questions might include "What does it mean to cleave unto Christ with all of your heart?" (verse 19) or "How do we obtain God's word?" (verse 21). Class members could put their questions at the top of a piece of paper and pass their papers around the room, adding thoughts and possible answers to each other's questions. (It might help to divide the class into small groups first.) Class members could then share with the class some of the insights that others wrote about their question.</li>
</ul>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 11:8–26</heading>
<heading>God will give us His Spirit as we prepare ourselves in His way.</heading>
<ul>
<li><p>Would members of your class benefit from talking about how to recognize personal revelation through the Spirit? If so, you might begin a discussion by inviting them to imagine that they were asked to write some truths about how to receive personal revelation. What would they include from Doctrine and Covenants 11:8–26? For example, what would they write about preparing to receive guidance for our lives and answers to our questions? What would they say about how to recognize answers when they come? Invite class members to ponder how they will apply what they have learned as they strive to seek personal revelation.</p>
<p>As part of this activity, you could share this statement from Sister Julie B. Beck, former Relief Society General President: "The ability to qualify for, receive, and act on personal revelation is the single most important skill that can be acquired in this life" ("And upon the Handmaids in Those Days Will I Pour Out My Spirit," Ensign or Liahona, May 2010, 11).</p></li>
</ul>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Include those who are struggling.</b>What can you do when a class member seems disconnected from the rest of the class? Sometimes he or she just needs to be included. Consider asking this person to participate in an upcoming lesson. If he or she does not respond to your efforts at first, continue to show love and concern. (See Teaching in the Savior's Way, 8–9.)</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<heading>FEBRUARY 8–14</heading>
<heading>Doctrine and Covenants 12–13; Joseph Smith—History 1:66–75</heading>
<heading>"UPON YOU MY FELLOW SERVANTS"</heading>
<p>Just as the Holy Ghost enlightened the minds of Joseph Smith and Oliver Cowdery concerning the scriptures, He can inspire you as you prayerfully study Doctrine and Covenants 12–13 and Joseph Smith—History 1:66–75.</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>One way to encourage sharing is to ask class members how they study the scriptures. What did they do to find insights in the scriptures this week?</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 13</heading>
<heading>The Aaronic Priesthood was restored by John the Baptist.</heading>
<ul>
<li>One way to discuss the truths in Doctrine and Covenants 13 would be for class members to talk about how this section might help youth better understand the Aaronic Priesthood. What does section 13 teach about the Aaronic Priesthood that young men and young women should understand? To give everyone an opportunity to participate, you could ask class members to discuss this question in pairs and then share what they learned from each other with the class.</li>
<li>This week's outline in<i>Come, Follow Me—For Individuals and Families</i>suggests resources that could help explain some of the phrases in Doctrine and Covenants 13. You could ask class members to share what they learned from studying these resources. To prompt a discussion about the keys mentioned in this section, you could display a set of keys and invite class members to talk about what keys allow us to do. The explanation by Sister Ruth and Elder Dale G. Renlund in "Additional Resources" could also help. What blessings do the keys of the Aaronic Priesthood give us access to? How would our lives be different without these blessings?</li>
<li>Part of the beauty of the restored gospel is that it engages us in the same work as the men and women in the scriptures: building the kingdom of God on earth. This makes us, in a sense, "fellow servants" with them. What does it mean to be a fellow servant in the Lord's work? Matthew 3:13–17; Luke 1:13–17; 3:2–20 can help class members better understand the work John the Baptist did.</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>Joseph Smith Baptizes Oliver Cowdery, by Del Parson</graphics-caption>
<heading>JOSEPH SMITH–HISTORY 1:66–75</heading>
<heading>Ordinances give us access to God's power.</heading>
<ul>
<li>To give class members a chance to testify to each other about the blessings that come from receiving priesthood ordinances, you could invite them to review Joseph Smith—History 1:66–75, including the note to verse 71, looking for blessings Joseph and Oliver received after their baptism and priesthood ordination. How do ordinances provide spiritual power? Class members could then share their own experiences when they have felt the power of God that comes from receiving priesthood ordinances such as baptism, the sacrament, or temple ordinances. You might also show the video "Blessings of the Priesthood" (ChurchofJesusChrist.org) as part of the discussion.</li>
<li>Class members may benefit from creating a chart that shows blessings that come from the ordinances of the priesthood. For example, you could write on the board the headings Ordinances and Blessings. Class members could search scriptures like the following to fill out the chart: John 14:26; Acts 2:38; Doctrine and Covenants 84:19–22; 131:1–4; Joseph Smith—History 1:73–74. They could also include other blessings they have received because of these ordinances. Perhaps they could share experiences when they felt that the ordinances they received brought the Savior's power into their lives.</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>What are priesthood keys?</heading>
<p>Elder Dale G. Renlund and his wife, Ruth, offered this explanation about priesthood keys:
"The term<i>priesthood keys</i>is used in two different ways. The first refers to a specific right or privilege conferred upon all who receive the Aaronic or Melchizedek Priesthood. . . . For instance, Aaronic Priesthood holders receive the keys of the ministering of angels and the keys of the preparatory gospel of repentance and of baptism by immersion for the remission of sins (see Doctrine and Covenants 13:1; 84:26–27). Melchizedek Priesthood holders receive the key of the mysteries of the kingdom, the key of the knowledge of God, and the keys of all the spiritual blessings of the Church (see Doctrine and Covenants 84:19; 107:18). . . .
"The second way the term<i>priesthood keys</i>is used refers to leadership. Priesthood leaders receive additional priesthood keys, the right to preside over an organizational division of the Church or a quorum. In this regard, priesthood keys are the authority and power to direct, lead, and govern in the Church" (The Melchizedek Priesthood: Understanding the Doctrine, Living the Principles [2018], 26).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Bear your testimony often.</b>"Your simple, sincere witness of spiritual truth can have a powerful influence on those you teach. . . . It need not be eloquent or lengthy" (Teaching in the Savior's Way, 11). Consider sharing your personal witness of the Aaronic Priesthood as you discuss Doctrine and Covenants 13.</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<heading>FEBRUARY 15–21</heading>
<heading>Doctrine and Covenants 14–17</heading>
<heading>"STAND AS A WITNESS"</heading>
<p>Think about the doctrine and events described in Doctrine and Covenants 14–17. How will you inspire the people you teach to "stand as a witness of [these] things"? (Doctrine and Covenants 14:8).</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>What did members of your class find meaningful in their personal or family scripture study? Perhaps you could invite the class to share one insight about participating in the Lord's work from each section in Doctrine and Covenants 14–17.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 14–16</heading>
<heading>The Lord invites us to participate in His work.</heading>
<ul>
<li>What do class members know about the Whitmer family? (see Saints, 1:68–69). It may be helpful for them to list on the board some facts about the Whitmers. How do these facts help us better understand the Lord's counsel to the Whitmers in sections 14–16? For example, why might the Lord have compared His work to harvesting a field?</li>
<li>To allow class members to share their thoughts about participating in the Lord's work, you could write the following references on the board: Doctrine and Covenants 14:1; 14:2–4; 14:5, 8; 14:6–7; 14:9–11; 15:6. Class members could read one of these scripture passages in pairs and discuss what they learn about the work of the Lord. A few of the pairs could share with the class what they discussed.</li>
<li>Invite class members to share their experiences helping others come closer to the Savior, including as full-time or service missionaries and through ministering. How have they seen the Lord's words in Doctrine and Covenants 15:6 and 16:6 fulfilled in their lives? What do we learn from these sections that can help us prepare to share the gospel?</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>Illustration of wheat field workers by Greg Newbold</graphics-caption>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 17</heading>
<heading>We can remain true to what we know, even if others reject us.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Why did the Lord provide witnesses of the Book of Mormon? Class members could share ideas that occurred to them as they read Doctrine and Covenants 17. Additional ideas may be found in the scriptures referred to in the heading to section 17 or in "The Testimony of Three Witnesses," found at the beginning of the Book of Mormon. How has the testimony of the Three Witnesses influenced our testimonies of the Book of Mormon?</li>
<li>Even if we have not seen angels or handled the gold plates, we can still bear witness of the Book of Mormon. What do class members find in section 17 (including the section heading) that they feel applies to them? If someone asked why we believe the Book of Mormon is true, what would we say? Perhaps class members could write a brief response, and you could invite a few to share what they wrote. The quote by President Ezra Taft Benson in "Additional Resources" could inspire members to bear their witness of the Book of Mormon to others.</li>
<li>It could be inspiring to have a class member share the experiences of other witnesses of the gold plates (see "The Testimony of Eight Witnesses" in the Book of Mormon and Mary Whitmer's experience in Saints, 1:70–71). What do we learn from the experiences of these witnesses?</li>
<li>You might share selections from the video "A Day for the Eternities" (ChurchofJesusChrist.org) as part of your discussion about the Book of Mormon witnesses (the portion about the Three Witnesses begins at about 15:00).</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>Sharing our witness of the Book of Mormon.</heading>
<p>President Ezra Taft Benson gave the following invitation to Church members in 1988:
"The Book of Mormon is the instrument that God designed to «sweep the earth as with a flood, to gather out [His] elect.» (Moses 7:62.) This sacred volume of scripture needs to become more central in our preaching, our teaching, and our missionary work.
". . . In this age of the electronic media and the mass distribution of the printed word, God will hold us accountable if we do not now move the Book of Mormon in a monumental way.
"We have the Book of Mormon, we have the members, we have the missionaries, we have the resources, and the world has the need. The time is now!
"My beloved brothers and sisters, we hardly fathom the power of the Book of Mormon, nor the divine role it must play, nor the extent to which it must be moved" (Teachings of Presidents of the Church: Ezra Taft Benson [2014], 143–44).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Ask questions that invite testimony.</b>An inspired question can be a powerful way to invite the Spirit. For example, when teaching Doctrine and Covenants 14:9, you could ask a question like "How have you come to know that Jesus Christ is 'a light which cannot be hid in darkness'?" (See Teaching in the Savior's Way, 32.)</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<graphics-caption>Martin Harris Farm, by Al Rounds</graphics-caption>
<heading>FEBRUARY 22–28</heading>
<heading>Doctrine and Covenants 18–19</heading>
<heading>"THE WORTH OF SOULS IS GREAT"</heading>
<p>It is only through the Holy Ghost that a person's heart can change. President Henry B. Eyring taught, "If you teach doctrinal principles, the Holy Ghost will come" ("Discussion with Elder Richard G. Scott and Elder Henry B. Eyring" [Church Educational System satellite training broadcast, Aug. 11, 2003]).</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>To prompt class members to share their experiences with the scriptures, read together Doctrine and Covenants 18:34–36. Then ask class members to share a verse they read this week in which they recognized the voice of the Lord.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 18:10–16; 19:15–20, 39–41</heading>
<heading>The Lord rejoices when we repent.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Many people associate repentance with negative feelings. How can the Lord's words in Doctrine and Covenants 18 and 19 help class members see repentance as something joyful? You could write on the board<i>Repentance is</i>__ and ask class members to suggest ways to complete this sentence, based on what they've read from sections 18 and 19. (Consider reviewing Doctrine and Covenants 18:10–16; 19:15–20, 39–41 in class.)</li>
<li>What does it mean to "cry repentance"? (Doctrine and Covenants 18:14). Perhaps class members could consider this question as they read Doctrine and Covenants 18:10–16. Why do people sometimes choose not to repent? How can we inspire those we love to come unto the Savior and receive forgiveness? Encourage class members to look for something in Doctrine and Covenants 18:10–16 or 19:15–20 that could help.</li>
</ul>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 18:10–16</heading>
<heading>"The worth of souls is great in the sight of God."</heading>
<ul>
<li>How can you help class members understand how valuable each of us is in God's sight? Maybe they could read Doctrine and Covenants 18:10–16 and share experiences in which they came to understand their worth to God. How do these verses affect the way we view ourselves? other people? How does God show us that we are of great worth to Him?</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>Worth of a Soul, by Liz Lemon Swindle</graphics-caption>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 19:15–19</heading>
<heading>Jesus Christ suffered for all mankind.</heading>
<ul>
<li>How can you help class members feel the witness of the Holy Ghost as they ponder the Savior's description of His own atoning suffering? (Doctrine and Covenants 19:15–19). Perhaps you could invite someone to sing a favorite hymn about the Savior. You could also display a picture of the Savior and invite class members to read verses 15–19; then they could write down their thoughts and feelings. (Elder D. Todd Christofferson's words in "Additional Resources" could also deepen class members' appreciation for the Savior's suffering.) A sentence like this on the board could help class members ponder:<i>I am grateful for the Atonement of Jesus Christ because</i>. . . A few class members may be willing to share what they wrote and bear their testimonies of Jesus Christ.</li>
</ul>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 19:16–26, 34–41</heading>
<heading>Doing God's will often requires sacrifice.</heading>
<ul>
<li>As class members face situations in which they must make sacrifices for the gospel, it may be inspiring for them to learn about the sacrifice Martin Harris made so the Book of Mormon could be published. Maybe you could invite someone to come to class prepared to tell about Martin's decision to mortgage his farm to pay for the printing of the Book of Mormon (see Saints, 1:76–78). What verses from section 19 might have helped him make his decision? You may want to invite class members to share how the Book of Mormon has blessed them and how thankful they are for Martin Harris's sacrifice and for others who sacrificed so the book could be published.</li>
<li>Perhaps someone in the class could share a sacrifice they have made for the Lord. This may lead class members to think about their own willingness to sacrifice. Encourage them to share anything they find from Doctrine and Covenants 19 that inspires them to make sacrifices in order to do God's will (see especially verses 16–26, 34–41).</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>The cost of God's love.</heading>
<p>Referring to Doctrine and Covenants 19:18, Elder D. Todd Christofferson said: "Let us consider the cost of God's precious love. . . . His agony in Gethsemane and on the cross was greater than any mortal could bear. Nevertheless, because of His love for His Father and for us, He endured, and as a consequence, He can offer us both immortality and eternal life" ("Abide in My Love," Ensign or Liahona, Nov. 2016, 50).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Create an environment that invites the Spirit.</b>There are many ways you can invite the Spirit into your class. Prelude music can encourage reverence. Expressions of love and testimony can create a warm, spiritual atmosphere. (See Teaching in the Savior's Way, 15.)</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<graphics-caption>Peter Whitmer Home, by Al Rounds</graphics-caption>
<heading>MARCH 1–7</heading>
<heading>Doctrine and Covenants 20–22</heading>
<heading>"THE RISE OF THE CHURCH OF CHRIST"</heading>
<p>Record your spiritual impressions as you study Doctrine and Covenants 20–22. Some of these impressions may lead to ideas that will help you when you teach.</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>During their study at home, class members may have gained insights about the blessings of having the true Church on earth. Invite them to share a passage from these sections that illustrates why they are thankful the Church was restored.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 20–21</heading>
<heading>The Church of Jesus Christ has been restored.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Class members may benefit from studying the similarities between The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints and the Church that Christ established anciently. You could draw on the board a chart with four columns labeled<i>Doctrine, Ordinances, Priesthood Authority,</i>and<i>Prophets</i>. You could provide the following references about Christ's Church in ancient times: Matthew 16:15–19; John 7:16–17; Ephesians 2:19–22; 3 Nephi 11:23–26; Moroni 4–5. Class members could identify what each passage teaches about Christ's Church and write the reference in the appropriate column on the board. (Some references could apply to more than one column.) They could do the same for the following references about Christ's restored Church: Doctrine do and Covenants 20:17–25, 60, 72–79; 21:1–2. What you learn about the Restoration of Christ's Church from this comparison?</li>
</ul>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 20:37, 75–79; 22</heading>
<heading>Sacred ordinances help us become like the Savior.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Give class members time to study the qualifications for baptism described in Doctrine and Covenants 20:37, and ask them to ponder questions like these: How do these qualifications help us prepare to be baptized into the Lord's Church? What does it mean to take Christ's name upon ourselves? (see Mosiah 5:5–12). What helps you maintain your "determination to serve [Jesus Christ] to the end"?</li>
<li>What does section 22 teach about baptism? Ask class members to imagine they have a friend who has been baptized into another church. They could read this section to find counsel to help their friend understand why baptism into the Savior's restored Church is necessary. Class members could role-play this scenario as a class or in pairs.</li>
<li>Read Doctrine and Covenants 20:75–79 together, and invite class members to consider what these verses teach about the Savior and His power in our lives. What words or phrases stand out when we read the sacrament prayers this way? Why is it important to partake of the sacrament each week?</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>The sacrament is a sacred ordinance.</graphics-caption>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 20:38–60</heading>
<heading>Priesthood service blesses Church members and their families.</heading>
<ul>
<li><p>The description of priesthood duties in Doctrine and Covenants 20:38–60 could help members of your class expand their understanding of priesthood service. Maybe you could invite them to imagine that a recently baptized friend or family member is about to be ordained to a priesthood office. How would they use these verses to help him understand his duties? What examples would they share to help him understand how fulfilling those duties can help him become more like Jesus Christ? Perhaps they could role-play this conversation.</p>
<p>In addition, how might they use these verses to help a newly baptized sister see how she can participate in the work described here? (The statement in "Additional Resources" could help.)</p></li>
</ul>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 21:4–7</heading>
<heading>We are blessed when we receive the Lord's word through His prophet.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Doctrine and Covenants 21 contains powerful statements about following the Lord's prophet. To help class members ponder and discuss these statements, ask them to search verses 4–7 for a phrase they would like to understand better and to write the phrase on the board. Choose a few of the phrases, and discuss as a class what they might mean. What do these phrases teach us about following the Lord's prophet?</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>We all work with priesthood power.</heading>
<p>"Men are ordained to priesthood offices, while both women and men are invited to experience the power and blessings of the priesthood in their lives. . . .
". . . [Women] preach and pray in congregations, fill numerous positions of leadership and service, participate in priesthood councils at the local and general levels, and serve formal proselytizing missions across the globe. In these and other ways, women exercise priesthood authority even though they are not ordained to priesthood office. . . .
". . . In ecclesiastical callings, temple ordinances, family relationships, and quiet, individual ministry, Latter-day Saint women and men go forward with priesthood power and authority. This interdependence of men and women in accomplishing God's work through His power is central to the gospel of Jesus Christ" (Gospel Topics, "Joseph Smith's Teachings about Priesthood, Temple, Women," topics.ChurchofJesusChrist.org).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>We learn together.</b>As a teacher, you are learning with the rest of your class. Show your willingness to learn from them by listening to their insights.</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<heading>MARCH 8–14</heading>
<heading>Doctrine and Covenants 23–26</heading>
<heading>"STRENGTHEN THE CHURCH"</heading>
<p>Before reading this outline, read Doctrine and Covenants 23–26 and ponder the principles you feel will strengthen the members of your class. Then consider what resources will help you teach, including those suggested in this outline.</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>What blessings have we experienced as we "let [our] time be devoted to the studying of the scriptures"? (Doctrine and Covenants 26:1). How have we felt the Spirit in our homes? Perhaps class members could share how they have overcome obstacles or distractions to devote time to personal and family scripture study.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 23–26</heading>
<heading>We can all strengthen the Church.</heading>
<ul>
<li>You may want to explore with class members what it means to "exhort the church" (Doctrine and Covenants 25:7). Maybe someone could share dictionary definitions of<i>exhort</i>or examples of exhortation they have seen. What opportunities do we have to exhort one another? How does this strengthen the Church? What else do we learn in Doctrine and Covenants 23–26 that can help us strengthen the Church? You might also discuss how these principles apply to strengthening our homes. To apply these principles to our ministering efforts, you could review parts of Sister Bonnie H. Cordon's message "Becoming a Shepherd" (Ensign or Liahona, Nov. 2018, 74–76).</li>
</ul>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 24</heading>
<heading>The Savior can lift us "up out of [our] afflictions."</heading>
<ul>
<li>The revelation in Doctrine and Covenants 24 was given to "strengthen, encourage, and instruct" Joseph and Oliver during a time of trial (Doctrine and Covenants 24, section heading; see also Saints, 1:94–96). You might invite the class to search this section for evidence that the Lord was aware of Joseph and his situation. How did the Lord address Joseph's needs? How does He do the same for us today? Consider asking class members to share experiences when they felt that the Lord was aware of their personal circumstances and lifted them during their afflictions.</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>He Healed Many of Diverse Diseases, by J. Kirk Richards</graphics-caption>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 25</heading>
<heading>Emma Smith is "an elect lady."</heading>
<ul>
<li>To help class members find personal relevance in the Lord's revelation to Emma Smith, consider this activity: Ask half of the class to search section 25 for things the Lord asked Emma to do, and ask the other half to search for things He promised He would do. Invite them to list what they find and share it with each other. A few class members could share principles that are especially meaningful to them.</li>
<li>What words and phrases in section 25 support the Lord's declaration to Emma Smith, "Thou art an elect lady"? (verse 3). Class members could also discuss how Emma lived the principles in this revelation. Helpful resources include the video "An Elect Lady" (ChurchofJesusChrist.org), "Thou Art an Elect Lady" (Revelations in Context, 33–39), and "Voices of the Restoration" in this week's outline in<i>Come, Follow Me—For Individuals and Families.</i></li>
<li>According to Doctrine and Covenants 25:11–12, how does the Lord feel about sacred music? Perhaps the class could discuss ways to use hymns to invite the Spirit into their homes.</li>
</ul>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 25:5, 14</heading>
<heading>We should seek to have a "spirit of meekness."</heading>
<ul>
<li>The Lord counseled Emma to "continue in the spirit of meekness" (Doctrine and Covenants 25:14; see also verse 5). To explore what this might mean, you could write<i>Meekness</i>on the board and invite class members to write next to it what that word makes them think of. Then they could search section 25 for words and phrases that they feel are related to meekness and then share what they find. Consider sharing the statement by Elder David A. Bednar in "Additional Resources." Why is it important to be meek?</li>
</ul>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 25:10, 13</heading>
<heading>We should seek for the things of a better world.</heading>
<ul>
<li>To help class members apply the Lord's counsel to "lay aside the things of this world, and seek for the things of a better" (Doctrine and Covenants 25:10), you could ask them to list examples of "things of this world" and examples of "things of a better [world]." What advice can we share with each other to help us focus on eternal things? How does the counsel in verse 13 relate to this goal?</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>Meekness is strength.</heading>
<p>Elder David A. Bednar explained: "The Christlike quality of meekness often is misunderstood in our contemporary world. Meekness is strong, not weak; active, not passive; courageous, not timid; restrained, not excessive; modest, not self-aggrandizing; and gracious, not brash. A meek person is not easily provoked, pretentious, or overbearing and readily acknowledges the accomplishments of others" ("Meek and Lowly of Heart," Ensign or Liahona, May 2018, 32).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Testify of promised blessings.</b>When you invite class members to act on what they are learning, testify of the blessings God has promised (see Teaching in the Savior's Way, 35).</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<heading>MARCH 15–21</heading>
<heading>Doctrine and Covenants 27–28</heading>
<heading>"ALL THINGS MUST BE DONE IN ORDER"</heading>
<p>Although the events that prompted the revelations in Doctrine and Covenants 27–28 happened in a different time and place, the principles taught in these sections have relevance today. What principles might bless members of your class in the situations they are facing?</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>Give class members a few minutes to review Doctrine and Covenants 27–28 and find a verse or a phrase they find meaningful. To give everyone an opportunity to share, you could divide class members into pairs to share what they found.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 27:1–2</heading>
<heading>We should take the sacrament with an eye single to God's glory.</heading>
<ul>
<li><p>To encourage discussion about Doctrine and Covenants 27:1–2, consider writing a question like this on the board: What did the Savior teach us about the purpose of the sacrament? Class members could look for phrases in these verses that help them answer the question. They may be willing to share impressions they have received about how to have a more sacred experience when partaking of the sacrament.</p>
<p>Class members may find additional insights by reading what the Savior said when He instituted the sacrament (see Luke 22:19–20; 3 Nephi 18:1–11; see also the video "The Last Supper" on ChurchofJesusChrist.org). If the Savior were present in our sacrament meeting, what might we do differently?</p></li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>The sacrament contains symbols of the Savior's sacrifice.</graphics-caption>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 27:15–18</heading>
<heading>The armor of God will help us withstand evil.</heading>
<ul>
<li>How can you help class members understand how to use the armor of God to withstand the evil in our day? Consider asking someone to draw on the board the armor described in verses 15–18. Class members could then share any insights they discovered in their personal study about the pieces of armor. Or the class could read Doctrine and Covenants 27:15–18 and label the pieces of armor on the board and the parts of the body they protect. What does it mean to put on the armor of God? Perhaps class members could talk about how the Lord protects us from evil when we put on the armor of God.</li>
<li>If you teach youth, you may want to connect Doctrine and Covenants 27:15–18 with the standards in<i>For the Strength of Youth.</i>For example, class members could read the verses and discuss why we need the armor of God. Then they could work in pairs and review one of the standards in<i>For the Strength of Youth.</i>What do we learn from these sources about Satan's attacks against us? How can the armor of God help us withstand these attacks? How can we put on His armor?</li>
</ul>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 28</heading>
<heading>The living prophet receives revelation for the Lord's Church.</heading>
<ul>
<li>To help class members learn about the role of the prophet, you could review the experience that led Joseph Smith to pray and receive section 28 (see the section heading), and then you could read verses 2–3, 6–7, 11–13. How does Satan try to convince us to follow those whom the Lord has not appointed? You might invite class members to share experiences that strengthened their testimonies that the prophet receives revelation for the Church.</li>
<li>One way for class members to review Doctrine and Covenants 28 is to imagine that they know someone who recently received a new calling in the Church. What could we share from Doctrine and Covenants 28:1–6, 13–16 to help that person in his or her calling? The quotation in "Additional Resources" could add insights to the discussion.</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>Counsel about personal revelation.</heading>
<p>President Joseph F. Smith and his counselors in the First Presidency taught:
"When visions, dreams, tongues, prophecy, impressions or any extraordinary gift or inspiration, convey something out of harmony with the accepted revelations of the Church or contrary to the decisions of its constituted authorities, Latter-day Saints may know that it is not of God, no matter how plausible it may appear. In secular as well as spiritual affairs, Saints may receive Divine guidance and revelation affecting themselves, but this does not convey authority to direct others. . . .
"The history of the Church records many pretended revelations claimed by imposters or zealots who believed in the manifestations they sought to lead other persons to accept, and in every instance, disappointment, sorrow and disaster ha resulted therefrom" (Joseph F. Smith, Anthon H. Lund, Charles W. Penrose, "A Warning Voice," Improvement Era, Sept. 1913, 1148–49).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Focus on true doctrine.</b>President Boyd K. Packer taught, "True doctrine, understood, changes attitudes and behavior" ("Do Not Fear," Ensign or Liahona, May 2004, 79). As we teach, we must focus on the teachings of Jesus Christ if we want to help bring souls unto Him.</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<graphics-caption>Every Knee Shall Bow, by J. Kirk Richards</graphics-caption>
<heading>MARCH 22–28</heading>
<heading>Doctrine and Covenants 29</heading>
<heading>JESUS CHRIST WILL GATHER HIS PEOPLE</heading>
<p>The most important way to prepare to teach Doctrine and Covenants 29 is to study it prayerfully and seek the guidance of the Spirit. Consider other ways to invite the Spirit into your life, such as fasting, attending the temple, or serving others.</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>In Doctrine and Covenants 29:5, the Lord told the Saints, "Lift up your hearts and be glad." You could invite class members to share something that they learned in their personal or family study that causes them to "lift up [their] hearts and be glad."</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 29</heading>
<heading>Heavenly Father prepared a plan for our exaltation.</heading>
<ul>
<li>One way to encourage learning at home is to build on activities found in the current week's outline in<i>Come, Follow Me—For Individuals and Families.</i>For example, you could list on the board parts of the plan of salvation, such as<i>premortal life, Creation, the Atonement of Jesus Christ,</i>and so on. Class members could share what they learn from Doctrine and Covenants 29 about these parts of the plan. You might even have them share what they would teach from this section to someone who doesn't know about God's plan.</li>
</ul>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 29:1–8, 14–21</heading>
<heading>Jesus Christ will gather His people before His Second Coming.</heading>
<ul>
<li>To help class members understand why Jesus Christ gathers His people, you could invite them to read verses 1–8 and discuss questions about the gathering, such as: How have we experienced Christ gathering and protecting us, like a hen gathers and protects her chickens? How do we gather to the Savior? (see, for example, verse 2). Class members could share how they have been blessed by gathering and worshipping with other members of the Church.</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>How Many Times, by Liz Lemon Swindle</graphics-caption>
<ul>
<li>To help class members think about their responsibility to help Heavenly Father gather His children, you could share President Russell M. Nelson's words in "Additional Resources." Or you could show the video "A Witness of God" (ChurchofJesusChrist.org). What do we learn about the gathering from these messages? How do these messages reinforce what the Lord says in Doctrine and Covenants 29:1–8?</li>
<li>Some of the latter-day events described in Doctrine and Covenants 29:14–21 may be distressing to class members. Let them share how they feel. Why does the Lord warn us about these events? What reassuring truths do we learn about the Savior and the gathering from verses 1–8? How does gathering help us look forward to these events with faith instead of fear? As part of your discussion, you could sing a hymn about gathering, such as "Israel, Israel, God Is Calling" (Hymns, no. 7), and discuss what the hymn teaches about the gathering of Israel.</li>
</ul>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 29:34–35</heading>
<heading>Every commandment of the Lord is spiritual.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Even though some commandments may seem temporal, all commandments are spiritual to the Lord. To understand this truth, class members could read together verses 34–35 and list some commandments on the board, along with the spiritual principles and blessings related to each. They could share examples from their lives or from the scriptures that have helped them see the spiritual nature of God's commandments. How does this activity affect the way we see commandments?</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 29</heading>
<heading>Participating in the gathering of Israel.</heading>
<p>President Russell M. Nelson taught:
"These surely<i>are</i>the latter days, and the Lord is hastening His work to gather Israel. That gathering is the most important thing taking place on earth today. Nothing else compares in magnitude, nothing else compares in importance, nothing else compares in majesty. And if you choose to, if you want to, you can be a big part of it. You can be a big part of something big, something grand, something majestic!
"When we speak of the<i>gathering,</i>we are simply saying this fundamental truth: every one of our Heavenly Father's children, on both sides of the veil, deserves to hear the message of the restored gospel of Jesus Christ. They decide for themselves if they want to know more. . . .
"Our Heavenly Father has reserved many of His most noble spirits — perhaps, I might say, His finest team — for this final phase. Those noble spirits — those finest players, those heroes — are<i>you!</i>" ("Hope of Israel" [worldwide devotional for youth, June 3, 2018], ChurchofJesusChrist.org).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Teach clearly and simply.</b>Rather than trying to entertain your class, teach doctrine clearly and simply. You can trust that "the virtue of the word of God" will have a "more powerful effect upon the minds of the people than . . . anything else" (Alma 31:5).</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<heading>MARCH 29–APRIL 4</heading>
<heading>Easter</heading>
<heading>"I AM HE WHO LIVETH, I AM HE WHO WAS SLAIN"</heading>
<p>Nothing is more important for us to understand than the Atonement of Jesus Christ. Think about the people who will be attending your class; what will help them deepen their faith in Jesus Christ?</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>As members of your class have studied the Doctrine and Covenants this year, they may have found passages about the Savior that are meaningful to them. Begin class by giving them opportunities to share these passages. How has our study of the Doctrine and Covenants so far deepened our faith in Jesus Christ?</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>Jesus Christ accomplished a "perfect atonement."</heading>
<ul>
<li>Because the Atonement of Jesus Christ is such an essential doctrine, consider spending sufficient time ensuring that class members understand it. To do this, you could write on the board questions like these:<i>What is the Atonement of Jesus Christ? How does it affect my daily life? How does it affect my eternal life? How do I receive the Savior's redeeming power in my life?</i>Give class members a few minutes to ponder these questions and to look for scriptures that help answer them. Class members could write their scripture references on the board, and you could discuss a few of them as a class. Here are some examples: Luke 22:39–44; 1 John 1:7; 2 Nephi 2:6–9; Mosiah 3:5–13, 17–18; Alma 7:11–14; Moroni 10:32–33; Doctrine and Covenants 19:16–19; 45:3–5.</li>
<li>It might be meaningful for class members to watch the video "The Savior Suffers in Gethsemane" (ChurchofJesusChrist.org) before reading the Savior's own words about His suffering in Doctrine and Covenants 19:16–19. How do these verses deepen our appreciation of Jesus Christ's sacrifice? Other Easter videos you might share are listed in "Additional Resources."</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>Lord of Prayer, by Yongsung Kim</graphics-caption>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 76:11–14, 20–24; 110:1–10</heading>
<heading>The Prophet Joseph Smith testified that Jesus Christ lives.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Joseph Smith saw the risen Savior and bore a powerful witness that Jesus Christ lives. To help class members study Joseph Smith's testimony, you could divide them into two groups and assign each group to read either Doctrine and Covenants 76:11–14, 20–24 or 110:1–10. Invite each class member to find at least one word in these verses that describes the Savior. Class members could take turns writing the words they found on the board, and you could use these words to guide a discussion about the Savior's attributes and power. How does Joseph Smith's testimony strengthen our faith in the divinity and mission of Jesus Christ?</li>
<li>Some class members may have connected teachings in the Doctrine and Covenants with words and principles in the hymn "I Know That My Redeemer Lives" (Hymns, no. 136; see this week's outline in Come, Follow Me—For Individuals and Families). Maybe they would be willing to share what they discovered. You could also read or sing this hymn as a class and look for connections with the following scriptures: Doctrine and Covenants 6:34; 45:3–5; 84:77; 98:18; 138:23. How have we come to know that our Redeemer lives?</li>
</ul>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 29:26–27; 42:45–46; 63:49; 88:14–17, 27–31; 93:33–34</heading>
<heading>Because of Jesus Christ, we will be resurrected.</heading>
<ul>
<li>To help class members discuss what the Doctrine and Covenants teaches about resurrection, you could invite them to imagine that a friend or family member asks what it means to be resurrected. How could we help that person understand what resurrection is? Encourage class members to search Doctrine and Covenants 88:14–17, 27–31 for something that might help. Other helpful scripture references include Alma 11:40–45 and Alma 40:21–23. What would we share to help our friend or family member feel the joy and hope that comes from the doctrine of resurrection?</li>
<li>How might you help class members contemplate the Savior's gift of resurrection? Perhaps you could write on the board<i>Because of Jesus Christ . . .</i>and invite class members to look in the following passages for words that could complete this phrase: Doctrine and Covenants 29:26–27; 42:45–46; 63:49; 93:33–34. How do the truths in these verses affect the way we view death? How do they affect our everyday lives?</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>Easter videos on ChurchofJesusChrist.org.</heading>
<ul>
<li>"He Lives: Testimonies of Jesus Christ"</li>
<li>"Because He Lives"</li>
<li>"Because of Him"</li>
<li>"Hallelujah — An Easter Message about Jesus Christ"</li>
<li>"His Sacred Name — An Easter Declaration"</li>
<li>"For God So Loved the World"</li>
</ul>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Help class members search in the scriptures.</b>"Ask questions that require learners to find answers in the scriptures. . . . Help them see that even though the scriptures were written many years ago, they contain the Lord's answers to questions and problems we all face" (Teaching in the Savior's Way, 30).</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<heading>APRIL 5–11</heading>
<heading>Doctrine and Covenants 30–36</heading>
<heading>"YOU ARE CALLED TO PREACH MY GOSPEL"</heading>
<p>As you read Doctrine and Covenants 30–36, what messages feel relevant to those you teach? What will help inspire them to share the gospel with others?</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>Perhaps class members could share something they read in Doctrine and Covenants 30–36 that inspires them to share the gospel.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 30–36</heading>
<heading>We are called to preach the gospel of Jesus Christ.</heading>
<ul>
<li>This week's outline in<i>Come, Follow Me—For Individuals and Families</i>suggests searching Doctrine and Covenants 30–36 for what the Lord asks of His missionaries and what He promises them. Class members could share what they found. (See, for example, Doctrine and Covenants 30:8; 31:3–5; 32:1, 5; 35:24.) Perhaps you could invite them to write a letter to someone currently serving or preparing to serve a mission and include some of the Lord's instructions and promises.</li>
<li>Do you teach youth who are preparing to serve as missionaries? If so, you could invite each class member to search one section from Doctrine and Covenants 30–36 and find something that inspires them to serve. You could point out that the missionaries mentioned in these sections were new and inexperienced in the Church. What qualified them to share the gospel? You might also want to show one of the videos listed in "Additional Resources." What do these videos suggest about why we should serve as missionaries and how we can prepare?</li>
<li>Not everyone has the opportunity to serve a full-time mission, but we can all invite others to come unto Christ and listen to the message of the Restoration. Class members could make a list of different ways they can "open [their] mouths" (Doctrine and Covenants 33:8–10). What are some natural opportunities we have to share our beliefs with others? What counsel in Doctrine and Covenants 30–36 applies to sharing the gospel in these ways? Consider asking a few class members who have had positive experiences sharing the gospel to share their ideas and answer questions the class may have.</li>
<li>The Lord promised Ezra Thayer and Northrop Sweet that if they opened their mouths to share the gospel, they would "become even as Nephi of old" (Doctrine and Covenants 33:8). What characteristics did Nephi have that can relate to sharing the gospel? (see, for example, 1 Nephi 3:7; 4:6; 10:17; 17:15; 2 Nephi 1:27–28). How can these characteristics help us in our efforts to share the gospel?</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>The Lord asks us to preach the gospel in our day as in the early Church.</graphics-caption>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 32–33; 35</heading>
<heading>The Lord prepares us for the work He wants us to do.</heading>
<ul>
<li>How has the Lord helped us do His work? A discussion about the lives of the people described in Doctrine and Covenants 32–33, 35 may be a good starting place for pondering these experiences. For instance, you could share with the class Ezra Thayer's account of his vision in "Additional Resources" and then invite class members to read Doctrine and Covenants 33:1–13, which is part of a revelation to Ezra Thayer. How was the Lord preparing Ezra for the work the Lord wanted him to do? (see Doctrine and Covenants 33:2). You could also ask a class member to share some background information about the relationship between Parley P. Pratt and Sidney Rigdon (see "Voices of the Restoration: Early Converts" in Come, Follow Me—For Individuals and Families). How did this relationship bless the Church? What evidence do we see that the Lord's hand was in the lives of these men? Perhaps class members could share experiences that helped them see that the Lord was aware of them in a similar way.</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>Videos about missionary work (on ChurchofJesusChrist.org).</heading>
<ul>
<li>"Value of a Full-Time Mission"</li>
<li>"Sharing the Gospel"</li>
<li>"Your Day for a Mission"</li>
<li>"Elder and Sister Bednar — Missionary Working Life"</li>
<li>"A Priesthood Duty"</li>
</ul>
<heading>Ezra Thayer's vision.</heading>
<p>Ezra Thayer wrote that sometime before he was baptized, he had a vision in which "a man came and brought me a roll of paper and presented it to me, and also a trumpet and told me to [play] it. I told him that I never [played] any in my life. He said you can [play] it, try it. . . . It made the most beautiful sound that I ever heard" ("Revelation, October 1830–B, Revelation Book 1," historical introduction, josephsmithpapers.org). When Joseph Smith later received a revelation for Ezra Thayer and Northrop Sweet, now recorded as Doctrine and Covenants 33, Ezra interpreted the revelation as the roll of paper in his vision.</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Encourage a respectful environment.</b>"Help your class members understand that each of them affects the spirit of the class. Encourage them to help you establish an open, loving, and respectful environment so that everyone feels safe sharing their experiences, questions, and testimonies" (Teaching in the Savior's Way, 15).</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<graphics-caption>Saints Move to Kirtland, by Sam Lawlor</graphics-caption>
<heading>APRIL 12–18</heading>
<heading>Doctrine and Covenants 37–40</heading>
<heading>"IF YE ARE NOT ONE YE ARE NOT MINE"</heading>
<p>Before planning what you will do in class, prayerfully study Doctrine and Covenants 37–40. You are more likely to receive spiritual guidance in your preparation to teach if you first have meaningful personal experiences with these scriptures.</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>Consider writing on the board,<i>As I read Doctrine and Covenants 37–40, I felt that the Lord was telling me __.</i>Class members could share how they would complete the sentence. Encourage them to share verses from their reading as part of their answers.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 37–38</heading>
<heading>God gathers us to bless us.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Sometimes it's easier to learn from the revelations in the Doctrine and Covenants when we think of ourselves in the place of the people to whom they were originally given. To help class members do this with sections 37–38, you could invite them to imagine that they are living in Fayette, New York, in 1831. A class member could pretend to be Joseph Smith and read section 37 to them. How might we have reacted to this commandment? Perhaps class members could imagine that they have a friend who does not want to gather to Ohio; they could search section 38 for principles that might encourage their friend to be faithful to the command to gather. (If necessary, you could direct them specifically to verses 1–4, 11–12, 17–22, and 27–33.) Class members may also be willing to share how similar principles have helped them when they needed to obey a commandment that seemed difficult.</li>
<li>Latter-day Saints are no longer commanded to gather by moving to one location, but we still gather in families, wards, and stakes. To discuss how this gathering blesses us today, you could divide the class into two groups. Ask one group to search Doctrine and Covenants 38:31–33 and look for blessings that apply to gathering as families, and ask the other group to search the same passage and look for blessings that apply to gathering as wards and stakes. They could then share their thoughts with the class. How are we blessed by gathering together as a Sunday School class?</li>
</ul>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 38:24–27</heading>
<heading>God's people must be one.</heading>
<ul>
<li>The Saints who gathered in Ohio came from a variety of circumstances, but the Lord commanded them to overcome their differences and "be one" (verse 27). Why do we sometimes fail to see other people as equals? Encourage class members to ponder how they treat others as they read Doctrine and Covenants 38:24–27. What does it mean to esteem our brothers and sisters as ourselves? Why is it impossible to truly be God's people if we are not united?</li>
<li>Reading Doctrine and Covenants 38:24–27 could lead to a discussion about unity in our relationships — as ward members, families, and so on. The videos "A Friend to All" or "Love in Our Hearts" on ChurchofJesusChrist.org could help. For example, class members could share statements or impressions from the video that help them better understand the principles in verses 24–27. They could also ponder and share thoughts about a question like "What can I do to help our ward feel more united?"</li>
</ul>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 38:39; 39–40</heading>
<heading>The Father desires to give us the riches of eternity.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Making a chart might help class members discuss Doctrine and Covenants 38:39. In one column, class members could list "riches of the earth," or things that are considered valuable here but do not last into the next life. In the other column, they could list "riches of eternity," or things that God values and that can last forever. What experiences have taught us that the riches of eternity are more valuable than the riches of the world?</li>
<li>James Covel, like many of us, had righteous desires. But his failure to obey God's direction is an important warning to all of us. To help class members learn from Covel's experience, you could invite some of them to search section 39 for things the Lord asked him to do. The others could search for blessings he was promised if he obeyed. They could also search section 40 to discover why James Covel did not receive these blessings. How can his experience apply to us? What "cares of the world" sometimes prevent us from receiving God's word "with gladness"? (Doctrine and Covenants 40:2).</li>
</ul>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Don't try to cover everything.</b>"There is much to discuss in each lesson, but it is not necessary to cover everything in one class period in order to touch someone's heart — often one or two key points are enough" (Teaching in the Savior's Way, 7). The Holy Ghost, comments from class members, and the ideas in this outline can help you know where to focus.</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<heading>APRIL 19–25</heading>
<heading>Doctrine and Covenants 41–44</heading>
<heading>"MY LAW TO GOVERN MY CHURCH"</heading>
<p>You won't be able to discuss as a class every principle taught in Doctrine and Covenants 41–44. Seek inspiration to help you select principles that will be most relevant to your class.</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>When the revelations in section 42 were published, Joseph Smith wrote that the Saints "received them gladly" ("Letter to Martin Harris," Feb. 22, 1831, josephsmithpapers.org). Encourage class members to share anything from their personal or family study this week that they received gladly.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 41–42</heading>
<heading>God's laws govern His Church and can govern our lives.</heading>
<ul>
<li>In Doctrine and Covenants 41, the Lord helped the Saints prepare to receive His law, which He would reveal just a few days later (see section 42). How might the revelation in section 41 have helped the Saints receive God's law? To help class members answer this question, you could invite them to read Doctrine and Covenants 41:1–6 and find principles that can help us receive God's law. How can we apply these principles when we have opportunities to receive instruction from the Lord?</li>
<li>This week's outline in<i>Come, Follow Me—For Individuals and Families</i>suggests dividing section 42 into five groups of verses, which each present an important gospel principle. These groupings might make it easier for you to discuss this section as a class. For example, you could write the references on the board and invite each class member to select one group. Ask class members to read their verses and find something that they feel is important for us in our day. Then they could share examples from their own lives that illustrate how we are blessed when we govern our lives by these laws.</li>
</ul>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 41:9–11</heading>
<heading>The Lord asks His servants to sacrifice.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Edward Partridge, the first bishop of the restored Church, was commanded to leave his profession and "spend all his time" serving in his calling. Even though this isn't required of us, what do we find in these verses that can apply to our service to God? (For more about Edward Partridge, see "A Bishop unto the Church," Revelations in Context, 77–83.)</li>
</ul>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 42:61, 65–68; 43:1–7</heading>
<heading>Revelation brings peace, joy, and eternal life.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Like the early Church leaders, members of your class may have questions that seem like "mysteries" because they require guidance from the Lord. You could encourage them to write down a question they have or a problem for which they need personal revelation. What do we find in Doctrine and Covenants 42:61, 65–68 that might help us as we seek revelation?</li>
<li>To help members understand how God gives revelation to guide His Church, you could invite them to read Doctrine and Covenants 43:1–7. They could also watch the video "Prophets and Revelation — Hearing His Voice" (ChurchofJesusChrist.org).</li>
</ul>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 43:8–10</heading>
<heading>We meet together to "instruct and edify each other."</heading>
<ul>
<li>How might we use Doctrine and Covenants 43:8–10 to teach someone who feels it is unnecessary to come to Church meetings? The list in "Additional Resources" could help focus this discussion on the divine purposes of priesthood quorums and the Relief Society (the list also applies to Young Women classes). Class members could share how their participation in quorums, Relief Society, and Church classes has blessed them. What do verses 8–10 imply about what we should do to prepare for and participate in our meetings?</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>Why we are organized into quorums and Relief Societies.</heading>
<p>Sister Julie B. Beck, former Relief Society General President, explained why God has organized us into priesthood quorums and Relief Societies:
<b>1. "To organize us under the priesthood and after the pattern of the priesthood."</b>
<b>2. "To focus Heavenly Father's sons and daughters on the work of salvation and to engage them in it.</b>Quorums and Relief Societies are an organized discipleship with the responsibility to assist in our Father's work to bring about eternal life for His children."
<b>3. "To help bishops wisely manage the Lord's storehouse.</b>The Lord's storehouse includes the time, talents, compassion, materials, and financial means' of the members of the Church [Handbook 2: Administering the Church, 6.1.3, ChurchofJesusChrist.org]. The talents of the Saints are to be used to help care for the poor and the needy and to build the Lord's kingdom."
<b>4. "To provide a defense and a refuge for Heavenly Father's children and their families in the latter days."</b>
<b>5. "To strengthen and support us in our family roles and responsibilities as sons and daughters of God."</b> ("Why We Are Organized into Quorums and Relief Societies" [Brigham Young University devotional, Jan. 17, 2012], speeches.byu.edu.)</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Invite.</b>"Rather than always extending invitations to do something specific, consider inviting learners to think of their own ways to apply what they have learned" (Teaching in the Savior's Way, 35).</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<heading>APRIL 26–MAY 2</heading>
<heading>Doctrine and Covenants 45</heading>
<heading>"THE PROMISES. . . SHALL BE FULFILLED"</heading>
<p>As you study Doctrine and Covenants 45, think about what verses, quotations from Church leaders, experiences, questions, and other resources you might use to teach the doctrine. As you teach, invite class members to record promptings they receive and make a plan to act on them.</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>Class members could write on a slip of paper the number of a verse from Doctrine and Covenants 45 that inspired them. Then you could collect the papers, select a few at random, and invite the class members who wrote them to read their verses to the class and share why they chose them. Encourage others to also share their insights.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 45:1–5</heading>
<heading>Jesus Christ is our Advocate with the Father.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Can someone in your class describe what an advocate does? It might be helpful to look up the definition of<i>advocate</i>in a dictionary. With this understanding, class members could read Doctrine and Covenants 45:3–5 in pairs. They could share with each other any words or phrases from these verses that help them understand Jesus Christ's role as our Advocate with the Father. (See also 2 Nephi 2:8–9; Mosiah 15:7–9; Moroni 7:27–28; Doctrine and Covenants 29:5; 62:1.) Consider asking class members to share their feelings about the Savior being their Advocate.</li>
</ul>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 45:11–75</heading>
<heading>We don't need to fear the Second Coming.</heading>
<ul>
<li>How can you help class members see both the sobering warnings and the hopeful promises in section 45? For example, you could write on the board the headings<i>Prophecies</i>and<i>Promised Blessings</i>, and class members could write under these headings the teachings they find in Doctrine and Covenants 45:11–75. Why would the Lord want us to know about these things in advance? What can we do to receive the promised blessings?</li>
<li>Perhaps class members could share advice with each other about how to be optimistic and hopeful as we face the calamities foretold for our day (such as those described in Doctrine and Covenants 45:11–75). To help class members look forward to the Second Coming with faith instead of fear, you might show the video "Men's Hearts Shall Fail Them" (ChurchofJesusChrist.org). In what sense are people's hearts failing them in our day? (see verse 26). What counsel did President Nelson give in this video to help us face fearful situations with peace?</li>
</ul>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 45:31–32</heading>
<heading>"Stand in holy places," and be not moved.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Class members may be willing to share their insights about how they are striving to "stand in holy places," as the Lord counseled in Doctrine and Covenants 45:31–32. How can we create holy places in our lives? The statement in "Additional Resources" and the video "Stand Ye in Holy Places — Bloom Where You're Planted" (ChurchofJesusChrist.org) could add insights to this discussion.</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>Parable of the Ten Virgins, by Dan Burr</graphics-caption>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>"Stand in holy places."</heading>
<p>Sister Ann M. Dibb, a former member of the Young Women General Presidency, taught that the instruction to stand in holy places and be not moved "explains how we can receive protection, strength, and peace in unsettling times." After noting that these holy places could include our temples, chapels, and homes, she said that "we can each find many more places." She continued:
"We might first consider the word<i>place</i>as a physical environment or a geographic location. However, a<i>place</i>can be «a distinct condition, position, or state of mind» [Merriam-Webster.com Dictionary, "place," merriam-webster.com]. This means holy places can also include<i>moments in time</i>— moments when the Holy Ghost testifies to us, moments when we feel Heavenly Father's love, or moments when we receive an answer to our prayers. Even more, I believe any have the courage to stand for what is right, especially in situations where no one else is willing to do so, you are creating a holy place" ("Your Holy Places," Ensign or Liahona, May 2013, 115).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Be a living testimony.</b>As you live the doctrine you teach, you will be able to bear your powerful, personal witness that it is true. The Holy Ghost will confirm your testimony to the hearts of your class members. Consider the principles you will be teaching this week and in the coming weeks. How can you live them more fully? (See Teaching in the Savior's Way, 13–14.)</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<graphics-caption>The Camp Meeting, by Worthington Whittredge</graphics-caption>
<heading>MAY 3–9</heading>
<heading>Doctrine and Covenants 46–48</heading>
<heading>"SEEK YE EARNESTLY THE BEST GIFTS"</heading>
<p>As you read Doctrine and Covenants 46–48, the Holy Ghost may testify to you about the truths in these sections. Recording and reviewing impressions can help you find ways to help class members discover these same truths.</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>It may be helpful for class members to share, from time to time, how their personal or family scripture study is going. For example, when class members share an insight about something they or a family member discovered this week, you could ask them what they were doing during their study that prompted those insights.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 46:1–7</heading>
<heading>We should welcome all to Jesus Christ's Church.</heading>
<ul>
<li>For many, how and what they feel in Church meetings can significantly influence their activity in the Church. The Lord's instructions in Doctrine and Covenants 46:1–7 can help your ward members create more welcoming, meaningful worship experiences for each other and for visitors. Class members could search these verses, looking for principles related to Church meetings and list on the board what they find. For each item in the list, the class could discuss what that principle looks like in practice.</li>
<li>How can the Lord's instructions in Doctrine and Covenants 46 help class members see Church meetings as an opportunity to feel the Holy Ghost? You could invite class members to search Doctrine and Covenants 46:2 and discuss when they have seen leaders and teachers conduct meetings by the Holy Ghost. What is the role of those attending the meetings? Consider inviting class members to share times when they felt a meeting was directed and guided by the Holy Ghost.</li>
<li>Perhaps you could invite a few class members to share their experiences when they first attended a meeting of The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints. What helped them feel welcome? What advice would they give to other members to help make our Church meetings more welcoming? How can we apply the Lord's counsel found in Doctrine and Covenants 46:1–7? Let class members practice what they would say if they saw a stranger walk into the chapel for the first time.</li>
<li>A hymn like "Tis Sweet to Sing the Matchless Love" (Hymns, no. 176 or 177) could also help class members think about and discuss how to make our Church meetings more welcoming and uplifting. Maybe class members could sing the hymn together and share ideas from the lyrics about how to help others feel God's love at church.</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>The Lord taught that all are welcome in His Church.</graphics-caption>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 46:7–33</heading>
<heading>Heavenly Father gives spiritual gifts for the benefit of His children.</heading>
<ul>
<li>The early Saints firmly believed in manifestations of the Holy Ghost. How can you help your class members build their faith that these gifts can be manifest in our lives today? You could begin by inviting class members to read Doctrine and Covenants 46:7–33 in pairs or small groups. Ask them to look for at least five spiritual gifts and to discuss ways they have seen those gifts manifested in their life or the life of someone they know — including people in the class. What did they find that they could share with the class to build their faith in these gifts?</li>
<li>The Lord declared that gifts of the Spirit benefit those who are faithful and are "not for a sign" (verse 9). Perhaps class members could discuss how spiritual gifts benefit the faithful. How can these gifts help those who want to gain or strengthen their testimony of the gospel?</li>
<li>Some people love God and try to keep His commandments but don't feel they have experienced any gifts of the Spirit. How could the counsel in Doctrine and Covenants 46:7–33 help?</li>
</ul>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 47</heading>
<heading>The Holy Ghost can direct us as we fulfill our callings.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Many people can relate to what John Whitmer felt when he wanted reassurance that his calling came from God. Maybe class members could share similar experiences they have had. What do we find in Doctrine and Covenants 47 that could have given John Whitmer confidence in his assignment?</li>
</ul>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Your role as a teacher.</b>Teaching is more than just presenting information you have prepared. Among other things, it includes creating an environment where class members can learn and discover truths for themselves and share what they have learned with others. For example, throughout the lesson, ask class members about their experiences studying the scriptures at home.</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<heading>MAY 10–16</heading>
<heading>Doctrine and Covenants 49–50</heading>
<heading>"THAT WHICH IS OF GOD IS LIGHT"</heading>
<p>In order to "preach the word of truth by the Comforter" (Doctrine and Covenants 50:17), seek divine inspiration as you ponder Doctrine and Covenants 49–50. Then be open to God's direction as you teach.</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>In addition to sharing insights they received while studying the scriptures, class members may benefit from discussing how those insights come. You could invite class members to share with each other insights about a verse in Doctrine and Covenants 49–50 and discuss what led them to those insights.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 49; 50:1–36</heading>
<heading>The truths of the gospel can help me recognize false teachings.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Section 49 was given to affirm true doctrine that corrected what others were teaching (see this week's outline in<i>Come, Follow Me—For Individuals and Families</i>for some historical background). To help class members explore this section, you could divide class members into groups and assign each group one of the doctrinal topics covered (as listed in the section heading for section 49). The groups could discuss the following questions: What truths did the Lord teach about this topic in section 49? What do people believe about this topic today? What further truths has the Lord taught about it through our latter-day prophets? Give class members an opportunity to share their gratitude for the truths revealed in our day.</li>
<li>Like the elders in Kirtland who "did not understand the manifestations of different spirits" (Doctrine and Covenants 50, section heading), sometimes we wonder if something we feel or see is from the Spirit or from another influence. What can we learn from Doctrine and Covenants 50:1–36 to help us recognize the influence of the Spirit? You could let each class member pick a set of verses to study and then ask class members to share what they find.</li>
</ul>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 49:15–17</heading>
<heading>Marriage between man and woman is essential to God's plan.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Because marriage is fundamental to Heavenly Father's plan, Satan is eager to create confusion about it. Your class might benefit from making a list on the board of truths the Lord has revealed about marriage. For example, what truths about marriage do we learn from Doctrine and Covenants 49:15–17? Other helpful scriptures include Genesis 2:20–24; 1 Corinthians 11:11; or others found in "Marriage, Marry" in the Guide to the Scriptures (scriptures.ChurchofJesusChrist.org). Class members could also find truths in "The Family: A Proclamation to the World." Based on what we learn from these resources, why is marriage between a man and a woman essential plan? (see "Additional Resources").</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>Marriage between a man and a woman is ordained of God.</graphics-caption>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 50:13–22</heading>
<heading>Teachers and learners are edified together by the Spirit.</heading>
<ul>
<li>The Lord's instruction about preaching and receiving truth might provide a good opportunity to discuss the shared role and the class members have in fostering gospel learning. Consider asking class members to review Doctrine and Covenants 50:13–22 in pairs and discuss the roles of the Spirit, teachers, and learners. A few pairs could share with the class what they learned. What are some "other way[s]" we sometimes try to teach or learn the gospel? (verse 17). How can we be better at receiving by the Spirit? What are we inspired to do in our homes and at church to better teach and learn the gospel?</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>Marriage is essential to Heavenly Father's plan.</heading>
<p>Elder David A. Bednar explained why marriage is essential to God's plan of salvation:
"By divine design, men and women are intended to progress together toward perfection and a fulness of glory. Because of their distinctive temperaments and capacities, males and females each bring to a marriage relationship unique perspectives and experiences. The man and the woman contribute differently but equally to a oneness and a unity that can be achieved in no other way. The man completes and perfects the woman and the woman completes and perfects the man as they learn from and mutually strengthen and bless each other. . . .
"A home with a loving and loyal husband and wife is the supreme setting in which children can be reared in love and righteousness and in which the spiritual and physical needs of children can be met. Just as the unique characteristics of both males and females contribute to the completeness of a marriage relationship, so those same characteristics are vital to the rearing, nurturing, and teaching of children" ("Marriage Is Essential to His Eternal Plan," Ensign, June 2006, 83–84).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Lead inspired discussions.</b>Everyone has something to contribute, but sometimes not everyone gets a chance. Following the influence of the Spirit, look for ways to increase the number of class members who can share their thoughts and feelings.</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<graphics-caption>First Furrow, by James Taylor Harwood</graphics-caption>
<heading>MAY 17–23</heading>
<heading>Doctrine and Covenants 51–57</heading>
<heading>"A FAITHFUL, A JUST, AND A WISE STEWARD"</heading>
<p>Sometimes inspiration about what to teach can come as you discuss the scriptures with a family member or friend.</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>Consider sharing these words from Elder Quentin L. Cook: "My hope is that each of us will review individually and as families the stewardships for which we have responsibility and accountability" ("Stewardship — a Sacred Trust," Ensign or Liahona, Nov. 2009, 94). You could then ask class members what they learned from sections 51–57 about their stewardships.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 51:9, 15–20</heading>
<heading>The Lord wants us to be faithful, just, and wise stewards.</heading>
<ul>
<li>How will you help class members consider how the Lord's words in section 51 apply to them? You could write on the board<i>What has the Lord entrusted to me?</i>and invite class members to list their answers (see "Additional Resources" for ideas). Then they could search for principles in verses 9, 15–20 that teach them how to be better stewards over the things on their list. Or you could focus on the words "faithful," "just," and "wise" in verse 19, discussing how each of these words can guide us in fulfilling our stewardships. If needed, review together the definition of "Steward, Stewardship" in the Guide to the Scriptures (scriptures.ChurchofJesusChrist.org).</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>Members living the law of consecration donated all they had to the Church.</graphics-caption>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 52:10; 53:3; 55:1–3</heading>
<heading>The gift of the Holy Ghost is received by the laying on of hands.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Multiple verses in these revelations mention receiving the Holy Ghost by the laying on of hands. If a discussion on this topic would be valuable to your class, you could ask class members what they learn from Doctrine and Covenants 52:10; 53:3; 55:1–3 about the gift of the Holy Ghost. For more on this topic, see Acts 8:14–17; 19:1–6. Perhaps class members could talk about their experience receiving the gift of the Holy Ghost or what they can do to continue to receive His influence in their lives.</li>
</ul>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 52:9–11, 22–27</heading>
<heading>We can share the gospel wherever we are.</heading>
<ul>
<li>When the Lord sent several Church leaders to Missouri, he told them to make use of the time spent traveling and "preach by the way" (verses 25–27). Reading Doctrine and Covenants 52:9–11, 22–27 could lead to a conversation about how we can share the gospel "by the way," or during the normal course of our lives. Class members could talk about how they make sharing the gospel a natural part of their lives.</li>
</ul>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 52:14–19</heading>
<heading>God gave a pattern for avoiding deception.</heading>
<ul>
<li>To introduce the pattern the Lord revealed in Doctrine and Covenants 52:14–19, you could share examples of other patterns that might be familiar to class members, such as patterns for building things or patterns of behavior. Class members may have their own examples to share. Why are patterns valuable? How can we apply the pattern in verses 14–19 to avoid deception we find in the world today?</li>
</ul>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 54</heading>
<heading>I can turn to the Lord when I am hurt by others' choices.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Many of us have suffered disappointment when someone we depended on didn't keep his or her commitments. This happened to the Saints from Colesville, New York, who expected to settle on Leman Copley's land in Ohio. To learn from this experience, class members could review the heading to section 54 (see also Saints, 1:125–28; "A Bishop unto the Church," Revelations in Context, 78–79). They could imagine that they had a friend among the Colesville Saints and then find counsel in section 54 that they could share with their friend. Or they could search the revelation for something that might help someone who is suffering because of another person's choices. (You might point out the promise in verse 6 to those who keep their covenants.)</li>
<li>Doctrine and Covenants 54:10 has several phrases that your class members might find meaningful, such as "patient in tribulation," "sought me early," and "rest to their souls." Class members could pick a phrase to ponder and study, using the footnotes or other resources to explore related scriptures. Then they could share their thoughts.</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>Our stewardships.</heading>
<p>President Spencer W. Kimball explained: "In the Church a stewardship is a sacred spiritual or temporal trust for which there is accountability. Because all things belong to the Lord, we are stewards over our bodies, minds, families, and properties. (See Doctrine and Covenants 104:11–15.) A faithful steward is one who exercises righteous dominion, cares for his own, and looks to the poor and needy" ("Welfare Services: The Gospel in Action," Ensign, Nov. 1977, 78).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Help learners support each other.</b>Create a class environment where learners support and encourage each other. Invite them to share ideas and strategies that enhance their personal and family study. (See Teaching in the Savior's Way, 36.)</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<graphics-caption>Independence, Missouri, by Al Rounds</graphics-caption>
<heading>MAY 24–30</heading>
<heading>Doctrine and Covenants 58–59</heading>
<heading>"ANXIOUSLY ENGAGED IN A GOOD CAUSE"</heading>
<p>After reading Doctrine and Covenants 58–59, consider the following questions: What do you feel inspired to share with your class? What do you hope they will discover? How will you help them discover these things?</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>To prompt class members to share what they learned in their scripture study, you could write the following questions on the board:<i>What did we learn? How will we live what we learned?</i>Class members could list under the first question truths they found in Doctrine and Covenants 58–59. Then they could spend a few minutes discussing ideas for living by those truths and writing their ideas under the second question.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 58:1–5, 26–33</heading>
<heading>Blessings come according to God's timing and our diligence.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Doctrine and Covenants 58 teaches truths that can bring peace in times of trial. Class members may have discovered some of these truths during their study of this section; invite them to share what they found. Or they could search verses 1–5, 26–33 in class, individually or in groups, for something that might be helpful to someone who is suffering adversity or who is waiting for a promised blessing. After sharing what they find, perhaps some class members could share experiences or other scriptures that have confirmed the truths in these verses.</li>
<li>As part of your discussion of this principle, you could show the video "Hope Ya Know, We Had a Hard Time" (ChurchofJesusChrist.org) and discuss what we might do to help those who are going through difficult times. The quote by Sister Linda S. Reeves in "Additional Resources" could also help your discussion. How do Sister Reeves's words affect the way we view our trials?</li>
</ul>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 58:26–29</heading>
<heading>We can "bring to pass much righteousness" of our "own free will."</heading>
<ul>
<li>What did class members learn from their study of Doctrine and Covenants 58:26–29 this week? Perhaps you could divide the class into groups and invite class members to discuss in their groups phrases they found meaningful in these verses. How do these verses inspire us to "bring to pass much righteousness"? (verse 27). Why does the Lord want us not to be "compelled in all things"? (verse 26). What do these verses suggest about what the Lord desires us to become?</li>
</ul>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 59:9–19</heading>
<heading>The Sabbath is the Lord's day.</heading>
<ul>
<li>To help class members explore what the Lord taught the early Saints in Missouri about the Sabbath, you could invite them to search Doctrine and Covenants 59:9–19 and make a list on the board of what each verse teaches us about the Sabbath. Class members could also share how their testimony of the Sabbath day has grown as they have kept the Sabbath day holy. Sabbath.ChurchofJesusChrist.org has some videos that could help start a discussion.</li>
<li>In Doctrine and Covenants 59, the Lord taught about the Sabbath day using words like "rejoicing," "cheerful," and "glad" (verses 14–15). Class members could look for words like these in verses 9–19. Class members could then share what they do to make the Sabbath joyful. How might we use these verses to teach others why we honor the Sabbath day?</li>
<li>This discussion could also be an opportunity for class members to share ideas about how they and their families use the Sabbath to make their homes the center of their gospel learning. Invite them to share how their efforts help them remain "more fully . . . unspotted from the world" (verse 9).</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>The sacrament is an essential part of honoring the Sabbath.</graphics-caption>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>Our tribulations can guide us to the Savior.</heading>
<p>Linda S. Reeves, former member of the Relief Society General Presidency, taught:
"The Lord allows us to be tried and tested, sometimes to our maximum capacity. We have seen the lives of loved ones — and maybe our own — figuratively burned to the ground and have wondered why a loving and caring Heavenly Father would allow such things to happen. But He does not leave us in the ashes; He stands with open arms, eagerly inviting us to come to Him. . . .
"He is eager to help us, to comfort us, and to ease our pain as we rely on the power of the Atonement and honor our covenants. The trials and tribulation that we experience may be the very things that guide us to come unto Him and cling to our covenants so that we might return to His presence and receive all that the Father hath" ("Claim the Blessings of Your Covenants," Ensign or Liahona, Nov. 2013, 119–20).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Ensure you are teaching true doctrine.</b>"Continually ask yourself, «How will what I am teaching help my class members build faith in Christ, repent, make and keep covenants with God, and receive the Holy Ghost?»" (Teaching in the Savior's Way, 20).</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<graphics-caption>Campfire on the Missouri, by Bryan Mark Taylor</graphics-caption>
<heading>MAY 31–JUNE 6</heading>
<heading>Doctrine and Covenants 60–62</heading>
<heading>"ALL FLESH IS IN MINE HAND"</heading>
<p>Elder Ronald A. Rasband said: "Each of us must first strengthen ourselves spiritually and then strengthen those around us. Ponder the scriptures regularly, and remember the thoughts and feelings you experience as you read them" ("Lest Thou Forget," Ensign or Liahona, Nov. 2016, 114).</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>You can inspire a meaningful discussion by inviting class members to respond to a specific question or idea that relates to the scriptures they read at home. For example, you could invite them to share something they learned this week about Heavenly Father or Jesus Christ.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 60:2–3, 7, 13–14; 62:3, 9</heading>
<heading>The Lord is pleased when we open our mouths to share the gospel.</heading>
<ul>
<li>As members of the Church, we know that the restored gospel is a great treasure that blesses the lives of God's children. So why do we sometimes hesitate to share our testimony with others? Consider inviting class members to list on the board some reasons why we might not open our mouths to share the gospel. Class members could then read Doctrine and Covenants 60:2–3, 7, 13–14; 62:3, 9, looking for words or phrases that inspire them to share the gospel. They could list what they found on the board. Perhaps some class members could share an experience when they overcame their fears and shared the gospel with someone.</li>
<li>Throughout Doctrine and Covenants 60–62, there are teachings, both stated and implied, about sharing the gospel. To help class members discover these teachings, you could ask each person to review one of these sections and share anything they find that teaches them about sharing the gospel. It might enhance the discussion to read about exemplary missionaries elsewhere in the scriptures (see, for instance, Acts 8:27–40; Alma 19:16–17) and discuss what we learn from them. What examples can we share from our own lives? Can any class members share how they were introduced to the gospel and how they felt about the people who taught them? Your class might benefit from role-playing ways in which we can "open [our] mouths" and share the gospel.</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>God wants us to share the gospel with others.</graphics-caption>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 60:2–4; 61:1–2, 20, 36–38; 62:1, 6</heading>
<heading>The scriptures teach us about Jesus Christ.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Invite class members to write on the board anything they learned about the Savior this week from studying sections 60–62, along with the related verses. Or they could search Doctrine and Covenants 60:2–4; 61:1–2, 20, 36–38; 62:1, 6 to find things taught about the Savior. What stories from the scriptures or our own lives illustrate the roles and attributes of the Savior that we have learned about? (for example, John 8:1–11; Ether 2:14–15). You could invite class members to share their testimonies of Jesus Christ or to privately reflect on what He means to them.</li>
</ul>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 60:5; 61:22; 62:5–8</heading>
<heading>The Lord wants us to make some decisions "as seemeth [us] good."</heading>
<ul>
<li>Consider inviting class members to read Doctrine and Covenants 60:5; 61:22; 62:5–8 in pairs or small groups and share what they feel might be the Lord's message to us. When have they felt that they should use their own judgment in making a decision? Consider sharing the statement by President Dallin H. Oaks in "Additional Resources" as part of your discussion. How can parents help their children learn this important principle?</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>Acting upon our best judgment.</heading>
<p>President Dallin H. Oaks taught:
"A desire to be led by the Lord is a strength, but it needs to be accompanied by an understanding that our Heavenly Father leaves many decisions for our personal choices. Personal decision making is one of the sources of the growth we are meant to experience in mortality. Persons who try to shift all decision making to the Lord and plead for revelation in every choice will soon find circumstances in which they pray for guidance and don't receive it. For example, this is likely to occur in those numerous circumstances in which the choices are trivial or either choice is acceptable.
"We should study things out in our minds, using the reasoning powers our Creator has placed within us. Then we should pray for guidance and act upon it if we receive it. If we do not receive guidance, we should act upon our best judgment" ("Our Strengths Can Become Our Downfall," Ensign, Oct. 1994, 13–14).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Know those who struggle.</b>The struggles of those you teach may be hard to detect. But with the help of the Spirit and your leaders, you can know the best way to reach out to these individuals. (see Teaching in the Savior's Way, 8–9.)</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<graphics-caption>Springhill, Daviess County, Missouri, by Garth Robinson Oborn</graphics-caption>
<heading>JUNE 7–13</heading>
<heading>"THAT WHICH COMETH FROM ABOVE IS SACRED"</heading>
<p>Record the impressions you receive as you study Doctrine and Covenants 63. An impression may seem small, but like a seed, it can grow into something meaningful and fruitful as you keep seeking and pondering.</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>To help focus your discussion on passages that class members find most meaningful, you could invite them to write on slips of paper some verses from section 63 that they would like to discuss. Then you could gather the papers and begin discussing verses that were suggested by multiple class members. Ask them to share why they chose those verses.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 63:7–12</heading>
<heading>Signs come by faith and the will of God.</heading>
<ul>
<li>To begin a discussion on the principles taught in Doctrine and Covenants 63:7–12, it might help to review a few examples in the scriptures of people who witnessed signs or miracles. Perhaps class members could think of examples of people whose faith was strengthened by a sign (see, for example, Luke 1:5–20, 59–64) or of people who wavered even after witnessing a sign (see, for example, 1 Nephi 3:27–31; Alma 30:43–56). Class members could then use what they learn in Doctrine and Covenants 63:7–12 to explain these different reactions to signs. Or you could review other scripture passages about signs, such as those listed under "Sign" in Guide to the Scriptures (scriptures.ChurchofJesusChrist.org). How can we be sure that we are not seeking or relying on signs as a foundation for our faith?</li>
</ul>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 63:13–16</heading>
<heading>Chastity means keeping our thoughts and our actions pure.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Although much of Doctrine and Covenants 63:13–16 addresses adultery specifically, the principles taught can be relevant to any violation of the law of chastity. Consider inviting class members to identify consequences described in Doctrine and Covenants 63:13–16. They could even make "beware" (verse 15) or caution signs that warn of these consequences. They could also discuss what they think these consequences mean. For instance, why would breaking the law of chastity lead to judgment coming upon someone "as a snare" (verse 15)? Why does the Lord counsel us to "repent speedily" (verse 15) of sexual sin? (see Sister Linda S. Reeves's statement in "Additional Resources").</li>
<li>Reading Doctrine and Covenants 63:16 might lead to a discussion about the prevalent influence of pornography in our society. How do the warnings in verse 16 relate to this problem? (Even though this revelation refers specifically to men lusting after women, these warnings apply to everyone.) What can we do to protect ourselves and our loved ones from pornography? Class members may be willing to give each other advice. The website AddressingPornography.ChurchofJesusChrist.org can give hope and help to any who might be struggling with pornography.</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>We are blessed when we keep the law of chastity.</graphics-caption>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 63:58–64</heading>
<heading>Sacred things should be treated with reverence.</heading>
<ul>
<li>You and your class might discuss Doctrine and Covenants 63:58–64 as a warning against taking the Lord's name in vain, and some of the resources in the Gospel Topics article titled "Profanity" (topics.ChurchofJesusChrist.org) could enhance such a discussion. You could also help class members apply these verses more broadly. For example, you could discuss what the phrase "having not authority" (verse 62) adds to our understanding of the passage. Class members could also list other sacred things that come "from above," or from God. What does it mean to speak of these things "with care"? (verse 64).</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>Chastity qualifies us for the companionship of the Holy Ghost.</heading>
<p>Sister Linda S. Reeves, former member of the Relief Society General Presidency, taught:
"I know of nothing that will qualify us for the constant companionship of the Holy Ghost as much as virtue. . . .
"When we are involved in watching, reading, or experiencing anything that is below our Heavenly Father's standards, it weakens us. Regardless of our age, if what we look at, read, listen to, or choose to do does not meet the Lord's standards in<i>For the Strength of Youth</i>, turn it off, rip it up, throw it out, and slam the door. . . . .
"I believe that if we could daily remember and recognize the depth of that love our Heavenly Father and our Savior have for us, we would be willing to do anything to be back in Their presence again, surrounded by Their love eternally" ("Worthy of Our Promised Blessings," Ensign or Liahona, Nov. 2015, 10–11).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Use sacred music.</b>The messages in hymns and songs from the Children's Songbook can reinforce the doctrine you are studying in the scriptures. For instance, singing a song about praising God's name, such as "Glory to God on High" (Hymns, no. 67), could reinforce the message in Doctrine and Covenants 63:58–64.</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<graphics-caption>Daviess County, Missouri</graphics-caption>
<heading>JUNE 14–20</heading>
<heading>Doctrine and Covenants 64–66</heading>
<heading>"THE LORD REQUIRETH THE HEART AND A WILLING MIND"</heading>
<p>During your study this week, prayerfully consider what principles from Doctrine and Covenants 64–66 would increase the faith and knowledge of members of your class.</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>To encourage class members to share something they found meaningful in their scripture study this week, you could ask them to ponder the challenges we face today. Then invite them to share a verse from Doctrine and Covenants 64–66 that they feel could help with one of those challenges.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 64:1–11</heading>
<heading>We are required to forgive everyone.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Maybe class members would benefit from talking about why forgiving others can be so difficult and how they've overcome those difficulties. They could search Doctrine and Covenants 64:1–11 for principles and truths that inspire them to be more forgiving. What do we learn about the Savior from these verses? To help illustrate the blessings of forgiveness, you could share the story of Morrell Bowen from Elder Jeffrey R. Holland's message "The Ministry of Reconciliation" (Ensign or Liahona, Nov. 2018, 77–79) or the video "Forgiveness: My Burden Was Made Light" (ChurchofJesusChrist.org). Or a class member may be willing to share a personal story of extending or receiving forgiveness. How were the people in these examples blessed by the power of forgiveness?</li>
</ul>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 64:31–34</heading>
<heading>The Lord asks for our "heart and a willing mind."</heading>
<ul>
<li>The Lord doesn't want to us to be "weary"; however, it's natural for people who are trying their best — including, perhaps, some in your class — to become "weary in well-doing." Why does this weariness happen? What counsel do we find in Doctrine and Covenants 64:31–34 that could help us when we struggle with such feelings?</li>
<li>To enrich your discussion, you might show pictures of something large and impressive that was built over a long time out of "small things" such as a mosaic or a brick building. What are some examples of the "great work" that the Lord has given us? What small things can we do now to lay the foundation for that work?</li>
<li>To help class members ponder more deeply about Doctrine and Covenants 64:34, you could write<i>Heart</i>and<i>Willing Mind</i>on the board. Class members could list under these headings what they feel it means to give our hearts and a willing mind to the Lord. For an explanation of these terms, see Elder Donald L. Hallstrom's words in "Additional Resources." Scriptures like the following could also provide some insights: Mosiah 7:33; Ether 4:15; Doctrine and Covenants 43:34; Moses 7:18; Joseph Smith—History 1:19.</li>
</ul>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 65</heading>
<heading>The kingdom of God on earth prepares the world for the Savior's return.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Doctrine and Covenants 65 gives an inspiring description of the mission of the Lord's Church in the latter days. To help class members see their part in this mission, you could invite them to search section 65 looking for answers to questions like these: What does the Lord want His kingdom to accomplish on the earth? What does He want me to do to help? You could also watch the video "Prepare Today for the Second Coming" (ChurchofJesusChrist.org) or refer to President Dallin H. Oaks's message in "Additional Resources." Class members could share how they would answer President Oaks's questions.</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>"The heart and a willing mind."</heading>
<p>Elder Donald L. Hallstrom suggested this possible meaning for the phrase 'heart and a willing mind':
"The heart is symbolic of love and commitment. We make sacrifices and bear burdens for those we love that we would not endure for any other reason. If love does not exist, our commitment wanes. . . .
"Having «a willing mind» connotes giving our best effort and finest thinking and seeking God's wisdom. It suggests that our most devoted lifetime study should be of things that are eternal in nature. It means that there must be an inextricable relationship between hearing the word of God and obeying it" ("The Heart and a Willing Mind," Ensign, June 2011, 31–32).</p>
<heading>Preparation for the Second Coming.</heading>
<p>"What if the day of [Jesus Christ's] coming were tomorrow? If we knew that we would meet the Lord tomorrow — through our premature death or through His unexpected coming — what would we do today? What confessions would we make? What practices would we discontinue? What accounts would we settle? What forgivenesses would we extend? What testimonies would we bear?" (Dallin H. Oaks, "Preparation for the Second Coming," Ensign or Liahona, May 2004, 9).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Draw strength from the Savior.</b>"In your efforts to live and teach more like the Savior, you will inevitably fall short at times. Do not become discouraged; rather, let your mistakes and weaknesses turn you to Heavenly Father and the Savior" (Teaching in the Savior's Way, 14).</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<heading>JUNE 21–27</heading>
<heading>Doctrine and Covenants 67–70</heading>
<heading>"WORTH. . . THE RICHES OF THE WHOLE EARTH"</heading>
<p>Preparing to teach means more than thinking about what you will say and do as the teacher. It should also include considering what learners can do to teach each other. How will you invite class members to share experiences or insights they have had reading these scriptures?</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>You could write on the board<i>This week the Lord taught me . . .</i>and invite class members to finish the sentence with something they learned.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 67:1–9</heading>
<heading>The revelations given through Joseph Smith are true and come from God.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Understanding the historical background of Doctrine and Covenants 67 could be helpful to a discussion on this section. Perhaps a class member could summarize the circumstances that led to this revelation (see Doctrine and Covenants 67, section heading; Saints, 1:140–43). If we were present in the meeting where publishing the revelations was discussed, what reasons could we give in favor of the idea? What could we say to people who were concerned about imperfections in Joseph Smith's language? What does section 67 teach us about prophets and revelation? Class members could also share how they have come to know for themselves that these revelations are true.</li>
</ul>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 68:1–6</heading>
<heading>The inspired words of the Lord's servants are the Lord's words.</heading>
<ul>
<li>To help class members discuss Doctrine and Covenants 68:1–6, you could invite them to read these verses in small groups and share with each other the truths they learn about the teachings of the Lord's servants. Invite groups to share with each other how they know the principles taught in verse 4 are true. Class members could share experiences when they spoke or taught as "moved upon by the Holy Ghost" (verse 3) and how the Lord was with them and stood by them (see verse 6).</li>
<li>If you'd like to discuss how these verses apply to the teachings of the Lord's servants in general conference, Elder Jeffrey R. Holland's statement in "Additional Resources" could be helpful. Class members could also share recent conference messages that strengthened their faith in the doctrine found in these verses.</li>
</ul>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 68:25–31</heading>
<heading>Parents have a responsibility to teach their children.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Are there parents in your class — or future parents? Maybe they would benefit from talking about the Lord's counsel to parents in section 68. For example, perhaps some parents in the class could pick a principle from verses 25–28 and talk about how they try to teach these things to their children (verses 29–31 also have some important principles). Or class members could talk about how their parents have taught them gospel principles.</li>
<li>Why is the home the best place for children to learn the gospel? What would we say to parents who feel inadequate or overwhelmed by the duty to teach their children?</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>God has given parents the responsibility of teaching their children.</graphics-caption>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 70:1–4</heading>
<heading>We are accountable for the revelations the Lord has given us.</heading>
<ul>
<li>The Lord gave certain brethren stewardship over the revelations to take them to Missouri and oversee their publication. In what sense can we see ourselves as stewards over the revelations? What other teachings from this section about stewardship can apply to us?</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>God speaks to us today.</heading>
<p>Elder Jeffrey R. Holland shared how the principle taught in Doctrine and Covenants 68:4 applies to general conference: "I ask you to reflect in the days ahead not only on the messages you have heard but also on the unique phenomenon that general conference itself is what we as Latter-day Saints believe such conferences to be and what we invite the world to hear and observe about them. We testify to every nation, kindred, tongue, and people that God not only lives but also that He speaks, that for our time and in our day the counsel you have heard is, under the direction of the Holy Spirit, «the will of the Lord, the word of the Lord, . . . the voice of the Lord, and the power of God unto salvation» [Doctrine and Covenants 68:4]" ("An Ensign to the Nations," Ensign or Liahona, May 2011, 111).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Help learners lift each other.</b>"Each individual in your class is a rich source of testimony, insights, and experiences with living the gospel. Invite them to share with and lift each other" (Teaching in the Savior's Way, 5).</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<graphics-caption>Dear to the Heart of the Shepherd, by Simon Dewey</graphics-caption>
<heading>JUNE 28–JULY 4</heading>
<heading>Doctrine and Covenants 71–75</heading>
<heading>"NO WEAPON THAT IS FORMED AGAINST YOU SHALL PROSPER"</heading>
<p>As you read Doctrine and Covenants 71–75, think about the people you teach. What do you know about them? What do they need?</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>Invite class members to share some of the truths that they found during their study of Doctrine and Covenants 71–75. What experiences have they had with these truths?</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 71</heading>
<heading>We can follow the guidance of the Holy Ghost as we defend our beliefs.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Have we ever felt fearful or nervous about defending our beliefs? Perhaps you could invite class members to write on the board words or phrases they find in Doctrine and Covenants 71 that describe how the Lord asked Joseph and Sidney to respond to the criticisms of Ezra Booth and others. Class members could then discuss in small groups what these instructions may mean for us today. Why is it important that we act "according to that portion of Spirit" the Lord gives us? (verse 1).</li>
<li>It might also be helpful to watch the video "Everyday Example: When Beliefs Are Questioned" (ChurchofJesusChrist.org). Class members could look for ways the truths in section 71 are demonstrated in the video. Perhaps they could also share examples of how the Savior responded to His critics (for example, see Matthew 22:15–22; 26:59–64; John 10:37–38).</li>
</ul>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 72:8–16</heading>
<heading>Bishops are stewards over the spiritual and temporal affairs of the Lord's kingdom.</heading>
<ul>
<li>How can the Lord's instructions to Newel K. Whitney, when he was called to be the bishop in Kirtland, help those you teach appreciate the bishops who have been called to serve them? You could ask class members to search Doctrine and Covenants 72:8–16, looking for some of the responsibilities of Bishop Whitney and then comparing them to the responsibilities of bishops today (see President Gordon B. Hinckley's description of the responsibilities of a bishop in "Additional Resources" or the related video, "The Office of Bishop" [ChurchofJesusChrist.org]). Perhaps class members could share how they have been blessed by a bishop's service. What can we do to more fully sustain our bishop?</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>Bishops help members meet their temporal needs.</graphics-caption>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 73</heading>
<heading>We can seek opportunities to share the gospel.</heading>
<ul>
<li>The Lord told Joseph Smith and Sidney Rigdon to preach the gospel "inasmuch as it is practicable" (Doctrine and Covenants 73:4) while also working on the translation of the Bible. Perhaps class members could share some ways they have found it "practicable" — or realistic — to share the gospel among their other responsibilities. They may find some helpful counsel in Elder Dieter F. Uchtdorf's message "Missionary Work: Sharing What Is in Your Heart" (Ensign or Liahona, May 2019, 15–18)</li>
</ul>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 75:2–16</heading>
<heading>God wants us to "labor with [our] might."</heading>
<ul>
<li>The Lord's instructions to several elders about how to share the gospel could inspire class members to share the gospel more diligently. You could write on the board<i>Labor with your might</i>and ask class members to list words and phrases that come to mind when they think of someone who labors with his or her might in sharing the gospel. They could also discuss what it means to "tarry" or "be idle" in sharing the gospel. What does Doctrine and Covenants 75:2–16 teach us about how the Savior supports those who serve Him faithfully?</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>Responsibilities of a bishop.</heading>
<p>President Gordon B. Hinckley taught:
"I carry in my heart a deep appreciation for our bishops. I am profoundly grateful for the revelation of the Almighty under which this office was created and functions. . . .
". . . We expect you to stand as the presiding high priest of the ward, a counselor to the people, a defender and helper of those in trouble, a comfort to those in sorrow, a supplier to those in need. We expect you to stand as a guardian and protector of the doctrine that is taught in your ward, of the quality of the teaching, of the filling of the many offices which are necessary. . . .
". . . You are to see that none goes hungry or without clothing or shelter. You must know the circumstances of all over whom you preside.
"You must be a comforter and a guide to your people. Your door must be ever open to any cries of distress. Your back must be strong in sharing their burdens. You must reach out in love even to the wrongdoer" ("The Shepherds of the Flock," Ensign, May 1999, 52–53).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Become a more Christlike teacher.</b>Consider using the personal evaluation questions on page 37 of<i>Teaching in the Savior's Way</i>to help you learn how you can teach more like the Savior.</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<graphics-caption>Refuge, by Shaelynn Abel</graphics-caption>
<heading>JULY 5–11</heading>
<heading>Doctrine and Covenants 76</heading>
<heading>"GREAT SHALL BE THEIR REWARD AND ETERNAL SHALL BE THEIR GLORY"</heading>
<p>Like visions recorded in the scriptures, the vision in section 76 came when Joseph Smith many and Sidney Rigdon "meditated upon" the scriptures (verse 19). You too can receive revelation — including guidance about how to teach — as you ponder Doctrine and Covenants 76.</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>To help class members talk about what they read in Doctrine and Covenants 76, you could invite them to imagine that a friend of another faith asks what we believe about life after death. What verses from section 76 would they share with their friend? Class members could also share something from "Voices of the Restoration: Testimonies of «the Vision»" that impressed them.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 76</heading>
<heading>Salvation comes through Jesus Christ, the Son of God.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Many people, when they think of section 76, think about the plan of salvation and the three kingdoms of glory. How can you help class members see that the central figure in this revelation is the Savior Jesus Christ? You could ask class members to share a verse they found in section 76 that strengthened their faith in Jesus Christ. If they need help, you could point them to verses such as 1–5, 20–24, 39–43, 69, 107–8.</li>
<li>To help class members explore the differences between those who inherit the three kingdoms of glory, write on the board<i>Celestial, verses 50–70, 92–96; Terrestrial, verses 71–79, 97;</i>and<i>Telestial, verses 81–90, 98–106, 109–12.</i>Class members could select one of the three sets of verses and find phrases that describe the relationship between Jesus Christ and the people who inherit the corresponding kingdom. What do these phrases teach us about being disciples of Jesus Christ? How can we strengthen our relationship with Him and with the Father? How do they reach out to us? What does it mean to be "valiant in the testimony of Jesus"? (verse 79).</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>Joseph Smith saw the vision of the degrees of glory in this room.</graphics-caption>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 76:5–10, 113–18</heading>
<heading>God's mysteries can only be "understood by the power of the Holy Spirit."</heading>
<ul>
<li>It might be interesting for members of your class to know that not all members of the Church easily accepted the revelation in section 76. For example, Brigham Young said: "My traditions were such, that when the Vision came first to me, it was directly contrary and opposed to my former education. I said, Wait a little. I did not reject it; but I could not understand it." He explained that he had to "think and pray, to read and think, until I knew and fully understood it for myself" (in "The Vision," Revelations in Context, 150). What do we learn from his experience that can help us when God reveals things that are different from our current understanding? What does Doctrine and Covenants 76:5–10, 113–18 teach us about how we can receive "the secrets of [God's] will"? (verse 10).</li>
</ul>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 76:50–70, 92–95</heading>
<heading>God wants all of His children to enjoy celestial glory with Him.</heading>
<ul>
<li>To some, it can be discouraging or overwhelming to think of everything that is required of us to qualify for the celestial kingdom. Consider how you can help class members find hope "through Jesus the mediator" (verse 69). For example, you could invite them to read verses 50–70 and 92–95. Invite them to share how they might respond to someone who says, "Living the gospel in today's world is so hard; I'm not sure it's worth it" or "I'm just not good enough for the celestial kingdom." What could we say to inspire or encourage this person?</li>
</ul>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Focus on the Savior and His doctrine.</b>"Continually ask yourself, «How will what I am teaching help my class members build faith in Christ, repent, make and keep covenants with God, and receive the Holy Ghost?»" (Teaching in the Savior's Way, 20).</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<graphics-caption>Going Home, by Yongsung Kim</graphics-caption>
<heading>JULY 12–18</heading>
<heading>Doctrine and Covenants 77–80</heading>
<heading>"I WILL LEAD YOU ALONG"</heading>
<p>Remember that the activities in this outline are only suggestions. As you prayerfully study Doctrine and Covenants 77–80, the Spirit will guide you to know how best to teach your class members.</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>Some members of your class might be more likely to share their insights if you ask them in advance. Consider contacting some of them a few days before class to ask if they would come prepared to share something that impressed them from Doctrine and Covenants 77–80.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 77</heading>
<heading>God reveals His mysteries to those who seek to know them.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Class members could share insights they found about the symbols in the book of Revelation during their study of section 77 this week. Talking about the answers Joseph Smith received could lead to a discussion about how class members can seek understanding when they study the scriptures. What do we learn from the types of questions Joseph asked? Class members might be willing to share experiences when their gospel questions led to greater understanding.</li>
</ul>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 78:17–19</heading>
<heading>The Lord will lead us along.</heading>
<ul>
<li>To begin a discussion of Doctrine and Covenants 78:17–19, you could show pictures of a few of your class members as children (ask them ahead of time to bring these pictures to class). Let the class guess who is in each picture. The class members who brought the pictures could talk about how they have changed since those pictures were taken. Then the class could read Doctrine and Covenants 78:17–19 and ponder questions such as these: How are we like little children to the Lord? In what ways does He want us to be like children (see Mosiah 3:19), and in what ways does He want us to grow? What counsel does He give us in these verses to help us grow?</li>
<li>To expand your class members' understanding of how the Lord may "lead [us] along" (verse 18), consider sharing the statement in "Additional Resources."</li>
</ul>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 79–80</heading>
<heading>The call to serve God matters more than where we serve.</heading>
<ul>
<li>There may be people in your class who felt disappointed at first with a calling they received in the ward or branch or with the place they were assigned to serve as a missionary. A few of them might be willing to share their experiences. How could the Lord's counsel in Doctrine and Covenants 80:3 help us in these circumstances? What could the phrase "it mattereth not" mean? Or the phrase "ye cannot go amiss"? What might matter most to the Lord when it comes to our callings? Elder David A. Bednar's insights on section 80 in his address "Called to the Work" could also be helpful (Ensign or Liahona, May 2017, 68).</li>
<li>The revelations in sections 79 and 80 were originally addressed to people called to preach the gospel, but they contain principles that can apply to all of us in our service to the Lord. To help class members find these principles, you could ask them to pretend they have a friend who recently joined the Church and just received his or her first calling. Invite class members to write their friend a letter of support and counsel, and encourage them to quote from sections 79 and 80 as they do. Then a few class members could share what they wrote.</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>The Lord is pleased when we serve Him and others.</graphics-caption>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>The Lord will lead us through the Holy Ghost.</heading>
<p>President Henry B. Eyring shared an experience when he prayed for guidance on a critical decision and learned to be led by the Lord:
"I prayed, but for hours there seemed to be no answer. Just before dawn, a feeling came over me. More than at any time since I had been a child, I felt like one. My heart and my mind seemed to grow very quiet. There was a peace in that inner stillness.
"Somewhat to my surprise, I found myself praying, «Heavenly Father, it doesn't matter what I want. I don't care anymore what I want. I only want that Thy will be done. That is all that I want. Please tell me what to do.»
"In that moment I felt as quiet inside as I had ever felt. And the message came, and I was sure who it was from. It was clear what I was to do. I received no promise of the outcome. There was only the assurance that I was a child who had been told what path led to whatever He wanted for me" ("As a Child," Ensign or Liahona, May 2006, 16).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Start with the scriptures.</b>Before turning to supplementary resources, diligently study and ponder the scriptures. This will invite the Spirit to help you draw upon what you have studied as you teach (see Teaching in the Savior's Way, 12).</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<graphics-caption>Christ and the Rich Young Ruler, by Heinrich Hofmann</graphics-caption>
<heading>JULY 19–25</heading>
<heading>Doctrine and Covenants 81–83</heading>
<heading>WHERE "MUCH IS GIVEN MUCH IS REQUIRED"</heading>
<p>Remember that your class members are having spiritual experiences as they study the scriptures at home. Prayerfully consider how you can encourage them to share their experiences to uplift each other.</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>Invite class members to pick a phrase from each of the following sections that would make a good title for the section: Doctrine and Covenants 81, 82, and 83. Why did they choose these titles?</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 81:5; 82:18–19</heading>
<heading>We should each seek "the interest of [our] neighbor."</heading>
<ul>
<li>This week's outline in<i>Come, Follow Me—For Individuals and Families</i>suggests questions to ponder about Doctrine and Covenants 81:5. These could also make good discussion questions for your class. Also consider sharing a personal experience when you felt "weak" in some way and someone's service lifted or strengthened you. Class members may have similar experiences of their own to share. You could also watch the video "Works of God" (ChurchofJesusChrist.org) to inspire class members to serve one another. You might also share President M. Russell Ballard's statement in "Additional Resources."</li>
<li>Consider asking class members to study Doctrine and Covenants 82:18–19, looking for principles that help them understand the purposes and blessings of serving others. Then let them share what they learn. You could also show the video "Teachings of Thomas S. Monson: Rescuing Those in Need" (ChurchofJesusChrist.org). How did Bishop Monson's ward members exemplify what verses 18–19 teach?</li>
</ul>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 82:8–10</heading>
<heading>"I, the Lord, am bound when ye do what I say."</heading>
<ul>
<li>To help class members understand the relationship between our willing obedience and God's promised blessings, you could read Doctrine and Covenants 1:37–38; 82:10; 130:20–21 together or in small groups. What do these scriptures teach us about the Lord? Perhaps class members could list words that describe His character, based on these verses.</li>
<li>After reading verse 10, class members could talk about what the Lord has promised us and how the Lord has kept His promises. The story by Sister Virginia H. Pearce found in "Additional Resources" could help class members see that the Lord blesses us according to His own wisdom, not always in the way we want or expect.</li>
<li>What do we learn from Doctrine and Covenants 82:8–10 about why Heavenly Father gives us commandments? Perhaps class members could find insights in these verses to use in helping a friend or a child who thinks that commandments are restrictive (see also the video "Blessed and Happy Are Those Who Keep the Commandments of God," ChurchofJesusChrist.org). Or they could share experiences that have taught them to see commandments as blessings.</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>Pure religion.</heading>
<p>President M. Russell Ballard taught:
"In our discipleship, we have many demands, concerns, and assignments. However, some activities must always be at the heart of our Church membership. «Wherefore,» the Lord commands, «be faithful; stand in the office which I have appointed unto you;<i>succor</i>the weak,<i>lift</i>up the hands which hang down, and<i>strengthen</i>the feeble knees» [Doctrine and Covenants 81:5; italics added].
"This is the Church in action! This is pure religion! This is the gospel in its true sense as we succor, lift, and strengthen those in spiritual and temporal need! Doing so requires us to visit them and to assist them [see James 1:27], that their testimonies of faith in Heavenly Father and Jesus Christ and His Atonement will be anchored in their hearts" ("Precious Gifts from God," Ensign or Liahona, May 2018, 11).</p>
<heading>The Lord blesses us in His own marvelous ways.</heading>
<p>Sister Virginia H. Pearce, former member of the Young Women General Presidency, told about a woman who worried about her wayward children. he set an ambitious goal of increased temple attendance and felt sure that the Lord would honor this significant sacrifice by changing her children's hearts. The woman reported:
"After ten years of increased temple attendance and constant prayer, I am sorry to say that my children's choices have not changed. . . .
"But I have. I am a different woman. . . . I have given up my time limits and am able to wait on the Lord. . . . My expectations have changed. Instead of expecting my children to change, I expect these frequent tender mercies and am full of gratitude for them. . . . The Lord works in marvelous ways, and I truly am filled with the peace that passeth all understanding" (in "Prayer: A Small and Simple Thing," At the Pulpit [2017], 288–89).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Invite the youth to be part of your lesson.</b>Give youth opportunities to teach each other. Hearing each other's testimonies or experiences can be very influential. As needed, help youth prepare to teach, and show them what it means to teach in the Savior's way (see Teaching in the Savior's Way, 27–28).</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<graphics-caption>Restoration, by Liz Lemon Swindle</graphics-caption>
<heading>JULY 26–AUGUST 1</heading>
<heading>Doctrine and Covenants 84</heading>
<heading>"THE POWER OF GODLINESS"</heading>
<p>What will you do to invite class members to share what they learned as they studied Doctrine and Covenants 84?</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>Invite class members to share with another class member a truth they found in section 84 that inspired them or helped them better understand the priesthood of God. Then invite a few to share with the class.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 84:1–5, 17–28, 31–42</heading>
<heading>We all have access to God's priesthood power and blessings.</heading>
<ul>
<li>The Lord begins this "revelation on priesthood" (Doctrine and Covenants 84, section heading) by tea that a temple will be built in Zion (see verses 1–5). How can you help class members understand the relationship between the sacred purposes of temples and the priesthood? You could begin by writing a question on the board such as<i>What are the purposes of the priesthood?</i>and then inviting class members to look for answers in Doctrine and Covenants 84:17–28, 31–42. How do temples and temple ordinances help fulfill these purposes?</li>
<li>To help class members understand the power the priesthood can have in their lives, you could invite them to read Doctrine and Covenants 84:17–28 and consider how their lives would be different without the priesthood of God. Encourage them to share why they are grateful for the priesthood, along with experiences they've had with priesthood power — in their families, callings, or personal lives. How do we gain access to the power of the priesthood?</li>
<li>The oath and covenant of the priesthood (see Doctrine and Covenants 84:31–42) has special application for those who are ordained to a priesthood office. But many of the promised blessings in these verses are available to all. To help class members see how these promises apply to them, you could invite them to read verses 33–42 and talk about ways we can "receive" the priesthood (verse 35), the Lord's servants, and the Lord. They could also read the statements in "Additional Resources" to find out what we need to do to receive the blessings of the priesthood. You might help class members think about what could be included in "all that [the] Father hath" (verse 38), such as His attributes and the kind of life that He enjoys. What else impresses us about these verses and statements?</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>Priesthood ordinances bless all of God's children.</graphics-caption>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 84:61–88</heading>
<heading>The Lord will sustain those who serve Him.</heading>
<ul>
<li>While these verses are directed to those who "shall go and preach this gospel of the kingdom" (verse 80), many of the principles they contain can apply to anyone who is serving God. You could give each class member a portion of Doctrine and Covenants 84:61–88 to read and ask them to share with another class member what they learned that could apply to anyone who serves the Lord. Class members could pick a favorite verse or group of verses to memorize or display where they will see it every day. What promises are they most excited about? What would we share from these verses to inspire current full-time missionaries or those who are preparing to serve?</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>All can receive all that the Father has.</heading>
<p>President M. Russell Ballard taught: "All who have made sacred covenants with the Lord and who honor those covenants are eligible to receive personal revelation, to be blessed by the ministering of angels, to commune with God, to receive the fulness of the gospel, and, ultimately, to become heirs alongside Jesus Christ of all our Father has" ("Men and Women and Priesthood Power," Ensign, Sept. 2014, 32). </p>
<p> The first Relief Society presidency of the Salt Lake Stake wrote in 1878: "We feel truly thankful that through the blessing of our Heavenly Father, we, His handmaidens are called to be co-laborers with our brethren in building up the kingdom of God upon the earth, in assisting to build Temples, wherein we can receive blessings for time and eternity. In all the ordinances received in the House of the Lord, woman stands beside the man, both for the living and the dead, showing that the man is not without the woman nor the woman without the man in the Lord" (Mary Isabella Horne, Elmina S. Taylor, and Serepta M. Heywood, "To the Presidents and Members of the Relief Society of Salt Lake Stake of Zion, Greeting!" Woman's Exponent, Jan. 15, 1878, 123).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Center your teaching on doctrine.</b>Make sure your class discussions focus on the foundational doctrine in the scriptures. You can do this by asking class members to read scriptures and then share the truths they found, as well as their experiences living those truths. (See Teaching in the Savior's Way, 20–21.)</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<heading>AUGUST 2–8</heading>
<heading>Doctrine and Covenants 85–87</heading>
<heading>"STAND YE IN HOLY PLACES"</heading>
<p>Don't feel pressure to cover every verse — or even every section — of the Doctrine and Covenants in Sunday School. Let the Spirit guide you, and be responsive to what class members find relevant to their lives.</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>Class members could scan Doctrine and Covenants 85–87 for a word or phrase that seems important to them (perhaps one they have marked in their scriptures). Ask them to write their words or phrases on the board, and choose a few to discuss.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 85:6</heading>
<heading>The Spirit speaks with a "still small voice."</heading>
<ul>
<li>In Doctrine and Covenants 85:6, the Prophet Joseph Smith used descriptive language to tell about how the Spirit had spoken to him. What do we learn about the Holy Ghost from his description? You might ask class members to think about times when the Spirit spoke to them — how would they describe their experience? They can find additional descriptions in scripture passages like these: Luke 24:32; Mosiah 5:2; Alma 32:28; Helaman 5:30; Doctrine and Covenants 6:22–23; 11:12–13.</li>
<li>Can you think of an object lesson or demonstration that would illustrate the still, small whisperings of the Spirit? Maybe you could have some sacred music playing softly as class members enter the room. Class members could talk about how the music made them feel and how much harder it would be to hear that music if there were distracting noises. This could lead to a discussion about distractions in our lives that keep us from hearing the still, small voice. Class members could share what they do to increase their sensitivity to the Spirit — some counsel can be found in "Additional Resources."</li>
</ul>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 86:1–7</heading>
<heading>The righteous are gathered in the last days.</heading>
<ul>
<li>The following activity could help class members understand the symbolism in the parable of the wheat and the tares: You could write symbolic phrases from the parable (such as "sowers of the seed," "tares choke the wheat," "blade is springing up," and "gathering of the wheat" [verses 2–4, 7]) and possible interpretations (like "the Apostles," "the Apostasy," "the Restoration," and "missionary work") on separate strips of paper and post them on the board. Then class members could work together to match the symbols with their meanings, using what they learn from Doctrine and Covenants 86:1–7 (they could also read Matthew 13:37–43). Why is it significant that the Lord addresses this revelation "unto you my servants"? (verse 1). What messages do we find that relate to our service to the Lord? (see also verse 11).</li>
</ul>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 87:2, 6, 8</heading>
<heading>Peace is found in "holy places."</heading>
<graphics-caption>The temple is a holy place where we can feel God's love.</graphics-caption>
<ul>
<li>To help class members understand the need to "stand. . . in holy places," you might begin by inviting them to list some of the challenges we face in the latter days. They could find some examples in Doctrine and Covenants 87:2, 6. Then you could discuss how the Lord's invitation in verse 8 can help with these challenges. Questions like these could help:
<ul>
<li>What is significant about the word "stand" in this verse?</li>
<li>What makes a place holy?</li>
<li>What might move a person from a holy place?</li>
<li>How can we ensure that we are not moved?</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Perhaps class members would be willing to share with each other examples of "holy places" and what makes them holy (you might point out that a holy place can be more than just a physical location). The video "Standing in Holy Places" (ChurchofJesusChrist.org) can give additional ideas. As they share, encourage them to talk about why those places are holy to them. How do these holy places help us find peace in the midst of latter-day perils?</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>Find "a still and quiet time each day."</heading>
<p>Sister Vicki F. Matsumori, a former counselor in the Primary General Presidency, gave this counsel: "Because the Spirit is often described as a still, small voice, it is . . . important to have a time of quiet in our lives as well. The Lord has counseled us to «be still, and know that I am God» [Psalm 46:10]. If we provide a still and quiet time each day when we are not bombarded by television, computer, video games, or personal electronic devices, we allow that still, small voice an opportunity to provide personal revelation and to whisper sweet guidance, reassurance, and comfort to us" ("Helping Others Recognize the Whisperings of the Spirit," Ensign or Liahona, Nov. 2009, 11).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Prepare with people in mind.</b>"Let your understanding of the people you teach guide your [preparation]. . . . Christlike teachers are not committed to a particular style or method; they are committed to helping people build faith in Jesus Christ" (Teaching in the Savior's Way, 7).</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<heading>AUGUST 9–15</heading>
<heading>Doctrine and Covenants 88</heading>
<heading>"ESTABLISH. . . A HOUSE OF GOD"</heading>
<p>As a gospel teacher, you have a responsibility to help your class "teach one another the doctrine of the kingdom" and "words of wisdom" (Doctrine and Covenants 88:77, 118). In addition to sharing the things you are inspired to teach from Doctrine and Covenants 88, encourage class members to teach each other what they have learned.</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>Sometimes a picture can prompt sharing. You could show a picture of an olive branch (or draw one on the board) and invite class members to share verses from Doctrine and Covenants 88 that help them understand why Joseph Smith might have called this revelation an "olive leaf' the Lord's message of peace to us" (section heading).</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 88:6–50</heading>
<heading>Light and law come from Jesus Christ.</heading>
<ul>
<li>To help your class understand Doctrine and Covenants 88:6–50, you could write<i>light</i>and<i>law</i>on the board and divide the class into two groups. One group could review Doctrine and Covenants 88:6–13, 40–50, looking for things they learn about Jesus Christ from the references to light in these verses. The other group could search verses 13–26, 34–42, looking for what they learn about the importance of following His law. What do the truths about light and law in section 88 teach us about the Savior? How do they inspire us to become more like Him?</li>
</ul>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 88:62–76, 119–26</heading>
<heading>We can become clean through the Atonement of Jesus Christ.</heading>
<ul>
<li>The Lord's command to "sanctify yourselves" appears twice in section 88 (verses 68, 74). If you feel inspired to discuss what that means, you might start by exploring together definitions of the word<i>sanctify</i>or reviewing some of the passages listed under "Sanctification" in the Guide to the Scriptures (scriptures.ChurchofJesusChrist.org). You could also invite class members to read Doctrine and Covenants 88:62–76, 119–26 and discuss questions like these with a partner: How do we become sanctified? What promises from the Lord do we find in these verses? Why does the Lord want us to be clean? They may also find answers to these questions in President Dallin H. Oaks's message "Cleansed by Repentance" (Ensign or Liahona, May 2019, 91–94; see also "Additional Resources").</li>
</ul>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 88:77–78, 118–26</heading>
<heading>The Lord wants us to seek learning by study and by faith.</heading>
<ul>
<li>The counsel the Lord gave to help establish the "school of the prophets" in Kirtland (verse 137) could help your class in your efforts to "teach one another the doctrine of the kingdom" (verse 77). Maybe you could explore verses 77–78 and 118–26 and discuss how to make your class a "house of learning" (verse 119). Class members could write some "class rules" or principles based on these verses that will guide your learning in class. You might also ask class members to share how they are trying to apply these principles as they "seek learning" (verse 118).</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>Our homes can be places of spiritual learning.</graphics-caption>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 88:119</heading>
<heading>The temple is the house of God.</heading>
<ul>
<li>If possible, display a picture of the nearest temple on the board, and invite the class to write next to it words from verse 119 used to describe the house of the Lord. Invite them to share experiences that show how the temple matches each description. You could also discuss how this verse could guide our lives.</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>Cleansed by repentance.</heading>
<p>President Dallin H. Oaks taught:
"Repentance begins with our Savior, and it is a joy, not a burden. . . .
"To be cleansed by repentance, we must forsake our sins and confess them to the Lord and to His mortal judge where required (see Doctrine and Covenants 58:43). Alma taught that we must also «bring forth works of righteousness» (Alma 5:35). All of this is part of the frequent scriptural invitation to come unto Christ.
"We need to partake of the sacrament each Sabbath day. In that ordinance we make covenants and receive blessings that help us overcome all acts and desires that block us from the perfection our Savior invites us to achieve (see Matthew 5:48; 3 Nephi 12:48). As we «deny [ourselves] of all ungodliness, and love God with all [our] might, mind and strength,» then we may «be perfect in Christ» and be «sanctified through the shedding of His blood, to become holy, without spot» (Moroni 10:32–33). What a promise! What a miracle! What a blessing!" ("Cleansed by Repentance," Ensign or Liahona, May 2019, 92).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Find resources to support the principles.</b>In addition to the suggestions in this outline, you could look for Church videos, music, or artwork to teach the principles in Doctrine and Covenants 88. (See Teaching in the Savior's Way, 17–18.)</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<heading>AUGUST 16–22</heading>
<heading>Doctrine and Covenants 89–92</heading>
<heading>"A PRINCIPLE WITH PROMISE"</heading>
<p>As you prepare to teach, consider the principles that stood out to you as you studied sections 89–92 this week.</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>Here are questions you can use to encourage class members to share something from their scripture study: What did you read this week that strengthened your faith in Jesus Christ? in Joseph Smith's prophetic calling? What did you read that helped better understand Heavenly Father's plan for His children?</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 89</heading>
<heading>The Word of Wisdom is a "principle with promise."</heading>
<ul>
<li>Many people may see the Word of Wisdom as simply a list of "dos" and "don'ts." To help class members ponder the principles behind this instruction, invite them to search Doctrine and Covenants 89 with questions like the following in mind: Why did the Lord give us the Word of Wisdom? What does this revelation teach us about Heavenly Father and His plan for us? The statement in "Additional Resources" might be helpful. If you feel it would benefit class members, you could invite them to list on the board the healthy and harmful practices the Lord identified in Doctrine and Covenants 89:5–17. Then they could review "Physical and Emotional Health" in For the Strength of Youth (25–27) and add to their lists other things they find. How have the promises in verses 18–21 been fulfilled in our lives?</li>
<li>Here's another way to help class members discuss the principles in the Word of Wisdom. You could divide the class into three groups and ask each group to read section 89, looking for answers to one of the following questions: What principles can give encouragement to someone who struggles to obey the Word of Wisdom? What principles can help us not be judgmental of those struggling to obey it? What principles can comfort us when we have health problems despite living the Word of Wisdom? As part of this activity, you could share President Dieter F. Uchtdorf's experience in training to become a fighter pilot (see "Continue in Patience," Ensign or Liahona, May 2010, 58). Encourage class members to reflect on something they felt impressed to do during the discussion, and give them time to write down their impressions.</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>God revealed the Word of Wisdom to help His children.</graphics-caption>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 90:1–17</heading>
<heading>The First Presidency holds "the keys of the kingdom."</heading>
<ul>
<li>This week's outline in<i>Come, Follow Me—For Individuals and Families</i>suggests that members search Doctrine and Covenants 90:1–17 to learn about the First Presidency. You could ask class members to share what they learned at home from this activity, or you could search these verses as a class. Class members could also find phrases in "Come, Listen to a Prophet's Voice" (Hymns, no. 21) or another song about prophets that relate to teachings in these verses. How has the service of the First Presidency helped you know Heavenly Father and Jesus Christ?</li>
</ul>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 91</heading>
<heading>"The Spirit manifesteth truth."</heading>
<ul>
<li>In the world today, we are exposed to messages that contain "many things. . . that are true" and "many things . . . that are not true" (verses 1–2). Invite class members to look in section 91 for counsel about the Apocrypha that can help them discern truth in the messages they encounter. What examples can they share of how the Spirit has helped them discern truth?</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>The Word of Wisdom.</heading>
<p>President Boyd K. Packer taught:
"The Word of Wisdom was «given for a principle with promise» [Doctrine and Covenants 89:3]. That word principle in the revelation is a very important one. A principle is an enduring truth, a law, a rule you can adopt to guide you in making decisions. Generally principles are no spelled out in detail. That leaves you free to find your way with an enduring truth, a principle, as your anchor.
"Members write in asking if this thing or that is against the Word of Wisdom. It's well known that tea, coffee, liquor, and tobacco are against it. It has not been spelled out in more detail. Rather, we teach the principle together with the promised blessings. There are many habit-forming, addictive things that one can drink or chew or inhale or inject injure both body and spirit which are not mentioned in the revelation. . . .
"Honor the principle of the Word of Wisdom and you will receive the promised blessings" ("The Word of Wisdom: The Principle and the Promises," Ensign, May 1996, 17–18).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Bear testimony often.</b>Your simple, sincere witness of spiritual truths can have a powerful influence on those you teach. Your witness does not need to be eloquent or lengthy. It may, for example, be a simple testimony of the blessings you have received from living the Word of Wisdom. (See Teaching in the Savior's Way, 35.)</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<graphics-caption>I See the Son of Man Standing on the Right Hand of God, by Walter Rane</graphics-caption>
<heading>AUGUST 23–29</heading>
<heading>Doctrine and Covenants 93</heading>
<heading>"RECEIVE OF HIS FULNESS"</heading>
<p>The people you teach are precious spirit sons and daughters of Heavenly Parents and have divine potential. After studying Doctrine and Covenants 93, what do you feel inspired to do to help them grow in "light and truth"? (verse 36).</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>Write on the board<i>In Doctrine and Covenants 93, Jesus Christ invited us to. . .</i>Invite class members to suggest ways they would complete the sentence.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 93</heading>
<heading>We worship God the Father and His Son, Jesus Christ.</heading>
<ul>
<li>In their study of Doctrine and Covenants 93, class members may have found many truths about Heavenly Father and Jesus Christ. Invite class members to share what they found. You could also divide the class into groups and give each group several verses to study together. Each group could then share with the class what they learned about "how to worship, and . . . what [we] worship" (verse 19).</li>
</ul>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 93:1–39</heading>
<heading>We can "receive of [God's] fulness, and be glorified."</heading>
<graphics-caption>We receive God's light as we keep His commandments and learn from Him.</graphics-caption>
<ul>
<li>Doctrine and Covenants 93 contains many truths about our eternal nature and potential as children of God. Some class members may have discovered these truths during their study of section 93 at home (see this week's outline in Come, Follow Me—For Individuals and Families). Those who did could share what they found, and you could discover other truths as a class. How could these truths affect the way we treat people around us―or ourselves?</li>
<li>Here's another way to learn about our eternal nature and potential: class members could read together verse 24 and write on the board the three headings<i>As we are, As we were,</i>and<i>As we are to come.</i>You could then divide the class into three groups and ask each group to search Doctrine and Covenants 93:6–39, looking for truths about our present, past, or future eternal identity. Each group could write under the headings what they found. How do these truths influence the choices we make?</li>
</ul>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 93:40–50</heading>
<heading>We are commanded to "set in order [our] own house."</heading>
<ul>
<li>The command to "set in order your own house" (verse 43) isn't about organizing cupboards and closets but about teaching and learning — "light and truth" (verse 42). Perhaps class members could share how they are trying to follow this counsel. What are some challenges they face? What truths or principles in Doctrine and Covenants 93 can help?</li>
<li>As part of your discussion of these verses, class members could read parts of President Henry B. Eyring's message "A Home Where the Spirit of the Lord Dwells" (Ensign or Liahona, May 2019, 22–25) and share any insights related to the truths in Doctrine and Covenants 93:40–50. (See also the statement in "Additional Resources.")</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>"See that they are more diligent and concerned at home."</heading>
<p>Elder David A. Bednar taught:
"In my office is a beautiful painting of a wheat field. The painting is a vast collection of individual brushstrokes — none of which in isolation is very interesting or impressive. In fact, if you stand close to the canvas, all you can see is a mass of seemingly unrelated and unattractive streaks of yellow and gold and brown paint. However, as you gradually move away from the canvas, all of the individual brushstrokes combine together and produce a magnificent landscape of a wheat field. Many ordinary, individual brushstrokes work together to create a captivating and beautiful painting.
"Each family prayer, each episode of family scripture study, and each family home evening is a brushstroke on the canvas of our souls. No one event may appear to be very impressive or memorable. But just as the yellow and gold and brown strokes of paint complement each other and produce an impressive masterpiece, so our consistency in doing seemingly small things can lead to significant spiritual results. «Wherefore, be not weary in well-doing, for ye are laying the foundation of a great work. And out of small things proceedeth that which is great» (D&amp;C 64:33). Consistency is a key principle as we lay the foundation of a great work in our individual lives and as we become more diligent and concerned in our own homes" ("More Diligent and Concerned at Home," Ensign or Liahona, Nov. 2009, 19–20).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Express love.</b>"Depending on your circumstances, expressing love to those you teach may mean giving them sincere compliments, taking an interest in their lives, listening carefully to them, involving them in the lesson, performing acts of service for them, or simply greeting them warmly when you see them" (Teaching in the Savior's Way, 6).</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<graphics-caption>Kirtland Temple, by Al Rounds</graphics-caption>
<heading>AUGUST 30–SEPTEMBER 5</heading>
<heading>Doctrine and Covenants 94–97</heading>
<heading>"FOR THE SALVATION OF ZION"</heading>
<p>How can you best help class members desire to receive the blessings promised in Doctrine and Covenants 94–97?</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>Perhaps class members could share something they found in Doctrine and Covenants 94–97 that inspires them to go to the temple more often. Or they could share other messages that inspired them as they read these sections.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 95:8; 97:10–17</heading>
<heading>In the temple God blesses His people.</heading>
<ul>
<li>How might you use the truths taught in Doctrine and Covenants 95 and 97 to inspire class members to seek the blessings of the temple more diligently? One way is to place a picture of the temple in the center of the board and ask class members why they think the Lord instructs His Saints to build temples. Class members could look for a few answers in Doctrine and Covenants 95:8; 97:10–17 and write what they find on the board around the picture of the temple. (They can find additional answers in "Why Latter-day Saints Build Temples" [temples.ChurchofJesusChrist.org].) How have these purposes been fulfilled in our lives? How can we make the temple a more important part of our lives?</li>
<li><p>The Church provides multiple resources that teach about temples. Consider how you might use some of them to enrich a class discussion about Doctrine and Covenants 95 and 97 and inspire class members to seek temple blessings more diligently. For example, before class you could invite a few class members to review the resources at temples.ChurchofJesusChrist.org or Temples of The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints (special issue of the Ensign or Liahona, Oct. 2010). Ask these class members to come prepared to share something they learned that supports the teachings in sections 95 and 97.</p>
<p>If you teach youth, you could invite them to read "Making the Temple a Part of Your Life" (in Temples of The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints, 77–78) and share how they make the temple a priority in their lives. </p>
<p>The videos "Two Apostles Lead a Virtual Tour of the Rome Italy Temple" and "Temples" (ChurchofJesusChrist.org) can help those who are preparing to go to the temple.</p>
<p>You could also sing together a hymn about temples and discuss what it teaches (see the topics index in Hymns).</p></li>
</ul>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 97:8–9</heading>
<heading>We can be accepted of the Lord.</heading>
<ul>
<li>What do we learn from Doctrine and Covenants 97:8 about what it means to be accepted of the Lord? How is that different from the ways we sometimes seek acceptance in the world? What blessings are promised in verse 9 to those who are accepted of the Lord? Class members could also review Elder Erich W. Kopischke's message "Being Accepted of the Lord" (Ensign or Liahona, May 2013, 104–6) and share how it helps them understand these verses. The statement in "Additional Resources" includes Elder Kopischke's invitation to seek the Lord's acceptance in our lives.</li>
</ul>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 97:18–28</heading>
<heading>Zion is "the pure in heart."</heading>
<ul>
<li>To help your class members think about what Zion is, you might write on the board<i>What is Zion?</i>and invite them to look for answers in Doctrine and Covenants 97:19 and 21 (see also Moses 7:18; Gospel Topics, "Zion," topics.ChurchofJesusChrist.org). It might be helpful to discuss how the Savior helps us become "pure in heart." What do we feel inspired to do to build Zion in our lives? in our ward or branch? in our community?</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>Building the Kirtland Temple made the Saints more "pure in heart."</graphics-caption>
<ul>
<li>The Lord taught about Zion after first commanding the Saints to build a temple "for the salvation of Zion" (see Doctrine and Covenants 97:12, 18–28). Why is the temple an important part of building Zion? How are the promises the Lord made about Zion in verses 18–28 being fulfilled in our day?</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>Being accepted of the Lord.</heading>
<p>Referring to the 'simple pattern' taught in Doctrine and Covenants 97:8, Elder Erich W. Kopischke taught:
"Seeking and receiving the acceptance of the Lord will lead to the knowledge that we are chosen and blessed by Him. We will gain increased confidence that He will lead us and direct us for good. His tender mercies will become evident in our hearts, in our lives, and in our families.
"With all my heart I invite you to seek the Lord's acceptance and enjoy His promised blessings. As we follow the simple pattern the Lord has laid out, we will come to know that we are accepted of Him, regardless of our position, status, or mortal limitations" ("Being Accepted of the Lord," Ensign or Liahona, May 2013, 106).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Get to know those you teach.</b>Each person you teach has unique experiences, perspectives, and talents. Pray to know how each person's contributions can be a blessing to the entire class. (See Teaching in the Savior's Way, 7.)</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<graphics-caption>C. C. A. Christensen (1831–1912), Saints Driven from Jackson County Missouri, c. 1878, tempera on muslin, 77 4 x 113 inches. Brigham Young University Museum of Art, gift of the grandchildren of C. C. A. Christensen, 1970</graphics-caption>
<heading>SEPTEMBER 6–12</heading>
<heading>Doctrine and Covenants 98–101</heading>
<heading>"BE STILL AND KNOW THAT I AM GOD"</heading>
<p>What kinds of challenges or trials do members of your class experience? What words of counsel and comfort in Doctrine and Covenants 98–101 could help them?</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>You could invite class members to share something they learned from Doctrine and Covenants 98–101 that helped them with a trial or challenge they have been facing.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 98:1–3, 11–16, 23–30, 37; 101:2–5, 9–16</heading>
<heading>Our trials can work together for our good.</heading>
<ul>
<li>The persecution or opposition we face today may be different from what the Saints faced in Missouri in 1833, but the Lord's counsel in Doctrine and Covenants 98 is still applicable. To help class members learn from this counsel, consider writing questions like the following on the board:<i>In what ways does the Lord want His Saints to view opposition? How does the Lord want us to respond to persecution?</i>Class members could work in small groups to find answers in Doctrine and Covenants 98:1–3, 11–16, 23–30 and then discuss what they learn. What truths do we find that can help us be better disciples of Jesus Christ? The statements in "Additional Resources" could add to this discussion.</li>
<li>In times of persecution or trials, this message from sections 98 and 101 can help: the Lord will help us if we are willing to trust Him. To help class members find this message, you could write the following list of verses on the board and invite class members to choose a few to read: Doctrine and Covenants 98:1–3, 11–12, 37; 101:2–5, 9–16. Ask them to share what they find that encourages them to trust in the Lord. What do these verses teach about how to put our trust in the Lord? (See also Linda S. Reeves, "Claim the Blessings of Your Covenants," Ensign or Liahona, Nov. 2013, 118–20.)</li>
</ul>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 101:1–8, 43–62</heading>
<heading>Following God's counsel helps keep us safe.</heading>
<ul>
<li>How can you help class members recognize the safety that comes as we "hearken unto the voice of the Lord"? (verse 7). Perhaps you can invite a few class members to act out the parable in Doctrine and Covenants 101:43–62 as another class member reads it aloud. You could then discuss questions like these: What might the different elements of the parable represent? What caused the servants to lose the vineyard? What lessons do we learn from the actions of the servants? What do we learn about the Lord from the actions of the nobleman? It may also be helpful to compare verses 1–8 with verses 47–51 and discuss how we can be "faithful and wise" in our efforts to build Zion in our individual lives, in our homes, and as a Church.</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>Detail from Christ and the Rich Young Ruler, by Heinrich Hof</graphics-caption>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>Turning the other cheek takes Christian courage.</heading>
<p>Elder Robert D. Hales taught:
"Some people mistakenly think responses such as silence, meekness, forgiveness, and bearing humble testimony are passive or weak. But to love [our] enemies, bless them that curse [us], do good to them that hate [us], and pray for them which despitefully use [us], and persecute [us]' (Matthew 5:44) takes faith, strength, and, most of all, Christian courage. . .
"When we do not retaliate — when we turn the other cheek and resist feelings of anger — we too stand with the Savior. We show forth His love, which is the only power that can subdue the adversary and answer our accusers without accusing them in return. That is not weakness.<i>That</i>is Christian courage" ("Christian Courage: The Price of Discipleship," Ensign or Liahona, Nov. 2008, 72).</p>
<heading>To forgive is not to condone.</heading>
<p>Elder Kevin R. Duncan said: "Brothers and sisters, please do not misunderstand. To forgive is not to condone. We do not rationalize bad behavior or allow others to mistreat us<i>because</i>of their struggles, pains, or weaknesses. But we<i>can</i>gain greater understanding and peace when we see with a broader perspective. . . . Forgiveness is a glorious, healing principle. We do not need to be a victim twice. We can forgive" ("The Healing Ointment of Forgiveness," Ensign or Liahona, May 2016, 35).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Include those who are struggling.</b>Sometimes struggling class members just need to be included in order to feel loved. Consider asking them to accept an assignment in an upcoming lesson, inviting them to class, or making sure they have a way to get to church. Don't give up if they don't respond to your efforts at first (see Teaching in the Savior's Way, 8–9).</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<graphics-caption>C. C. A. Christensen (1831–1912), Zion's Camp, c. 1878, tempera on muslin, 78 x 114 inches. Brigham Young University Museum of Art, gift of the grandchildren of C. C. A. Christensen, 1970</graphics-caption>
<heading>SEPTEMBER 13–19</heading>
<heading>Doctrine and Covenants 102–105</heading>
<heading>"AFTER MUCH TRIBULATION. . . COMETH THE BLESSING"</heading>
<p>As you prepare to teach Doctrine and Covenants 102–5, listen to the promptings of the Spirit. He may lead you to principles not mentioned in this outline that will bless the people you teach</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>Class members could write down a verse or two from Doctrine and Covenants 102–5 that they find personally meaningful. Then they could trade verses with another class member and discuss with each other what they learned from these verses.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 103; 105</heading>
<heading>Our trials teach us valuable lessons and give us experience.</heading>
<ul>
<li>As class members studied sections 103 and 105 this week, they may have found principles that can help us during times of trial or opposition; let them share what they found. Or you might invite them to look for such principles in Doctrine and Covenants 103:5–7, 12, 36; 105:5–6, 9–12, 18–19 (see also "Additional Resources"). What do these principles suggest about how we can respond when faced with difficulty or disappointment? Class members might be willing to share experiences in which blessings came "after much tribulation" (Doctrine and Covenants 103:12).</li>
<li>If you feel that some historical background or personal accounts about Zion's Camp would be useful, you could invite someone to review one of the following resources before class and briefly share what they learn:<i>Saints,</i>1:194–206; "The Acceptable Offering of Zion's Camp" (Revelations in Context, 213–18); or "Voices of the Restoration: Zion's Camp" (in this week's outline in Come, Follow Me—For Individuals and Families). If we could travel back in time and talk to Zion's Camp, what might we say to encourage them? What might they say to encourage us?</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>Zion's Camp stayed along the banks of Little Fishing River, pictured here.</graphics-caption>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 104:11–18</heading>
<heading>Each of us is "a steward over earth</heading>
<ul>
<li>To help class members personalize the teachings in Doctrine and Covenants 104:11–18, you could invite them to imagine that they were going to entrust something precious to the care of someone else. What would they say to that person? What would they expect of him or her? Class members could then read Doctrine and Covenants 104:11–18 to discover what the Lord has entrusted into our care and what He expects of us. How might these verses affect the way we think about the world, our blessings, or the people around us?</li>
<li>To help class members better understand "the way that . . . the Lord [has] decreed to provide for [His] saints" (Doctrine and Covenants 104:16), consider sharing the video "The Labor of His Hands" (ChurchofJesusChrist.org). Based on what we learn from this video and Doctrine and Covenants 104:11–18, what is the Lord's way of providing for His Saints? You might also share this statement by President Marion G. Romney: "The Lord. . . could take care of [the poor] without our help if it were his purpose to do so. . . . But we need this experience; for it is only through our learning how to take care of each other that we develop within us the Christlike love and disposition necessary to qualify us to return to his presence" ("Living Welfare Principles," Ensign, Nov. 1981, 92). Give class members a few minutes to record their impressions about how they can help provide for others in the Lord's way.</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>The purifying power of trials.</heading>
<p>Elder Orson F. Whitney taught: "No pain that we suffer, no trial that we experience is wasted. It ministers to our education, to the development of such qualities as patience, faith, fortitude and humility. All that we suffer and all that we endure, especially when we endure it patiently, builds up our characters, purifies our hearts, expands our souls, and makes us more tender and charitable, more worthy to be called the children of God. . . and it is through sorrow and suffering, toil and tribulation, that we gain the education that we come here to acquire and which will make us more like our Father and Mother in heaven" (in Spencer W. Kimball, Faith Precedes the Miracle [1972], 98).</p>
<p>Elder David A. Bednar said: "At some point in each of our lives, we will be invited to march in our own Zion's Camp. The timing of the invitations will vary, and the particular obstacles we may encounter on the journey will be different. But our ongoing and consistent response to this inevitable call ultimately will provide the answer to the question «Who's on the Lord's side?»" ("On the Lord's Side: Lessons from Zion's Camp," Ensign, July 2017, 35).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Work together with family members.</b>"Because the home is the center of gospel living and learning, your efforts to strengthen a class member will be most effective when you work together with [his or her]. . . family members" (Teaching in the Savior's Way, 8–9).</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<heading>SEPTEMBER 20–26</heading>
<heading>Doctrine and Covenants 106–108</heading>
<heading>"TO HAVE THE HEAVENS OPENED"</heading>
<p>As you study Doctrine and Covenants 106–8, consider the spiritual experiences that members of your class may be having as they study these sections. As you prepare to teach them, it might be helpful to find out what they found meaningful before you meet together.</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>Invite class members to share a verse from these sections that teaches a principle that could strengthen someone in their Church service.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 106; 108</heading>
<heading>The Lord instructs, encourages, and supports those He calls to serve.</heading>
<ul>
<li>As class members studied Doctrine and Covenants 106 and 108 this week, they may have found phrases that could help those serving in Church callings (see this week's outline in Come, Follow Me—For Individuals and Families). Consider giving class members time to write phrases they found in these sections on the board and asking them to share their insights. What experiences have they had that relate to or illustrate these phrases?</li>
</ul>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 107</heading>
<heading>The Lord leads His Church through priesthood authority.</heading>
<ul>
<li>You could begin a discussion about priesthood offices by inviting the class to make a list of reasons the Lord gives us prophets, apostles, and other Church leaders. Perhaps class members could add to their list after reading together Doctrine and Covenants 107:18–20. Then you could spend time reviewing the responsibilities the Lord gives those holding the following offices: the First Presidency (verses 9, 21–22, 65–66, 91–92), the Twelve Apostles (verses 23–24, 33–35, 38, 58), the Seventy (verses 25–26, 34, 93–97), and bishops (verses 13–17, 68–76, 87–88). What can we do to uphold our leaders by our "confidence, faith, and prayer[s]"? (verse 22).</li>
<li>How would we answer if a friend not of our faith asked us, "What is the priesthood?" or "What are priesthood keys?" How might the teachings in "Additional Resources" affect our answers? Perhaps class members can also find helpful insights in Doctrine and Covenants 107:1–4, 18–20 (see also True to the Faith, 124–28). How does the priesthood help us receive "the mysteries of the kingdom" and "have the heavens opened unto [us]"? How does it help us "enjoy the communion and presence of God the Father, and Jesus"? (verse 19).</li>
</ul>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 107:27–31, 85</heading>
<heading>The Lord governs His kingdom through councils.</heading>
<ul>
<li>President M. Russell Ballard said, "I know councils are the Lord's way and that He created all things in the universe through a heavenly council" ("Family Councils," Ensign or Liahona, May 2016, 63). How can you help those you teach understand how to counsel together at home and at church? Perhaps you could ask a few members to come prepared to share their experiences at church or at home in which they applied the principles of counseling in Doctrine and Covenants 107:27–31, 85 (or in President Ballard's message referenced above). Consider inviting class members during the week to come to class prepared to share ideas about what makes a council effective. Encourage class members to identify principles they learn from this discussion that will help them be more effective as they participate in future home and church councils.</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>Counseling together is one way the Lord accomplishes His work.</graphics-caption>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>Priesthood authority.</heading>
<p>President Dallin H. Oaks taught:
"We are not accustomed to speaking of women having the authority of the priesthood in their Church callings, but what other authority can it be? When a woman — young or old — is set apart to preach the gospel as a full-time missionary, she is given priesthood authority to perform a priesthood function. The same is true when a woman is set apart to function as an officer or teacher in a Church organization under the direction of one who holds the keys of the priesthood. Whoever functions in an office or calling received from one who holds priesthood keys exercises priesthood authority in performing her or his assigned duties" ("The Keys and Authority of the Priesthood," Ensign or Liahona, May 2014, 51).</p>
<p>President M. Russell Ballard said:
"Our Father in Heaven is with His generous power. All men and all women have access to this power for help in their lives. All who have made sacred covenants with the Lord and who honor those covenants are eligible to receive personal revelation, to be blessed by the ministering of angels, to commune with God, to receive the fulness of the gospel, and, ultimately, to become heirs alongside Jesus Christ of all our Father has" ("Men and Women in the Work of the Lord," New Era, Apr. 2014, 4–5).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Help learners lift each other.</b>"Each individual in your class is a rich source of testimony, insights, and experiences with living the gospel. Invite them to share with and lift each other" (Teaching in the Savior's Way, 5).</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<graphics-caption>Kirtland Temple, by Jon McNaughton</graphics-caption>
<heading>SEPTEMBER 27–OCTOBER 3</heading>
<heading>Doctrine and Covenants 109–110</heading>
<heading>"IT IS THY HOUSE, A PLACE OF THY HOLINESS"</heading>
<p>Sections 109 and 110 describe some of the most sacred events of the Restoration. Be sure to let class members share what they thought and felt as they studied these events.</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>The Lord declared that "the fame of this house [the Kirtland Temple] shall spread to foreign lands" (Doctrine and Covenants 110:10). You might invite class members to share something they found in their study that they feel should be spread to people around the world.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 109; 110:1–10</heading>
<heading>The Lord wants to bless us in His holy house.</heading>
<ul>
<li><p>Studying section 109 is a wonderful opportunity to help class members strengthen their desire to worship in the temple. You could write on the board the numbers of some verses that mention the blessings of the temple — such as verses 12–13, 22–23, 24–28, 29–32. Class members could choose verses to read and ponder them, individually or in groups, and then summarize for the class the blessing those verses describe. Members who have been to the temple could share how they have experienced these blessings in their lives.</p>
<p>You could also read or sing together "The Spirit of God" (Hymns, no. 2), which was sung at the Kirtland Temple dedication. Class members could point out blessings of the temple described in the hymn and share any related experiences they have had, as appropriate.</p></li>
<li>Receiving temple blessings often requires sacrifice. What does Doctrine and Covenants 109:5 teach about the sacrifices the early Saints made to build the Kirtland Temple? Perhaps someone could come prepared to talk about these sacrifices (see "A House for Our God," Revelations in Context, 169–71). What sacrifices do we make to receive temple blessings today? Perhaps class members would be willing to share their experiences. Some modern examples are found in the videos "Sealed Together: The Manaus Temple Caravan" and "Temples Are a Beacon" (ChurchofJesusChrist.org).</li>
<li>Studying the description of the risen Savior in Doctrine and Covenants 110:1–10 is a great way to build our faith in Jesus Christ. You might ask class members to note the imagery in these verses and consider what these images teach us about Jesus Christ. What might the "paved work of pure gold" represent? or the voice "as the sound of the rushing of great waters"?</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>Each end of the Kirtland Temple has pulpits for priesthood leaders.</graphics-caption>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 110:11–16</heading>
<heading>The priesthood keys needed to accomplish God's work are in the Church today.</heading>
<ul>
<li>To help class members understand the priesthood keys that Moses, Elias, and Elijah committed to Joseph Smith and Oliver Cowdery in the Kirtland Temple, you could invite them to read and discuss the statement in "Additional Resources," individually or in groups. Why are these keys significant in our lives now? You might also ask each class member to choose one of the prophets who committed those keys — Moses, Elias, and Elijah — and learn about him from the Bible Dictionary or Guide to the Scriptures. What do the lives of these prophets teach us about the keys they committed? This could lead to a discussion about what the Lord expects us to do now that these keys are on the earth.</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>Keys provide power and authority for God's work.</heading>
<p>Elder Quentin L. Cook explained:
"The Kirtland Temple, both in location and size, was relatively obscure. But in terms of its enormous significance to mankind, it was<i>eternity-shaping.</i>Ancient prophets restored priesthood keys for the eternal saving ordinances of the gospel of Jesus Christ. This resulted in overwhelming joy for faithful members.
"These keys provide the «power from on high» [Doctrine and Covenants 38:38] for divinely appointed responsibilities that constitute the primary purpose of the Church. On that wonderful Easter day in the Kirtland Temple, three keys were restored:
"<b>First</b>, Moses appeared and committed the keys of the gathering of Israel from the four parts of the earth, which is missionary work.
"<b>Second</b>, Elias appeared and committed the keys of the dispensation of the gospel of Abraham, which includes the restoration of the Abrahamic covenant [see Abraham 2:8–11]. President Russell M. Nelson has taught that the purpose of the covenant keys is to prepare members for the kingdom of God [see 'Covenants,' Ensign or Liahona, Nov. 2011, 88]. . . .
"<b>Third</b>, Elijah appeared and committed the keys of the sealing power in this dispensation, which is family history work and temple ordinances enabling salvation for the living and the dead" ("Prepare to Meet God," Ensign or Liahona, May 2018, 114–15).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Invite the Spirit into your teaching.</b>"The ultimate purpose of everything a gospel teacher does every question, every scripture, every activity is to invite the Spirit to build faith and to invite all to come unto Christ. . . . Sacred music, the scriptures, words of latter-day prophets, expressions of love and testimony, and moments of quiet contemplation can all invite the presence of the Spirit" (Teaching in the Savior's Way, 10).</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<heading>OCTOBER 4–10</heading>
<heading>Doctrine and Covenants 111–114</heading>
<heading>"I WILL ORDER ALL THINGS FOR YOUR GOOD"</heading>
<p>As you read Doctrine and Covenants 111–14, consider the spiritual truths that the Lord wants your class members to understand. The Holy Ghost will help guide you to know what principles to focus on.</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>Consider drawing a treasure chest on the board. Class members could write on the board verses from sections 111–14 where they found something they consider "much treasure" (Doctrine and Covenants 111:2). Ask several members to share what they found valuable in those verses.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 111</heading>
<heading>The Lord can "order all things for [our] good."</heading>
<ul>
<li>The Lord's counsel in Doctrine and Covenants 111 can help members of your class when they worry about temporal or spiritual concerns, just as it helped Joseph Smith with his concerns about Zion. You could begin a discussion of this section by inviting class members to list on the board things that they or people they know are worried about. Then, with those concerns in mind, they could search section 111 for counsel and comfort the Lord gives to help us. Class members could share how the Savior has helped them when they put their faith in Him.</li>
<li>Members of your class may have had experiences like Joseph's — when they felt the Lord accepted them despite their "follies" (Doctrine and Covenants 111:1). How do their experiences exemplify the truths taught in Doctrine and Covenants 111? For instance, when have they felt the Lord "order[ed] all things for [their] good"? (verse 11). What do these experiences teach them about the Savior and about themselves?</li>
</ul>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 112:3–15, 22</heading>
<heading>The Lord will lead those who humbly seek His will.</heading>
<ul>
<li>To help class members discuss what section 112 teaches about humility, consider dividing the class into three groups. Give each group one of the following questions to ponder as they review verses 3–15 and 22: What is humility? How can we become more humble? What blessings are promised to the humble? Give the class time to share their answers. The groups could gain additional insights by reading Elder Quentin L. Cook's statement in "Additional Resources" or the section titled "Humility" in<i>Preach My Gospel</i>(pages 126–27). Why is humility essential for doing the Lord's work?</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>If we are humble, the Lord will guide us and answer our prayers.</graphics-caption>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 112:12–26</heading>
<heading>Those who are truly converted come to know Jesus Christ.</heading>
<ul>
<li>The fact that some Apostles in 1837 turned against the Prophet is a good reminder that regardless of the calling we have or how much we know about the gospel, we must individually make sure we are truly converted. Reading the counsel the Lord gave Thomas B. Marsh to help him unify the Quorum of the Twelve can give your class insights into what conversion means. Perhaps class members could read Doctrine and Covenants 112:12–26 with a family member or friend in mind — someone who might be struggling with their faith. What truths in these verses would class members emphasize to help that person become more fully converted? Give class members time to ponder what they can do to strengthen their own conversion to the Lord.</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>The Christlike attribute of humility.</heading>
<p>Elder Quentin L. Cook taught:
"Unfortunately, in our day in almost every segment of society, we see self-importance and arrogance flaunted while humility and accountability to God are denigrated. Much of society has lost its moorings and does not understand why we are on this earth. True humility, which is essential to achieve the Lord's purpose for us, is seldom evident.
"It is important to understand the magnitude of Christ's humility, righteousness, character, and intelligence, as exemplified in the scriptures. It is foolish to underestimate the necessity of continuously striving for these Christlike qualities and attributes on a day-by-day basis, particularly humility. . . .
"On July 23, 1837, the Prophet Joseph met with Elder Thomas B. Marsh, President of the Quorum of the Twelve. Elder Marsh was apparently frustrated that the Prophet had called two members of his quorum to go to England without consulting him. As Joseph met with Elder Marsh, any hurt feelings were put aside, and the Prophet received a remarkable revelation. It is now the 112th section of the Doctrine and Covenants. It gives incredible direction from heaven with respect to humility and missionary work. Verse 10 reads, «Be thou<i>humble</i>; and the Lord thy God shall lead thee by the hand, and give thee answer to thy prayers» [Doctrine and Covenants 112:10; emphasis added]" ("The Eternal Everyday," Ensign or Liahona, Nov. 2017, 51–52).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Focus on people.</b>"The way you treat people is just as important as what you teach them. Sometimes our preoccupation with presenting a lesson can prevent us from expressing our love for those we teach. . . . Consider how you could focus on what matters most" (Teaching in the Savior's Way, 6).</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<graphics-caption>Far West, by Al Rounds</graphics-caption>
<heading>OCTOBER 11–17</heading>
<heading>Doctrine and Covenants 115–120</heading>
<heading>"HIS SACRIFICE SHALL BE MORE SACRED UNTO ME THAN HIS INCREASE"</heading>
<p>As you prepare to teach, remember that your main objective is to help others build faith in Jesus Christ</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>Before you talk about principles from sections 115–20 that were meaningful to you, ask class members to share what was meaningful to them. For example, you could invite class members to complete this sentence: "I am grateful I read sections 115–20 because. . ."</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 115:4–6</heading>
<heading>The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints is a defense and a refuge.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Class members could search President Russell M. Nelson's message "The Correct Name of the Church" (Ensign or Liahona, Nov. 2018, 87–90) for insights that help them understand verses 4–6. Why is it important to use the correct name of the Church?</li>
<li>After reading together Doctrine and Covenants 115:4–6, class members could discuss how the Church and its members are like a light or a standard. You could show an image of a lighthouse in a storm and ask class members how it relates to the message of verses 5–6. How has gathering to "Zion, and . . . her stakes" given you "refuge from the storm"? (verse 6).</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>We can shine as lights to help others find refuge in the Church.</graphics-caption>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 117</heading>
<heading>Our sacrifices are sacred to the Lord.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Invite class members to imagine that they are Newel K. Whitney or his wife, Elizabeth, who owned a successful store in Kirtland but were asked by the Lord to leave their property and move to Missouri. They could then read verses 1–11 and share something the Lord said that would help them make this sacrifice.</li>
<li>Visual aids might help class members consider the "drop" we sometimes covet instead of the "weighty matters" (verse 8). Consider showing objects such as a drop of water and a bottle of water or a chocolate chip and a chocolate bar. Maybe class members could think of other examples. You could also write drop and weighty matters on the board and ask class members to list examples of things we may need to "let. . . go" (verse 5) in order to receive God's "abundance" (verse 7).</li>
<li>If class members had any impressions while reading the Lord's words about Oliver Granger in verses 12–15, invite them to share. Why might our sacrifices be more sacred to the Lord than our increase?</li>
</ul>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 119–20</heading>
<heading>By paying tithing, we help build and "sanctify the land of Zion."</heading>
<ul>
<li>Imagine the spiritual strength that could come from class members sharing with each other the blessings they've received from obeying the law of tithing. They could also read Doctrine and Covenants 119:6 and discuss how this law can "sanctify the land of Zion" and make our ward or branch "a land of Zion unto [us]." They could also read Malachi 3:8–12 to identify blessings the Lord promises for paying tithing.</li>
<li>If class members have questions about how tithing is used, you might invite them to read section 120 and the explanation in "Additional Resources." (Elder David A. Bednar also gives a helpful description in "The Windows of Heaven" [Ensign or Liahona, Nov. 2013, 19–20].) How can we help others increase their faith in the Lord's law of tithing?</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>The Council on the Disposition of the Tithes.</heading>
<p>Elder Robert D. Hales said:
"As revealed by the Lord, the use of tithing is determined by a council comprised of the First Presidency, the Quorum of the Twelve Apostles, and the Presiding Bishopric. The Lord specifically states that the council's work be directed «by mine own voice unto them» [Doctrine and Covenants 120:1]. This council is called the Council on the Disposition of the Tithes.
"It is remarkable to witness this council heed the Lord's voice. Each member is aware of and participates in all the council's decisions. No decision is made until the council is unanimous. All tithing funds are spent for the purposes of the Church, including welfare — care for the poor and needy — temples, buildings and upkeep of meetinghouses, education, curriculum — in short, the work of the Lord. . . .
". . . I bear my testimony of the Council on the Disposition of the Tithes. I have sat on this council for 17 years, as the Presiding Bishop of the Church and now as a member of the Quorum of the Twelve Apostles. Without exception, the tithing funds of this Church have been used for His purposes" ("Tithing: A Test of Faith with Eternal Blessings," Ensign or Liahona, Nov. 2002, 28).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Invite learners to teach each other.</b>"It may be appropriate to invite learners to help each other find answers to their questions. When prompted by the Spirit, you may decide to do this even if you feel that you know the answer" (Teaching in the Savior's Way, 24).</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<graphics-caption>Liberty Jail Spring, by Al Rounds</graphics-caption>
<heading>OCTOBER 18–24</heading>
<heading>Doctrine and Covenants 121–123</heading>
<heading>"O GOD, WHERE ART THOU?"</heading>
<p>The best way to prepare to teach is to read the scriptures, think about the people you teach, and follow the Spirit. The activities in this outline can supplement the inspiration you receive.</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>Invite class members to choose one message from Doctrine and Covenants 121–23 that they would want to share with someone who is suffering. Let them explain their choice.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 121:1–33; 122</heading>
<heading>If we endure our trials well, God will exalt us on high.</heading>
<ul>
<li>You may have class members who, because of difficult trials, have feelings similar to what Joseph Smith expressed in Doctrine and Covenants 121:1–6. After reading these verses together, you could invite class members to identify and share messages in verses 7–33 that give them hope and comfort during their trials. What does it mean to "endure. . . well"? (verse 8). How does the Savior help us endure well? How can we help each other endure well?</li>
<li>To help class members consider how trials can "give [us] experience" and "be for [our] good" (Doctrine and Covenants 122:7), you could give them a piece of paper and ask them to write down a trial they have experienced. On the other side of the paper, class members could write the words "experience" and "good." As you discuss together Doctrine and Covenants 122, encourage class members to write any thoughts they have about the "other side" of their trials: the "experience" or "good" they gained. Some class members may be comfortable sharing how their trial ended up being for their good. Or they could read Elder Koichi Aoyagi's experience in "Hold on Thy Way" (Ensign or Liahona, Nov. 2015, 126–28).</li>
</ul>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 121:34–46</heading>
<heading>We must be righteous to access the "powers of heaven."</heading>
<ul>
<li>It could be interesting to contrast how "power or influence" is maintained in the world with how the Lord taught that power or influence should be maintained (see section 121). To assist in this discussion, you could make a two-column table on the board labeled<i>Worldly Power</i>and<i>Powers of Heaven.</i>Class members could fill in the table with words and phrases from Doctrine and Covenants 121:34–46. How might these verses change how we see our responsibilities in our families, as ministering brothers and sisters, or in other situations where we hope to influence others for good?</li>
<li>One way to discuss the counsel and wonderful blessings in Doctrine and Covenants 121:45–46 is to divide the class into groups and ask each group to study and discuss a phrase from these verses, such as "let virtue garnish thy thoughts unceasingly" or "as the dews from heaven." They could look up definitions of words, read related scriptures in the footnotes, and discuss what the phrases mean to them. Some groups may want to draw pictures to illustrate their phrase. Invite each group to share with the class what they learned.</li>
</ul>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 122:8–9</heading>
<heading>Jesus Christ has descended below all things and strengthens us in our trials.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Understanding that Jesus Christ "hath descended below. . . all [things]" can give class members the confidence to turn to Him. These additional scriptures can help explain what this phrase means: Isaiah 53:3–4; Hebrews 2:17–18; 1 Nephi 11:16–33; Alma 7:11–13. Class members could read these verses, along with Doctrine and Covenants 122:8, looking for something that builds their faith that Jesus Christ can help them in their trials. They might also find inspiration in hymns about the Savior, such as "Where Can I Turn for Peace?" (Hymns, no. 129).</li>
<li>The statement in "Additional Resources" gives further insight about how the Savior descended below all things. You might think of a way you could demonstrate how being "beneath" a heavy object makes us "perfectly positioned to lift [it]." How has knowing that the Savior descended below all things helped us in our trials?</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>Jesus understands our suffering. Not My Will, But Thine, by Walter Rane.</graphics-caption>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>Christ descended below all things.</heading>
<p>President Dallin H. Oaks taught, "There are millions of God-fearing people who pray to God to be lifted out of their afflictions. Our Savior has revealed that He descended below all things' (D&amp;C 88:6). As Elder Neal A. Maxwell taught, «Having 'descended below all things,' He comprehends, perfectly and personally, the full range of human suffering» [Ensign, Nov. 1997, 23]. We might even say that having descended beneath it all, He is perfectly positioned to lift us and give us the strength we need to endure our afflictions" ("Strengthened by the Atonement of Jesus Christ," Ensign or Liahona, Nov. 2015, 64).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Your call is inspired.</b>As a teacher, you have been called by the Lord to bless His children. He wants you to succeed, so as you live worthy of His help, He will give you the revelation you need (see Teaching in the Savior's Way, 5).</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<graphics-caption>Nauvoo the Beautiful, by Larry Winborg</graphics-caption>
<heading>OCTOBER 25–31</heading>
<heading>Doctrine and Covenants 124</heading>
<heading>"A HOUSE UNTO MY NAME"</heading>
<p>In order for the Spirit to bring principles to our remembrance as we teach (see John 14:26), we must first diligently study and ponder those principles.</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>Consider inviting class members to share something they found in Doctrine and Covenants 124 that caused them to consider a gospel principle in a new way. What did they read — individually or as families — that changed the way they feel, think, or live?</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 124:15, 20</heading>
<heading>The Lord delights in integrity.</heading>
<ul>
<li>In section 124, the Lord praised Hyrum Smith and George Miller for their integrity. To help class members study this attribute more deeply, you might invite them to read Doctrine and Covenants 124:15, 20 and ponder what they learn about integrity from these verses. What else do we learn from the scriptures listed under "Integrity" in the Guide to the Scriptures (scriptures.ChurchofJesusChrist.org) or from Elder Richard J. Maynes's message "Earning the Trust of the Lord and Your Family"? (Ensign or Liahona, Nov. 2017, 75–77). Perhaps class members could share examples of people they know who have integrity. Why is integrity such a valued attribute?</li>
</ul>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 124:22–24, 60–61</heading>
<heading>The Lord wants us to welcome and accept others.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Members of your class may learn something from the Lord's description of the Nauvoo House that can help them in their interactions with people who are not Latter-day Saints or who have drifted away from the Church. You might draw a house on the board and invite class members to search Doctrine and Covenants 124:22–24, 60–61 for words that the Lord used to describe the purposes of the Nauvoo House. They could then write the words around the house. How might these terms also be applied to the Church of Jesus Christ? What can we do to create this same welcoming culture in our ward and our homes?</li>
</ul>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 124:25–45, 55</heading>
<heading>The Lord commands us to build temples so we can receive sacred ordinances.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Perhaps class members could imagine they are living in Nauvoo in 1841 and working on the Nauvoo Temple when a friend asks, "Why do we keep building these temples?" What would we say to this friend? Class members could look for ideas in Doctrine and Covenants 124:28–30, 37–42, 55. If some class members are unfamiliar with the ordinances mentioned in these verses, consider describing the purposes and blessings of these ordinances. See temples.ChurchofJesusChrist.org for guidance about what can appropriately be discussed outside of the temple and for pictures of temples you could show in class.</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>Joseph Smith at the Nauvoo Temple, by Gary E. Smith</graphics-caption>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 124:45–55</heading>
<heading>The Lord will bless those who strive to obey His commandments.</heading>
<ul>
<li>The Saints had been commanded to build a temple in Jackson County but were "hindered by their enemies" (Doctrine and Covenants 124:51). In verses 49–55, where the Lord addressed this situation, there may be a reassuring message for people who want to obey God's commandments but are prevented from doing so because of family or other circumstances. You might read these verses with class members and ask them to think of situations in which people might not be able to fulfill their righteous desires because of circumstances they can't control. What counsel do we find in these verses that could help someone in such a situation? What do these verses teach us about obedience?</li>
</ul>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 124:91–92</heading>
<heading>The Lord can guide us through our patriarchal blessings.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Would members of your class benefit from a discussion about patriarchs and patriarchal blessings? You could begin by inviting class members to read Doctrine and Covenants 124:91–92, looking for what Hyrum Smith was called to do. Then you could write on the board<i>What</i>and<i>Why</i>and invite class members to read "Patriarchal Blessings" (True to the Faith, 111–13) to find out what patriarchal blessings are and why they are valuable. How can a person prepare to receive a patriarchal blessing? Consider inviting a few people who have received their patriarchal blessings to share why they are grateful for them. (Remind them not to share anything too personal or sacred from their blessings.) How can we show that we treasure our patriarchal blessings?</li>
</ul>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Pray for your class members.</b>Pray by name for the people you teach. You could pray to understand their needs and to know what to teach in order to meet those needs. You might also ask Heavenly Father to "prepare their hearts" (Alma 16:16) to receive the truths you will teach. (See Teaching in the Savior's Way, 6.)</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<graphics-caption>Us with Them and Them with Us, by Caitlin Connolly</graphics-caption>
<heading>NOVEMBER 1–7</heading>
<heading>Doctrine and Covenants 125–128</heading>
<heading>"A VOICE OF GLADNESS FOR THE LIVING AND THE DEAD"</heading>
<p>Ponder these words by Elder Ulisses Soares: "The best teacher is a good role model. Teaching something that we truly live can make a difference in the hearts of those we teach" ("How Can I Understand?" Ensign or Liahona, May 2019, 7).</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>Class members could write on the board phrases from Doctrine and Covenants 125–28 that impressed them. Let them share their thoughts about those phrases. How did studying these truths influence their actions this week?</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 126</heading>
<heading>"Take especial care of your family."</heading>
<ul>
<li>The calls Brigham Young received to serve in the Church required him and his family to make great sacrifices; the Lord's words to Brigham in section 126 could inspire a class discussion about why the Lord sometimes requires sacrifice in our service. How has the Lord helped us fulfill our responsibilities at home, in Church callings, and in other aspects of life?</li>
</ul>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 127:2–4</heading>
<heading>We can rely on the Lord during difficult times.</heading>
<ul>
<li>How might Doctrine and Covenants 127:2–4 help class members who feel that, like Joseph Smith, they are swimming in "deep water"? You could invite class members to read these verses and share how they would summarize Joseph's attitude toward his challenges. What phrases from these verses would help someone who is struggling? How did Joseph rely on the Lord during his trials? How can we follow his example?</li>
</ul>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 128</heading>
<heading>The salvation of our ancestors is essential to our salvation.</heading>
<ul>
<li><p>Consider how you might inspire class members to participate in temple and family history work. Doctrine and Covenants 128:15–18 could help them feel the urgency of this work; you might invite them to search these verses for something that increases their desire to do baptisms for their deceased ancestors. Questions like these might help them ponder these verses: Why can't "we without our dead be made perfect"? (verse 15). Why does Joseph Smith call baptism for the dead the "most glorious of all subjects belonging to the everlasting gospel"? (verse 17; see also the quotation in "Additional Resources"). In what sense might the earth be cursed if there is no "welding link. . . between the fathers and the children"? (verse 18). If class members need help getting started with family history work, you could invite the ward temple and family history leader to introduce them to FamilySearch.org.</p>
<p>You could also inspire them with verses that express the joy of temple and family history work, such as Doctrine and Covenants 128:19–23. Class members could read these verses and find phrases that show how Joseph Smith felt about the salvation of the dead. Then you could ask them to share experiences when they had similar feelings about this work. Showing one of the videos in "Additional Resources" could also give them encouragement.</p></li>
<li>Because the salvation of the dead is unique to The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints, we might have opportunities to explain this doctrine to people who have never heard of it before. Class members could search Doctrine and Covenants 128 for something they could share in a conversation with someone who asks about baptism for the dead. What does this doctrine teach us about Heavenly Father and Jesus Christ? Let class members practice what they would say.</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>Videos about family history work (ChurchofJesusChrist.org).</heading>
<ul>
<li>"I Couldn't Explain the Feeling"</li>
<li>"If We Put God First"</li>
<li>"Redeeming the Dead Redeemed Me"</li>
<li>"A Visit from Father"</li>
<li>"Connected to Eternal Families"</li>
<li>"Gatherers in the Kingdom"</li>
<li>"Including Me"</li>
<li>"Is Anything Too Hard for the Lord?"</li>
</ul>
<heading>"A Glorious and Wonderful Provision."</heading>
<p>President Gordon B. Hinckley said:
"Jesus's Atonement in behalf of all represents a great vicarious sacrifice. He set the pattern under which He became a proxy for all mankind. This pattern under which one man can act in behalf of another is carried forward in the ordinances of the house of the Lord. Here we serve in behalf of those who have died without a knowledge of the gospel. Theirs is the option to accept or reject the ordinance which is performed. They are placed on an equal footing with those who walk the earth. The dead are given the same opportunity as the living. Again, what a glorious and wonderful provision the Almighty has made through His revelation to His Prophet" ("The Great Things Which God Has Revealed," Ensign or Liahona, May 2005, 82–83).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Pray for your class members.</b>Pray by name for those you teach, and seek to understand their specific needs. As you do so, Heavenly Father can help you know what to teach in order to help meet those needs. (See Teaching in the Savior's Way, 6.)</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<graphics-caption>Joseph Smith in Nauvoo, 1840, by Theodore Gorka</graphics-caption>
<heading>NOVEMBER 8–14</heading>
<heading>Doctrine and Covenants 129–132</heading>
<heading>"WHEN WE OBTAIN ANY BLESSING FROM GOD, IT IS BY OBEDIENCE"</heading>
<p>While it's important to have a teaching plan, it's also important to be responsive to the Spirit and the needs of class members. Find out from class members what principles in sections 129–32 were meaningful to them.</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>Class members may have learned things from their study of sections 129–32 that relate to a variety of gospel topics. To give them a chance to share what they learned, you could write a few of those topics on the board, such as<i>angels, exaltation, obedience, the nature of God,</i>and<i>eternal marriage</i>(you might also write<i>other</i>on the board to account for additional topics). Class members could take a few minutes to find a verse in these sections that relates to one of the topics and write the reference on the board. You could then read the verses as a class and talk about what each one teaches about that topic.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 130:2, 18–23; 131:1–4; 132:20–25</heading>
<heading>This life is meant to prepare us for exaltation.</heading>
<ul>
<li>There are many things we don't know about exaltation or life in the celestial kingdom — much of it may be beyond our current ability to understand. But God has revealed a few precious clues, and many of them are found in Doctrine and Covenants 130–32. Class members could study one or more of the references listed above and share any insights they find about exaltation or the celestial kingdom. How does knowing this information about eternal life bless our lives now?</li>
</ul>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 130:20–21; 132:5</heading>
<heading>Blessings come from obedience to God.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Doctrine and Covenants 130:20–21 and 132:5 teach the same principle. Encourage class members to read both passages and state, in their own words, what that principle is. How has this principle been demonstrated in our lives? How can we find hope and reassurance in Christ when we are obedient but the blessings we expect do not come right away? For more on this subject, you could review together insights from Elder Dale G. Renlund's message "Abound with Blessings" (Ensign or Liahona, May 2019, 70–73).</li>
</ul>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 131:1–4; 132:3–25</heading>
<heading>Heavenly Father made it possible for families to be eternal.</heading>
<ul>
<li>What might we say to a friend who asks, "Why are marriage and family so important in your church?" Class members could think about how they would answer that question as they read Doctrine and Covenants 131:1–4; 132:3–25; or Elder Dieter F. Uchtdorf's words in "Additional Resources." How do these truths affect the way we live?</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>Family relationships can be made eternal through temple ordinances.</graphics-caption>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 132:1–2, 29–40</heading>
<heading>Plural marriage is acceptable to God only when He commands it.</heading>
<ul>
<li>If class members have questions about plural marriage, help them see that Joseph Smith and other early Saints had questions too. Encourage them to find the question Joseph asked the Lord in Doctrine and Covenants 132:1 and the answer he received in verses 29–40 (see also Jacob 2:27, 30). To help class members learn about ways they can find answers to their gospel questions, it might help to review together "Answering Gospel Questions" at topics.ChurchofJesusChrist.org. Maybe class members could share how they have sought answers to gospel questions and how they remain faithful even when some of their questions remain unanswered.</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>Family is "the order of heaven."</heading>
<p>President Dieter F. Uchtdorf taught:
"I am grateful that I belong to a church that values marriage and family. Members of The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints are known throughout the world for having some of the finest marriages and families you can find. I believe this is, in part, due to the precious truth restored by Joseph Smith that marriages and families are meant to be eternal. Families are not just meant to make things run more smoothly here on earth and to be cast off when we get to heaven. Rather, they are the order of heaven. They are an echo of a celestial pattern and an emulation of God's eternal family.
"But strong marriage and family relationships do not happen just because we are members of the Church. They require constant, intentional work. The doctrine of eternal families must inspire us to dedicate our best efforts to saving and enriching our marriages and families" ("In Praise of Those Who Save," Ensign or Liahona, May 2016, 77).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Create a safe environment.</b>"Encourage [class members] to help you establish an open, loving, and respectful environment so that everyone feels safe sharing their experiences, questions, and testimonies" (Teaching in the Savior's Way, 15).</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<graphics-caption>The Bridegroom Cometh, by Elizabeth Gibbons</graphics-caption>
<heading>NOVEMBER 15–21</heading>
<heading>Doctrine and Covenants 133–134</heading>
<heading>"PREPARE YE FOR THE COMING OF THE BRIDEGROOM"</heading>
<p>What truths in Doctrine and Covenants 133–34 do you feel will help your class the most? Prayerfully consider their needs as you study this week.</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>You could write the word<i>hearken</i>on the board and invite class members to write next to it verses from Doctrine and Covenants 133–34 that they believe we need to hearken to in our day. Ask them to share their thoughts about those verses. (Help class members focus on doctrinal principles rather than political views.)</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 133:1–19; 37–39</heading>
<heading>The Lord wants us to prepare for His Second Coming.</heading>
<ul>
<li>How will you help your class understand why it is important to sanctify ourselves in order to help others prepare for the Savior's Second Coming? You could invite class members to review Doctrine and Covenants 133:1–19, 37–39 and make two lists: one list of the Lord's counsel about how to sanctify ourselves and another of counsel about how to prepare the world for the Savior's return. What does it mean, in a spiritual sense, to "go out from Babylon" (verse 5) and "flee unto Zion"? (verse 12). For more about what sanctification means, see "Sanctification" in Guide to the Scriptures (scriptures.ChurchofJesusChrist.org).</li>
</ul>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 133:19–53</heading>
<heading>The Second Coming will be joyful for the righteous.</heading>
<ul>
<li>In their scripture study at home, members of your class may have found meaningful passages in this section that cause them to look forward to the Savior's Second Coming. Invite them to share these passages. You could also invite the class to search verses 19–53 in pairs, looking for reasons to look forward to the Second Coming of Jesus Christ. As class members share what they found, encourage them to talk about how the Savior has "redeemed them, and [borne] them, and carried them" (verse 53). This might be a good opportunity to sing together a hymn about the Savior's redeeming power, such as "Savior, Redeemer of My Soul" (Hymns, no. 112). What other "songs of everlasting joy" (verse 33) help us feel the "loving kindness of [our] Lord"? (verse 52).</li>
</ul>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 134</heading>
<heading>"Governments were instituted of God for the benefit of man."</heading>
<ul>
<li>To help class members learn from Doctrine and Covenants 134, you could put questions like these in a container or on the board: How does God want governments to benefit His children? What should we do if earthly laws contradict heavenly laws? What are our duties and responsibilities as citizens? Invite class members to choose a question and use section 134 to create an answer. Encourage class members to avoid talking about specific political issues or views.</li>
<li>The freedom to "worship how, where, or what [we] may" (Articles of Faith 1:11) is a privilege that the Lord wants everyone to have. If you feel it would benefit your class to talk about the principle of religious freedom, consider reading together Doctrine and Covenants 134:4, 7, 9. What do these verses teach us about a government's role in protecting religious freedom? How can we promote religious freedom for others and ourselves? Class members may find insights to help answer this question in "Additional Resources."</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>Cornerstones of religious freedom.</heading>
<p>Elder Robert D. Hales taught:
"There are four cornerstones of religious freedom that we as Latter-day Saints must rely upon and protect.
"The first is freedom to believe. No one should be criticized, persecuted, or attacked by individuals, or governments either, for what he or she believes about God. . . .
"The second cornerstone of religious liberty is the freedom to share our faith and our beliefs with others. . . . As parents, full-time missionaries, and member missionaries, we rely on religious freedom in order to teach the Lord's doctrine in our families and throughout the world.
"The third cornerstone of religious liberty is the freedom to form a religious organization, a church, to worship peacefully with others. The eleventh article of faith declares, 'We claim the privilege of worshiping Almighty God according to the dictates of our own conscience, and allow all men the same privilege, let them worship how, where, or what they may.'. . .
"The fourth cornerstone of religious liberty is the freedom to live our faith — free exercise of faith not just in the home and chapel but also in public places" ("Preserving Agency, Protecting Religious Freedom," Ensign or Liahona, May 2015, 112).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Teach the "why."</b>"If [class members] understand Heavenly Father's eternal plan for the happiness of His children, the reasons for gospel principles and commandments become clearer and the motivation to obey increases" (Teaching in the Savior's Way, 20).</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<graphics-caption>Carthage Jail</graphics-caption>
<heading>NOVEMBER 22–28</heading>
<heading>Doctrine and Covenants 135–136</heading>
<heading>HE "HAS SEALED HIS MISSION AND HIS WORKS WITH HIS OWN BLOOD"</heading>
<p>As you read sections 135–36, the Holy Ghost may give you insights that might be helpful to members of your class. The ideas in this outline could also spark ideas you could use as you teach.</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>Here's one way to invite class members to share their thoughts about sections 135–36. Invite them to imagine that they could talk to a member of the Church from 1844, someone who is distraught about the death of Joseph Smith and worried about what it might mean for the Church. What could we share from these sections that might help this person?</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 135; 136:37–39</heading>
<heading>Joseph and Hyrum Smith sealed their testimonies with their blood.</heading>
<ul>
<li>How did the sacrifices of Joseph and Hyrum Smith "seal" their testimonies? Maybe class members could ponder this question as they review Doctrine and Covenants 135; 136:37–39. They could then share any insights they receive. They could also share their feelings about Joseph's and Hyrum's willingness to give their lives for the truth. While we may not be asked to die for the truth, how can our lives be like a "seal" for our testimonies?</li>
</ul>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 135:3</heading>
<heading>Joseph Smith has done more for our salvation than anyone except Jesus Christ.</heading>
<ul>
<li>How can you help class members understand what Joseph Smith has done for their salvation? You could write on the board<i>Because of what the Lord revealed through Joseph Smith, I . . .</i>and then invite class members to think of ways to complete this sentence. They could begin by searching Doctrine and Covenants 135:3 for things that Joseph Smith did to help us gain salvation. Consider inviting class members to share their feelings about Joseph Smith and what the Lord revealed through him.</li>
<li>Another way to help class members think about Joseph Smith's mission is to invite them to write a brief obituary or eulogy for him. You might want to discuss important events or accomplishments from his life that they could include. What do they find in Doctrine and Covenants 135 that they could mention? What could they say in their eulogy to help others strengthen their faith in Joseph Smith's divine mission?</li>
<li>Many truths about Jesus Christ and His Atonement were revealed through Joseph Smith — truths that contributed to the salvation of all men and women. To help class members recognize these contributions, you could display a picture of Jesus Christ and ask a few class members to share a favorite verse about Jesus Christ from the scriptures revealed through Joseph Smith: the Book of Mormon, Doctrine and Covenants, and Pearl of Great Price. How do these scriptures help us understand and draw closer to the Savior? How do the truths in these verses contribute to our salvation?</li>
</ul>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 136</heading>
<heading>We can accomplish the Lord's will as we follow His counsel.</heading>
<ul>
<li>This week's outline in<i>Come, Follow Me—For Individuals and Families</i>suggests that class members look for counsel in Doctrine and Covenants 136 that could help them turn a trial into a spiritual experience. You might ask class members to share any counsel they found. You could also ask them to search this section looking for counsel that can help us accomplish the Lord's will in our day, just as it helped the Saints in their "journeyings to the West" (verse 1).</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>Winter Quarters, by Greg Olsen</graphics-caption>
<ul>
<li>It might be fun for your class to create a poster like those found in Church magazines about one of the verses in section 136. Working in pairs or individually, class members could begin by searching the verses for a truth that stands out to them. They could then create a simple poster that shows how this truth, taught in 1847, can still help us today.</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>Related Music</heading>
<p>Singing the following hymns or watching the videos could invite the Holy Ghost or inspire a discussion about the work of the Prophet Joseph Smith and the sacrifices of the Saints who continued after him.</p>
<p>"A Poor Wayfaring Man of Grief" (Hymns, no. 29). While in Carthage Jail, Joseph Smith asked John Taylor to sing this hymn.</p>
<p>"Praise to the Man" (Hymns, no. 27; video, thetabernaclechoir.org/videos/praise-to-the-man-mormon-tabernacle-choir). The text of this hymn was written as a tribute to Joseph Smith.</p>
<p>"Come, Come, Ye Saints" (Hymns, no. 30; video, thetabernaclechoir.org/videos/come-come-ye-saints-mormon-tabernacle-choir).</p>
<p>"Faith in Every Footstep" (video, thetabernaclechoir.org/videos/faith-in-every-footstep).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Testify of true doctrine.</b>You can share your testimony about doctrinal truths throughout the lesson, not just at the end. As you do, the Holy Ghost will confirm the truth of the doctrine in the hearts of those you teach. (See Teaching in the Savior's Way, 21.)</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<graphics-caption>Joseph sees his father, mother, and brother in the celestial kingdom. Joseph Smith's Vision of the Celestial Kingdom, by Robert T. Barrett.</graphics-caption>
<heading>NOVEMBER 29–DECEMBER 5</heading>
<heading>Doctrine and Covenants 137–138</heading>
<heading>"THE VISION OF THE REDEMPTION OF THE DEAD"</heading>
<p>President Dallin H. Oaks taught: "We can all wonder privately about circumstances in the spirit world. . . . But let us not teach or use as official doctrine what does not meet the standards of official doctrine" ("Trust in the Lord," Ensign or Liahona, Nov. 2019, 28). Ensure that your discussion is founded on the scriptures and words of the prophets.</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>There are many inspiring doctrinal truths found in Doctrine and Covenants 137–38. Invite class members to list some of them. Then you could spend a few minutes reviewing their lists as a class and talking about why these truths are important to them. Did anyone learn something from these sections that they had not previously understood?</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 137; 138:32–37</heading>
<heading>Every soul will have the opportunity to choose celestial glory.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Many of us know people who did not have the chance to accept the gospel in this life — including those who die as children. Invite class members to share a truth they find in section 137 that helps them understand God's plan for these individuals. What truths do we find in Doctrine and Covenants 138:32–37 that add to our understanding of God's plan? Class members could share how these truths make them feel about Heavenly Father, His plan of salvation, and the Atonement of Jesus Christ. The statement in "Additional Resources" may be helpful to your discussion.</li>
</ul>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 138:1–11, 25–30</heading>
<heading>Reading and pondering the scriptures prepares us to receive revelation.</heading>
<ul>
<li>The experience Joseph F. Smith described in Doctrine and Covenants 138:1–11, 25–30 helps us understand how we can prepare ourselves to receive revelation. Perhaps class members could work together to identify what they learn about revelation from these verses. You might ask class members to share how reading and pondering the scriptures has prepared them to receive revelation (see also Joseph Smith—History 1:11–12).</li>
<li>President M. Russell Ballard's message "The Vision of the Redemption of the Dead" (Ensign or Liahona, Nov. 2018, 71–74) describes Joseph F. Smith's "lifetime of preparation to receive this remarkable revelation [Doctrine and Covenants 138]." If members of your class read President Ballard's message this week, encourage them to share something that impressed them. Or you could read portions of the message as a class. What impresses us about President Smith's life and his character? What can we learn from his example?</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>Joseph F. Smith, by Albert E. Salzbrenner</graphics-caption>
<heading>DOCTRINE AND COVENANTS 138:12–60</heading>
<heading>The work of salvation continues after death.</heading>
<ul>
<li>To help class members discover truths in Doctrine and Covenants 138:12–60, you could provide them with several questions about the spirit world that are answered in these verses. For example:<i>What did the Savior do while He was in the spirit world? Who are the Lord's messengers, and what is their message?</i>Class members could select one or more of these questions and work in small groups to search for answers. Then they could share with each other the truths they found. What difference do these truths make in our lives?</li>
<li>What would we say to somebody who asks, "What happens when we die?" What would we share from Doctrine and Covenants 138:12–60 that could help answer this question? (see also Alma 40:11–15).</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>God's plan provides a way for all of His children to accept the gospel.</heading>
<p>President Henry B. Eyring taught:
"Only a very small minority of God's children obtain during this life a complete understanding of God's plan, along with access to the priesthood ordinances and covenants that make the Savior's atoning power fully operative in our lives. . . .
"Some may consider this unfair. They may even take it as evidence that there is no plan, no specific requirements for salvation — feeling that a just, loving God would not create a plan that is available to such a small proportion of His children. Others might conclude that God must have determined in advance which of His children He would save and made the gospel available to them, while those who never heard the gospel simply were not «chosen.»
"But you and I know, because of the truths restored through the Prophet Joseph Smith, that God's plan is much more loving and just than that. Our Heavenly Father is anxious to gather and bless all of His family. While He knows that not all of them will choose to be gathered, His plan gives each of His children the opportunity to accept or reject His invitation" ("Gathering the Family of God," Ensign or Liahona, May 2017, 20–21).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Use the words of prophets.</b>"The scriptures and words of latter-day prophets and apostles are the source of the truths we teach. At every opportunity, inspire those you teach to turn to the word of God for guidance" (Teaching in the Savior's Way, 21).</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<graphics-caption>To All Worthy Male Members, by Emma Allebes</graphics-caption>
<heading>DECEMBER 6–12</heading>
<heading>The Articles of Faith and Official Declarations 1 and 2</heading>
<heading>"WE BELIEVE"</heading>
<p>Prayerfully read the Articles of Faith and Official Declarations 1 and 2, and seek the inspiration of the Holy Ghost as you plan a meaningful learning experience for class members on Sunday.</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>You could invite class members to complete the following statement: "I am glad I read the scriptures this week because. . ."</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>THE ARTICLES OF FAITH</heading>
<heading>The Articles of Faith contain foundational truths of the restored gospel.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Here's a way to help class members share what they found especially meaningful in the Articles of Faith: You could write the numbers 1 through 13 on the board and ask class members to write next to the numbers something they learned from the corresponding article of faith. What difference do these truths make in our relationship with our Heavenly Parents and Jesus Christ? Perhaps class members can share how the Articles of Faith have enhanced their gospel study or helped them share the gospel with others.</li>
</ul>
<heading>ARTICLES OF FAITH 1:9; OFFICIAL DECLARATIONS 1 AND 2</heading>
<heading>The Church of Jesus Christ is guided by revelation.</heading>
<ul>
<li>Why is continuing revelation important to us? Invite class members to share their feelings about this question. Class members could also discuss how the principle of continuing revelation relates to Official Declarations 1 and 2. (This week's outline in Come, Follow Me—For Individuals and Families suggests helpful resources related to these revelations.) What do we learn from Official Declarations 1 and 2 about the role of revelation in guiding the Church? (see also Articles of Faith 1:9 and the statement by President Gordon B. Hinckley in "Additional Resources"). What other examples of continuing revelation can class members think of? How do these revelations influence our lives and help us build Heavenly Father's kingdom?</li>
<li>Consider inviting class members to review Official Declarations 1 and 2 and to share something from these revelations that might help someone who is struggling to accept a recent policy change, revelation, or Church doctrine. How have class members learned to trust in God when they are struggling with something in the Church? How did their study this week strengthen their faith that the Lord is leading His Church? The insights from President Dieter F. Uchtdorf in "Additional Resources" could also help.</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>Wilford Woodruff, by H. E. Peterson</graphics-caption>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>"The Spirit of God was there."</heading>
<p>President Gordon B. Hinckley was serving as a member of the Quorum of the Twelve Apostles when the revelation described in Official Declaration 2 was received. Years later he described his experience:
"There was a hallowed and sanctified atmosphere in the room. For me, it felt as if a conduit opened between the heavenly throne and the kneeling, pleading prophet of God who was joined by his Brethren. The Spirit of God was there. And by the power of the Holy Ghost there came to that prophet an assurance that the thing for which he prayed was right, that the time had come, and that now the wondrous blessings of the priesthood should be extended to worthy men everywhere regardless of lineage.
"Every man in that circle, by the power of the Holy Ghost, knew the same thing.
"It was a quiet and sublime occasion. . . . No voice audible to our physical ears was heard. But the voice of the Spirit whispered with certainty into our minds and our very souls" ("Priesthood Restoration," Ensign, Oct. 1988, 70).</p>
<heading>"It's natural to have questions."</heading>
<p>President Dieter F. Uchtdorf said the following to those who have doubts about Church history or doctrine:
"It's natural to have questions — the acorn of honest inquiry has often sprouted and matured into a great oak of understanding. There are few members of the Church who, at one time or another, have not wrestled with serious or sensitive questions. One of the purposes of the Church is to nurture and cultivate the seed of faith — even in the sometimes sandy soil of doubt and uncertainty. Faith is to hope for things which are not seen but which are true.
"Therefore, my dear brothers and sisters — my dear friends — please, first doubt your doubts before you doubt your faith. We must never allow doubt to hold us prisoner and keep us from the divine love, peace, and gifts that come through faith in the Lord Jesus Christ" ("Come, Join with Us," Ensign or Liahona, Nov. 2013, 23; see also Lawrence E. Corbridge, "Stand Forever" [Brigham Young University devotional, Jan. 22, 2019], speeches.byu.edu).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>It's OK to say, "I don't know."</b>While you should try your best to help class members answer their questions about the gospel, the Lord doesn't expect you to know everything. When you don't know how to answer something, admit it. Then point your learners to revealed doctrine, and bear sincere testimony of what you do know. (See Teaching in the Savior's Way, 24.) "It was a quiet and sublime occasion. . . . No voice audible to our physical ears was heard. But 101</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<heading>DECEMBER 13–19</heading>
<heading>The Family: A Proclamation to the World</heading>
<heading>"THE FAMILY IS CENTRAL TO THE CREATOR'S PLAN"</heading>
<p>As you study "The Family: A Proclamation to the World" this week, consider the truths that will support class members in their efforts to strengthen their homes and families.</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>To encourage class members to share what they learned this week from their study of the family proclamation, you could ask them to choose any paragraph and summarize in one sentence what that paragraph teaches.</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>"The family is central to the Creator's plan."</heading>
<ul>
<li>The Church is known for its emphasis on families, and the family proclamation reveals the doctrinal reasons for that emphasis. To encourage a discussion about this, you could invite class members to imagine that someone asked them why the Church emphasizes families so much. What truths from the proclamation could we share to answer the person's question?</li>
<li>One reason the family proclamation is so important is that it reaffirms truths that are under attack in our day. What truths in the proclamation help us not be deceived by false ideas about families in today's world? How do these truths affect the choices we make? The statement by President Dallin H. Oaks in "Additional Resources" may be helpful in answering this question.</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>Parents should raise their children in love and righteousness.</graphics-caption>
<heading>"Happiness in family life is most likely to be achieved when founded upon the teachings of the Lord Jesus Christ."</heading>
<ul>
<li><p>Discussing the principles in paragraphs six and seven of the family proclamation could help members of your class find greater happiness in their family relationships. Consider listing the principles on the board and inviting class members to choose a principle to discuss in pairs. They could use questions like these to guide their discussions: What examples of this principle have we seen in family life? How does living this principle lead to happiness in our families? How does living this principle help to make the Savior the foundation of our family life? What scriptures might help our families understand this principle better? (Class members could find scriptures using the Topical Guide or Guide to the Scriptures [scriptures.ChurchofJesusChrist.org].) Each pair could then share with the class what they learned.</p>
<p>Emphasize that regardless of our current family circumstances, we can strive to build an eternal family on the foundation of the Savior and His gospel.</p></li>
</ul>
<heading>"We call upon responsible citizens. . . to promote those measures designed to maintain and strengthen the family."</heading>
<ul>
<li>How can you help members of your class understand their responsibility to uphold the truths in the family proclamation? To begin the discussion, you might discuss what class members learn from the title of the proclamation. What is a proclamation? What qualified the First Presidency and Council of the Twelve Apostles to issue a proclamation to the world regarding families? Class members could list what they consider to be the main messages of the proclamation (encourage them to cite specific passages). Then they could discuss ways to promote these messages in their community or nation. Sister Bonnie L. Oscarson's message "Defenders of the Family Proclamation" contains examples you could review together as a class (Ensign or Liahona, May 2015, 14–17). You could also watch the video "Defenders of the Faith" (ChurchofJesusChrist.org).</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>Families in God's plan.</heading>
<p>President Dallin H. Oaks taught:
"Latter-day Saints who understand God's plan of salvation have a unique worldview that helps them see the reason for God's commandments, the unchangeable nature of His required ordinances, and the fundamental role of our Savior, Jesus Christ. Our Savior's Atonement reclaims us from death and, subject to our repentance, saves us from sin. With that worldview, Latter-day Saints have distinctive priorities and practices and are blessed with the strength to endure the frustrations and pains of mortal life. . . .
"The gospel plan each family should follow to prepare for eternal life and exaltation is outlined in the Church's 1995 proclamation, 'The Family: A Proclamation to the World.' Its declarations are, of course, visibly different from some current laws, practices, and advocacy of the world in which we live. In our day, the differences most evident are cohabitation without marriage, same-sex marriage, and the raising of children in such relationships. Those who do not believe in or aspire to exaltation and are most persuaded by the ways of the world consider this family proclamation as just a statement of policy that should be changed. In contrast, Latter-day Saints affirm that the family proclamation defines the kind of family relationships where the most important part of our eternal development can occur" ("The Plan and the Proclamation," Ensign or Liahona, Nov. 2017, 29).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Live the gospel with all your heart.</b>"Power comes when a teacher has done all that he can to prepare, not just the individual lesson, but in keeping his life in tune with the Spirit" (Boyd K. Packer, Teach Ye Diligently [1975], 306).</p>
</chapter>
<chapter type="lesson">
<graphics-caption>Nativity in Copper and Umber, by J. Kirk Richards</graphics-caption>
<heading>DECEMBER 20–26</heading>
<heading>Christmas</heading>
<heading>THE MATCHLESS GIFT OF GOD'S DIVINE SON</heading>
<p>Remember that class members' most important and effective gospel learning takes place in their homes. As you prepare to teach, consider how your Sunday School class can reinforce their personal and family study.</p>
<heading>Invite Sharing</heading>
<p>How has studying "The Living Christ" (ChurchofJesusChrist.org) this week blessed members of your class? You might share these words from President Jean B. Bingham, Relief Society General President, and then invite class members to talk about any similar experiences they've had: "As I have studied the life and teachings of Jesus Christ with more focus and committed «The Living Christ» to memory, my gratitude and love for our Savior have increased. Each sentence of that inspired document contains a sermon and has enhanced my understanding of His divine roles and earthly mission. What I have learned and felt through this period of study and reflection confirms that Jesus truly is the light, the life, and the hope of the world'" ("That Your Joy Might Be Full," Ensign or Liahona, Nov. 2017, 85).</p>
<heading>Teach the Doctrine</heading>
<heading>"None other has had so profound an influence."</heading>
<ul>
<li>Class members could read the first paragraph of "The Living Christ" and share their thoughts about why Jesus Christ's influence has been more profound than any other person's. What other statements in "The Living Christ" support this claim? Invite class members to share how He has influenced them personally. The video "Why We Need a Savior" (ChurchofJesusChrist.org) can supplement your discussion.</li>
<li>Have class members ever had to explain to someone of another culture why they celebrate Christmas? Perhaps they could share their experiences. Or you could invite class members to imagine they were asked this question by someone who is unfamiliar with Christianity. How might we respond to this question? Encourage class members to review "The Living Christ" with this question in mind, and invite a few to share their thoughts. As a class, you could also read Luke 2:10–14 or sing a hymn that expresses the joy of Christmas (such as "Joy to the World," Hymns, no. 201) and talk about why the birth of Christ brings "great joy." What can we do to "receive [our] King"?</li>
</ul>
<graphics-caption>Light of the World, by Howard Lyon</graphics-caption>
<heading>"God be thanked for [His] matchless gift."</heading>
<ul>
<li>In "The Living Christ," the Apostles refer to the Savior as a "gift" from our Heavenly Father. To help class members learn more about this gift, you could write on the board<i>Through Jesus Christ, God gives us the gift of . . .</i>and invite class members to suggest ways to complete this sentence, based on what they read in "The Living Christ" and the statement by President Russell M. Nelson in "Additional Resources." How do we receive these gifts? You could invite class members to choose one of these gifts and work to receive that gift more fully.</li>
</ul>
<heading>Additional Resources</heading>
<heading>Gifts the Savior offers.</heading>
<p>Speaking at Christmastime, President Russell M. Nelson listed four gifts that the Savior gives to all who are willing to receive them:
"First, He gave you and me an unlimited capacity to<i>love.</i>That includes the capacity to love the unlovable and those who<i>not</i>only do not love you but presently persecute and despitefully use you. . . .
"With the Savior's help, we can learn to love as He loved. . . .
"A second gift the Savior offers you is the ability to<i>forgive.</i>Through His infinite Atonement, you can forgive those who have hurt you and who may never accept responsibility for their cruelty to you. . .
"A third gift from the Savior is that of<i>repentance.</i>This gift is not always well understood. . . . Repentance is a resplendent gift. It is a process never to be feared. It is a gift for us to receive with joy and to use — even embrace — day after day as we seek to become more like our Savior. . . .
"A fourth gift from our Savior is actually a promise — a promise of<i>life everlasting.</i>. . . Eternal life is the kind and quality of life that Heavenly Father and His Beloved Son live. When the Father offers us everlasting life, He is saying in essence, «If you choose to follow my Son — if your<i>desire</i>is<i>really</i>to become more like Him — then in time you may live as we live and preside over worlds and kingdoms as we do.»
"These four unique gifts will bring us more and more joy as we accept them. They were made possible because Jehovah condescended to come to earth as the baby Jesus" ("Four Gifts That Jesus Christ Offers to You" [First Presidency Christmas devotional, Dec. 2, 2018], broadcasts.ChurchofJesusChrist.org).</p>
<heading>Improving Our Teaching</heading>
<p><b>Prepare yourself spiritually.</b>"Powerful gospel teaching means not just preparing a lesson but preparing ourselves. . . . Effective gospel teachers — before they think about filling class time — focus on filling their hearts with the Holy Ghost" (Teaching in the Savior's Way, 12).</p>
</chapter>
</text>
